- We're talking about a society that was right in the middle
我们谈论的是一个处于 中间地带的社会
of one of the main corridors of empire building and new religions
帝国扩张和新兴宗教 的主要通道之一
in the world. This is the most dangerous neighborhood that you can possibly live in.
在世界上。这是你所能 居住的最危险的街区。
- 26 emperors were murdered in a period of 50 years.
- 50年间，共有26位 皇帝被谋杀。
- Yes. It's tremendous instability.
- 是的。它极不稳定。
- Almost all were of these emperors were generals, and almost all were
这些皇帝几乎都是将军 ，而且几乎都是
murdered by their men. So civil war was the norm, hyperinflation, economic crash,
被他们的人杀害。所以内战、恶性 通货膨胀、经济崩溃成了常态。
plus there's a plague. There's just a lot of chaos.
此外，还有瘟疫 。现场一片混乱。
- Here's why I don't think the Eastern Roman Empire is a military
这就是我不认为东罗马帝国 是一个军事帝国的原因。
dictatorship. Even though, again, the emperors control the armies,
专政。尽管如此，皇帝们 仍然控制着军队，
and the armies themselves will often have a say in,
军队本身往往也 会有发言权。
Who becomes emperor, like through the civil wars that we mentioned. The reason
谁会成为皇帝，就像我们之前 提到的内战那样。原因
why I don't think it's a military dictatorship is because
我不认为它是军事 独裁政权的原因是：
they almost never, very, very, very rarely use the army as an instrument of social
他们几乎从不、非常、非常、 极少将军队用作社会工具。
control. Sometimes these eunuchs were extremely competent
控制。有时这些太监 能力非常强。
like Narses, Justinian's general, who defeated the Goths in Italy in this
就像查士丁尼的将军纳尔塞斯一样 ，他在意大利击败了哥特人。
massive battle. Like, this guy was a total hardass. And he's this little
大规模战斗。这家伙简直是 个十足的硬汉。他这么小
old man. He was- he was very old, and he was tiny, and he was a eunuch, and the Goths
老人。他——他年纪很大，个子很 小，而且是个太监，哥特人
laughed at him, but he had the last laugh.
他曾嘲笑他，但他笑到了最后。
- The following is a conversation with Anthony Kaldellis, a
以下是与安东尼·卡尔德利斯（Anthony Kaldellis） 的对话，他是一位……
historian of the Eastern Roman Empire, also known as the Byzantine Empire.
研究东罗马帝国（又称拜占庭 帝国）的历史学家。
This is a Lex Fridman podcast. To support it, please check out our sponsors in the
这是 Lex Fridman 的播客。为了支持 我们，请查看我们的赞助商。
description, where you can also find links to contact me,
描述部分还包含 联系我的链接，
ask questions, give feedback, and so on. And
提出问题、提供 反馈等等。和
now, dear friends, here's Anthony Kaldellis.
亲爱的朋友们，现在请出安东尼 ·卡尔德利斯。
You've described that the Byzantine Empire is the Roman
你曾描述过拜占庭 帝国是罗马帝国
Empire, that calling it the Byzantine Empire is an invention of
称其为拜占庭帝国 是人为捏造的。
historians writing long after the empire has collapsed,
历史学家在帝国崩溃很久之后 才撰写这些历史，
that the people of that time considered themselves Romans, and that
当时的人们认为 自己是罗马人，而且
the so-called Byzantine Empire never actually existed, that it was,
所谓的拜占庭帝国实际上从未存在 过，事实就是如此。
in every legal and cultural sense, the Roman Empire
从法律和文化的各个方面 来看，罗马帝国
continuing unbroken. So let's get our terms right in the grand historical context.
持续不断。所以，让我们在宏大的 历史背景下厘清我们的术语。
What is the Byzantine Empire, and why should we just call it the Roman Empire?
什么是拜占庭帝国？为什么我们 应该直接称其为罗马帝国？
- So Lex, the burden of proof is on those who would assert that what we've been
所以莱克斯，举证责任在于那些声称 我们所做的事情属实的人。
calling the Byzantine Empire is something other-
称拜占庭帝国 是另一回事——
... than the Roman Empire, because all of our sources are very clear about this. And we've known about
比罗马帝国还要强大，因为我们所有的史料都 对此有非常明确的记载。我们早就知道了
this. We've always known about it. It's almost a form of cognitive dissonance, right?
这。我们一直都知道这件事。 这几乎是一种认知失调，对吧？
It's like when you know something is the case, but you carry on as if it's not.
就像你知道某件事是真的，但 你却装作不是真的一样。
So the Eastern Roman Empire, this is the direct continuation
所以东罗马帝国，这 是它的直接延续。
of the ancient Roman Empire in the East, right? Everybody knows the Western Empire
是东方的古罗马帝国，对吧 ？人人都知道西罗马帝国
fell in the fifth century.
五世纪时陷落。
And for many conceptions of Western history, that was sufficient. Like, that's when
对于许多西方历史观念而言，这就 足够了。比如，就是那时候
we just called it. The Roman Empire fell in the fifth century.
我们刚才就预言到了。 罗马帝国在五世纪灭亡。
And we kinda, yeah, we kinda know that the eastern half survived, but we don't wanna include
我们大概知道东半部幸存了 下来，但我们不想把它算进去。
that in our cultural genealogy. And so we kinda pretend that it became
那在我们文化谱系中。所以 我们假装它变成了
something else. But in fact, it called itself the Roman Empire. Its subjects were
别的什么。但实际上，它自称 为罗马帝国。其研究对象是
Roman citizens. They called themselves Romans all the way down through to the end and
罗马公民。他们自称罗马人 ，直到最后都是如此。
beyond. So there are a number of reasons why Western Europeans wanted to
超过。因此，西欧人想要 ……的原因有很多。
think that the Eastern Empire is something different, and those reasons have
我认为东罗马帝国有所不同 ，而这些原因……
created these models where
创建这些模型的地方
They were, they called it Empire of the Greeks for 1,000 years, then they switched to Byzantine
他们称之为希腊帝国，持续了一千 年，然后改称为拜占庭帝国。
Empire for very political reasons. Now that's collapsing.
帝国建立是出于非常政治 的原因。现在它正在崩溃。
So we're now moving into a phase where we have the long Roman Empire. We,
所以我们现在正进入一个漫长 的罗马帝国时期。我们，
we recognize that the history of the Roman state, the Roman polity,
我们认识到罗马国家的历史 ，罗马政体的历史，
is something that lasts an extraordinarily long time.
是持续时间异常 长的事物。
Very unique almost in history, from antiquity,
从古代到现在，几乎在 历史上都是独一无二的。
like the archaic period, down to the 15th century.
从古代一直 到15世纪。
- I think it would be really nice to actually look
我觉得如果能亲眼看看 就太好了。
just for a brief moment at the grand scale of the,
仅仅是在这宏大的规模 下短暂的一刻，
the full Roman state as it lasted for over 2,200 years.
完整的罗马国家， 持续了2200多年。
- Yeah.
- 是的。
- So its founding, 753 BC, to let's say the fall of Constantinople in 1453 AD.
所以，从公元前 753 年建国，到 公元 1453 年君士坦丁堡陷落。
So can we try to give a big picture overview of everything that happened?
那么我们能否尝试对所有发生 的事情做一个全面的概述？
- Okay, so first we have a period of the kings. This is almost legendary, from
- 好的，首先我们来看国王时期 。这几乎堪称传奇，来自
like the eighth century BC down to around 510 BC.
例如公元前八世纪到 公元前510年左右。
So this is when Rome is ruled by a series of local kings.
所以，罗马当时是由一系列 地方国王统治的。
The kings are expelled, and the republic, or what we call the republic,
国王们被驱逐，共和国， 或者我们今天所说的共和国，
is instituted, and this is a regime that's governed by mostly
已经建立，这是一个主要 由……统治的政权。
an aristocracy, but with cooperation from the
一个贵族阶层，但得到 了……的合作
people of Rome. In various ways, the arrangements change over the
罗马人。随着时间的推移 ，各种安排会发生变化。
centuries. So that lasts for about five centuries.
几个世纪。所以这种情况 持续了大约五个世纪。
And then we have the end of the republic in the era of Julius Caesar and
然后，随着尤利乌斯·凯撒时代的 到来，共和国走向终结。
Augustus Caesar, when the civil wars lead to the creation of an imperial monarchy...
奥古斯都·凯撒，当内战最终 导致帝国君主制的建立……
...right, under Augustus. So that's, we date that roughly either,
……没错，在奥古斯都统治时期。所以，我们 大致可以确定，那段时间是：
yeah, 27 BC, something like that. And thereafter, it is an
对，公元前27年左右 。此后，它就变成了
imperial monarchy for the next millennium and a half.
接下来一千五百年将 实行帝国君主制。
Very broadly, we can divide that into two phases, one where the
总的来说，我们可以将其分为 两个阶段，第一阶段是……
center of power is in Rome, and one where it's in Constantinople.
权力中心在罗马，或者 在君士坦丁堡。
And, you know, we can debate the dates of when that transition takes place.
而且，我们还可以讨论 过渡期的具体日期。
These big transitions usually take place over long periods of time. They're not, like,
这些重大转变通常需要很长时间才 能完成。他们不是那种……
very sudden. So that's the big picture. Kings, republic, imperial monarchy.
非常突然。这就是大致情况。君主制 、共和国、帝国君主制。
- The Roman Kingdom, the Roman Republic, the Roman Empire.
罗马王国、罗马共和国 、罗马帝国。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- And then the West and East Roman Empire.
然后是西罗马帝国和东罗马帝国。
- Uh, and then maybe what are the different terms that we could be
呃，那么我们或许可以用 哪些不同的术语呢？
using for the Byzantine Empire, including Byzantium?
是指拜占庭帝国， 包括拜占庭城吗？
Is it also fair to say the Late Roman Empire?
也可以说罗马 帝国晚期吗？
- So Late Roman Empire we use for both east and west, starting
因此，我们用“晚期罗马帝国”来指代 东西罗马帝国，从……开始。
around the reign of Diocletian maybe, even a bit earlier, so during the third
大约在戴克里先统治时期，甚至可能 更早一些，也就是在第三个时期。
century AD. And that goes down to maybe the early seventh century. So that
公元世纪。那可以追溯 到七世纪初。以便
period we call Late Roman Empire. And
我们称之为罗马帝国晚期的这段时期。和
if you ask me to define its principal characteristics, it would probably
如果让我定义它的主要 特征，它大概会是
be the tax system and the administration, the bureaucracy...
无论是税收制度和行政 管理，还是官僚机构……
...of the later Roman Empire is that that comes from mostly
……后期罗马帝国 的……主要来源于
Diocletian and Constantine's reforms.
戴克里先和君士坦丁的改革。
- And Diocletian was in the 3rd century.
而戴克里先生活在公元3世纪。
- Yes, 284 to 305 AD. Yes. A very important reformer.
- 是的，公元284年至305年。是的。 一位非常重要的改革家。
- And we'll talk about it, but let's just do this whirlwind, and hopefully there'll be
我们会讨论这件事，但先让我们快速 推进一下，希望会有所进展。
automagical images somewhere overlaid, but-
自动生成的图像叠加 在某处，但是——
- Okay.
- 好的。
- So in 753 BC, Rome, a small city state, is founded, and in 509 BC, the kings are
因此，公元前753年，罗马这个小城邦 建立；公元前509年，国王们……
overthrown, and the Roman Republic is born. 390 BC, the Gauls sack Rome, and this, I
罗马帝国被推翻，罗马共和国诞生。公元前 390年，高卢人洗劫了罗马，而这，我
believe, among other events throughout its history, is a formative
相信，在其历史进程中，诸多事件 之一是形成性事件。
trauma that hardens Rome's security obsession.
创伤加剧了罗马对安全 的过度重视。
It turns out, throughout its history, people want to
事实证明，纵观其 历史，人们一直都想
attack from different directions, and so you have to defend. So
来自不同方向的攻击，所以 你必须防守。所以
there's two wars, as we're actually saying off mic. There's two kinds
正如我们私下里说的那样，实际上 存在两场战争。有两种
of military operations. One is wars of conquest and expansion, and one is
军事行动。一种是征服和 扩张战争，另一种是……
more defensive. And we'll talk about how the military
更偏向防守。我们还 会讨论军队的情况。
changes throughout its history to allocate more effort to one versus the other.
在其发展历程中，它曾多次改变策略，将 更多精力分配给其中一个方面。
In 264 to 146 BC, the Punic
公元前264年至公元前146年，布匿帝国
Wars and the survival against Hannibal transform Rome into a Mediterranean
战争以及对抗汉尼拔的生存之战将 罗马转变为一个地中海国家
superpower. Then like you mentioned, Caesar in 49 to 31 BC,
超级大国。正如你提到的， 凯撒在公元前49年至公元前31年。
Caesar's crossing of the Rubicon to assassination of Caesar to
从凯撒渡过卢比孔河 到凯撒遇刺
the Battle of Actium, and then the Civil War dismantles
阿克提姆海战，以及随后 的内战，导致战乱瓦解。
the Republic and concentrates power in a single ruler, Octavian, AKA Augustus, the
共和国将权力集中在一位统治者—— 屋大维（又名奥古斯都）——手中。
first Roman emperor, let's say. Then 27 BC, Augustus founds the Principate,
比如说，第一位罗马皇帝。公元 前27年，奥古斯都建立了元首制。
really low-key monarchy. And so officially, that ends the
非常低调的君主制。 至此，正式结束。
Republic, and then that begins, 27 BC to 180 AD, the Pax Romana, which is a
共和国时期，然后从公元前27年到公元180年 ，进入罗马和平时期（Pax Romana）。
period of relative peace and stability. And a lot of the emperors we know of,
相对和平稳定的时期。我们 所知道的许多皇帝，
the sexy, popular emperors all come from that period.
那些性感、受欢迎的皇帝 都来自那个时期。
Marcus Aurelius, who I'm a big fan of, from that period. Then that
我非常欣赏那个时期的马可 ·奥勒留。然后就是
takes us to 284 AD, the guy we mentioned,
这就把我们带到了公元284年，也就是我们之前提到的那个人。
Diocletian, who rebuilds the state. Emperors drop the first citizen mask,
戴克里先重建了国家。皇帝们 抛弃了第一个公民面具，
this perception of the way, and we'll talk about this, the persona that's
这种对方式的看法，我们稍后会谈到 ，这种人格特质是……
presented by the state. 312 AD, Constantine defeats Maxentius at the
由州政府提供。公元312年，君士坦丁 在……击败马克森提乌斯。
Milvian Bridge to become the sole ruler of the western half of the empire, and then
米尔维安桥成为帝国西部地区 的唯一统治者，然后
founds Constantinople in 330 AD. East and West are split in 395 AD. Visigoths
公元330年建立君士坦丁堡。公元 395年，东西方分裂。西哥特人
sack Rome in 410 AD. The West falls at 476 AD as the last Western
公元410年洗劫罗马。西方文明于公元476年 灭亡，成为最后一个西方文明。
emperor is deposed. And then we sort of focus more on the East Roman Empire with
皇帝被废黜。然后我们更 多地关注东罗马帝国。
527. In the 6th century, Justinian's reign.
527. 公元6世纪，查士丁尼 统治时期。
In the 7th century, Heraclius defeats Persia and then loses against
公元7世纪，希拉克略击败波斯 ，随后败给了……
the Arabs. There's the Arab conquest continuing in the 7th
阿拉伯人。阿拉伯人的 征服在7世纪仍在继续。
century. In the 8th the Arab siege of Constantinople fails.
世纪。公元8世纪，阿拉伯人 围攻君士坦丁堡失败。
There's the Macedonian dynasty in that you
那里有马其顿王朝。
have an excellent book about. And then the Crusades,
有一本很棒的书。然后 是十字军东征，
and then eventually leading to Constantinople falling in 1453 AD.
最终导致君士坦丁堡 于公元 1453 年陷落。
As a person who understands the full journey of it with
作为一个完全了解 这段历程的人
a focus on East Roman history, is there obvious glaring
以东罗马历史为重点，是否存在 显而易见的显著问题？
holes or incorrect things in what I just said?
我刚才说的话有漏洞 或错误吗？
- No, nothing incorrect. I would say if you wanted to produce a sort of
- 没有，没有错误。我想说 ，如果你想制作某种……
very swift timeline of its history, it's obviously important to focus on the
鉴于其历史发展时间线非常短暂 ，显然重点应该放在……
moments when lots of territory was
很多领土都处于这样的时期
lost to foreign invaders, and these are actually three main
被外国侵略者攻陷，而这 实际上是三个主要地区。
moments. There's the Arab conquests in the
瞬间。阿拉伯人的征服……
630s. This is a decade. In a decade, that war was lost. It is the Seljuk Turk
630年代。这是十年。十年后，那 场战争失败了。这是塞尔柱突厥语
conquest of Asia Minor, modern Turkey, in the 1070s,
11世纪70年代征服小亚细亚 （今土耳其）
and that was very swift and partly reversed afterwards, but only partly.
这件事进展得非常迅速，后来部分 地被逆转了，但只是部分地逆转了。
And then there's the Fourth Crusade, 1204, when the armies from
然后是1204年的第四次十字军东征 ，当时来自世界各地的军队……
mostly France sack, conquer Constantinople, and dismember the empire as
法国主要洗劫并征服了君士坦丁堡 ，并将帝国肢解。
much as they could. It didn't last that long. The Romans managed to
尽其所能。这段关系并没有 持续太久。罗马人设法
regroup and recover but those are the three main crisis points. They are very swift,
重整旗鼓，恢复元气，但这三个是主要 的危机点。它们速度非常快，
but they cause incredible damage.
但它们会造成巨大的破坏。
For all the rest of its history, it is a state and
在其历史的其余部分 ，它是一个州，
society that is generally sort of consolidating, you know, regrouping,
社会总体上处于某种巩固 、重组的状态，你知道，
and generally engaged in slow but steady economic growth, territorial expansion on a
总体而言，经济增长缓慢但稳定 ，领土扩张也在进行中。
small scale, but steady.
规模虽小，但稳定。
Uh, so we can talk about this. It's... I think it's an important thing
嗯，我们可以谈谈这件事。 我觉得这很重要。
to keep in mind about the big picture, that the defeats were swift
要从大局出发，要意识 到这些失败来得很快。
and kind of, you know, terrible. But most of its history is one of slow growth.
而且，你知道，挺糟糕的。但它的大部分 发展历史都是缓慢增长的。
- There's some traumatic events that have a big impact, but a
有些创伤性事件 影响巨大，但
lot of the developments we'll talk about it might
我们将要讨论的许多 发展情况可能会
seem or feel like there's a particular moment
感觉或体会到某个 特定的时刻
when those developments or changes in the way the government or the military is
当政府或军队的运作方式发生 这些变化或发展时
structured arise, but really it's a gradual process.
结构化的发展是必然的，但实际上 这是一个渐进的过程。
- Exactly.
- 确切地。
- And so that's the tension we have to be constantly dancing with.
所以，这就是我们必须时刻 应对的紧张关系。
- Yeah, so as historians, this is a point of method, and it's very important. There
- 是的，作为历史学家，这是一个 方法论要点，非常重要。那里
are moments when, like, individuals with a great deal of power
有些时刻，比如，那些拥有 巨大权力的人……
make choices that impact everybody else and have, you know, long-term
做出会影响到所有人的选择 ，并且要考虑长远影响。
consequences downstream.
后续影响。
Constantine's conversion to Christianity, for example, right?
例如，君士坦丁皈依 基督教，对吧？
Not something that anybody could have or did predict. Okay.
这是任何人都无法预料 到的事情。好的。
Otherwise, most of the developments that we identify by
否则，我们所识别的 大多数发展趋势都将是……
specific dates, like you mentioned 395, the division of the eastern and the western
具体日期，比如你提到的公元395年 ，东西方分裂的年份。
empires, those are conventional dates that we use to actually capture what is in
帝国，这些是我们用来实际记录 历史事件的传统日期。
fact a much longer process. There was no split between the two
事实上，这是一个漫长的过程 。两者之间没有分裂。
halves. It was one among many
一半。它是众多案例之一。
allocations of jurisdiction to, like, one son and another son in the east and the
比如，将管辖权分配给东部的一 个儿子和另一个儿子，以及
west. The two halves were subsequently reunited, then they kind of
西方。随后两部分重新结合在一起 ，然后他们有点……
divided again among different emperors. It's just a process,
再次被不同的皇帝瓜分 。这只是这个过程，
and so we sometimes use fixed dates for what is in fact a process. Or for
因此，我们有时会用固定的日期 来表示一个过程。或者为了
76, the fall of the Western Empire, that's just the last date. It's
76年，西罗马帝国灭亡，这只 是最后一个日期。它是
actually a very long process that took decades.
实际上，这是一个耗时 数十年的漫长过程。
Right? So that's just something to keep in mind, that sometimes we're talking about processes,
正确的？所以需要记住一点， 有时候我们谈论的是过程。
sometimes we're talking about very discrete events with long-term consequences. Yeah.
有时我们谈论的是一些非常具体的事件 ，但却会产生长期的影响。是的。
- Maybe an impossible question for a Roman state that lasted
对于一个持续存在的罗马国家来说， 这或许是一个不可能回答的问题。
over 2,200 years, but is there a kind of through
超过2200年，但是否存在 某种贯穿始终的方式
line, a thread, a soul that runs through the entire history of the Roman
线，线，灵魂，贯穿 罗马的整个历史
Empire? As you said, it's a slow
帝国？正如你所说，这是一个缓慢的过程。
transformation and evolution. But if we dare call the whole
转变与演化。但如果 我们敢称整个
thing Roman, Rome, the Roman state-
罗马事物，罗马，罗马国家
- Yes
- 是的
- ... is there some aspect, some characteristics that run through the whole thing?
……是否存在贯穿始终的某些 方面或特征？
- I think so, yes. By the way, you know the metaphor of the Ship of Theseus?
- 我也这么认为。对了，你知道 忒修斯之船的比喻吗？
Okay. So in case the audience doesn't know it, this is when there's a ship, and it's, you know,
好的。所以，万一观众不知道的话，这里 指的是有一艘船的时候，你知道的，
at sea, and over time, like, every component of that ship
在海上，随着时间的推移，就 像那艘船的每一个部件一样。
is replaced with some other component, so that by the end of the story, it
被其他一些组件替换，这样 ，到故事结尾时，它
has none of the original parts. But it's, like, in a
没有一个原装零件 。但它就像是在……
certain sense still that ship because of the story, right? The... Okay.
因为故事的缘故，你仍然对那艘船 抱有某种感觉，对吧？好的。
So Roman history is different from, let's say, Greek history
所以罗马历史与希腊 历史有所不同。
or Christian history, right? Christian history is the story of a religion. It can be
或者基督教历史，对吧？基督教 历史就是一个宗教的历史。它可以是
in any country, among any ethnic group. It's here, there, right? It's everywhere.
在任何国家，在任何民族群体中。它就在 这里，就在那里，对吧？它无处不在。
But you still have histories of Christianity.
但你们仍然拥有 基督教的历史。
It's the same with, like say, Greek culture-
比如说，希腊文化 也是如此——
... or your Greek literature, right? It's not a function of a particular
……或者说，是希腊文学，对吧？ 这并非某个特定因素的功能。
state. Ancient Greeks were famously never united in a state.
状态。众所周知，古希腊人 从未统一建立一个国家。
But it's people who culturally accept that
但只有那些在文化上接受这一点的人才会这样。
tradition as their kind of elite prestige culture and engage
传统是他们精英阶层享有声望的文化 象征，并以此参与其中。
with Homer and Plato and so forth. And they can be anywhere.
比如荷马、柏拉图等人。 它们可能出现在任何地方。
Roman history is not like that. Roman history is very specifically the history of a
罗马历史并非如此。罗马史具体来 说就是罗马帝国的历史。
state or a political community. And so this is the
国家或政治共同体 。所以这就是……
community of the Roman people, the Roman citizens. And it
罗马人民的共同体，罗马 公民。而且它
is in gradual evolution, but at no point is there a rupture in that
处于渐进演变过程中， 但从未出现过断裂。
history such that its members would ever think that something
历史如此悠久，以至于它的成员们 永远不会认为某件事会发生。
dramatic had changed, and that they're no longer part of that
情况发生了巨大的变化，他们 不再是其中的一部分了。
story. So in the same way as the ship I just mentioned,
故事。所以，就像我刚才 提到的那艘船一样，
in other words, it's the narrative that you tell about it where the changes that
换句话说，改变之处在于你讲述 的关于这件事的叙述方式。
take place to it make sense only when you see them within the context of that story.
只有将它们放在故事的背景下 理解，才能明白其中的含义。
It's the same with Roman history. Yes, there are changes. Like, eventually
罗马历史也是如此。是的，情况 有所变化。比如，最终
everything changes. But it happens so gradually that it doesn't
一切都会改变。但这发生得如此缓慢 ，以至于人们不会注意到。
seem that way to anyone living in it.
对于住在里面的人来说，似乎就是这样。
And so the narrative of the history of the Roman
因此，罗马历史 的叙述……
people is what holds all of this together.
人才是维系这一切的关键。
- How important is it that, so you mentioned Greek culture. So a lot
- 你刚才提到了希腊文化， 这有多重要？所以很多
of my friends who are Greek are extremely proud of being Greek.
我的希腊朋友都为自己是 希腊人而感到无比自豪。
There's certain cultures that are proud.
有些文化以骄傲为傲。
- Sure.
- 当然。
- And it's not a momentary ephemeral thing. It feels
而且这不是转瞬即逝 的事情。感觉
like a thing that has lasted for many generations.
就像一件流传了许多代 的事情一样。
- Oh, yeah.
- 哦，是的。
- And so that is an engine that propagates through
因此，这就是一种 传播的引擎。
time that carries that culture forward. And so does
时间让这种文化得以 传承。确实如此。
a similar thing apply for the Roman Empire in a different way? Maybe
类似的情况也适用于罗马帝国， 只是方式略有不同？或许
because you say it's a political kind of community, that means a set of ideals.
因为你说它是一个政治性的社群 ，那就意味着它有一套理念。
And we'll talk about, because those ideals become even more
我们会讨论这个问题，因为 这些理念会变得更加重要。
concretized and explicit, I think, through the East Roman
我认为，东罗马帝国具体 而明确地体现了这一点。
Empire, because one of the things you talk about is that the
帝国，因为你谈到的其中 一点就是……
citizens of the empire are kind of all connected, that they are—
帝国的公民之间其实都存在 某种联系，他们就是——
... engaged in this whole sort of machinery. Anyway, that's a complicated way
……参与了整套这类机制的运作 。总之，这是一种复杂的方法。
of asking, is there some elements that Greek
问，希腊语中是否存在 一些元素？
pride, dare I speak, is there some kind of Roman pride that propagates the thing?
恕我直言，是不是某种罗马式 的骄傲助长了这种现象？
- Oh, there totally is. You can find authors and historical agents who definitely
- 哦，当然有。你可以找到一些作家 和历史代理人，他们肯定会
display this or talk about it. But we don't want to make that
展示出来或者谈论它。 但我们不想那样做。
the center of the story or the basis for any analysis because... So what you're
故事的核心或任何分析的基础， 因为……所以你的意思是……
observing in your Greek friends is also the result of modern nation building,
观察你的希腊朋友也是现代 国家建设的结果。
is it's the result of modern systems of education, and sort of national identities,
这是现代教育体系和某 种民族认同的产物吗？
and these are fostered and created through all kinds of media and
这些内容是通过各种媒体 进行培育和创造的，
institutions. It's just a different situation altogether. What you
机构。这完全是另 一种情况。你
find in ancient republics or medieval states is more something like a consensus
在古代共和国或中世纪国家 中发现的，更像是某种共识。
to be ruled, to be, to rule and to be ruled in this particular political community.
在这个特定的政治共同体中，既要被统治，又 要生存，既要统治他人，又要被统治。
Now, some members of it may definitely, and in fact did have this kind of pride. I'll
现在，其中一些成员肯定，而且实际上 也确实有过这种自豪感。患病的
give you an example. So there's an ambassador in the sixth century, and he's concluding
举个例子。所以，六世纪有 一位大使，他正在总结
a deal with the Persians. And you know, the Persians are skeptical
与波斯人达成协议。你知道 ，波斯人是多疑的。
cause, you know, Romans can't always be trusted. But this guy says to them, he says,
因为你知道，罗马人并不总是值得 信任的。但这个人对他们说，他说，
and let me just tell you, you're making a deal here with the Romans.
我得告诉你，你这是 在和罗马人做交易。
The Romans. The name should say it all."
罗马人。名字本身就说明了一切。
Like, you, okay, and you get a sense that this is, he's expressing a certain pride in, like,
就像，你，好吧，你会感觉到，他 是在表达某种自豪感，就像，
being a bearer of the Roman tradition and speaking for the emperors and the Roman Empire.
作为罗马传统的传承者， 代表皇帝和罗马帝国发声。
I mean, that's, for him, this was something very, very momentous. You find these kinds of
我的意思是，对他来说，这是一件非常 非常重要的事情。你会发现这类
examples, so these people exist. But I wouldn't want to make that the basis
举例说明，所以这类人确实存在 。但我不想以此为基础。
for like an analysis of how the society works as a whole.
例如，对整个社会如何 运作进行分析。
For the most part, it was something like a consensus where, you
在很大程度上，这形成了 一种共识，即：
know, subjects or citizens, however you want to call them, they agree to—
无论是臣民还是公民，无论你 怎么称呼他们，他们都同意——
let's say be taxed and be ruled by political authorities because of what
假设因为什么原因而被 征税并受政治当局统治
they get in return, and there's this kind of understanding of a
他们从中获得了回报，并且 存在这样一种理解：
mutual set of responsibilities. And
双方的责任。和
my concern, among other things, is to try to explain how this
我关心的问题之一是， 如何解释这一切。
society held together for so long. Pride, yes, among some people, definitely. You
社会维持了这么长时间。是的，在 某些人身上，的确存在骄傲。你
find it in the sources. But sources are, texts are written by
在资料来源中查找。但资料 来源是，文本是由……撰写的
literate, you know, usually elites. So this is a small part
你知道，有文化的人通常是精英 阶层。所以这只是很小的一部分。
of the population. We can't automatically extend their attitudes to everybody else.
人口。我们不能自动将他们 的态度推广到其他人身上。
So in dealing with everyone else, we have to work with different kinds of materials, different kinds of
因此，在与其他人打交道时，我们必须 使用不同类型的材料，不同类型的……
assumptions. We can't just posit that they're just proud of being Roman.
假设。我们不能就此断定他们只 是以身为罗马人而自豪。
They could have been. We don't know that, though. We can see other sorts of things
他们本来可能是。但我们并不知道这一点 。我们还可以看到其他类型的事物。
about them. Like, for example, did they pay their taxes? Did they try to rebel and
关于他们。例如，他们是否缴纳 了税款？他们是否曾试图反抗？
leave the empire? So those are the kinds of things that I look for.
离开帝国？所以，这些就 是我所关注的方面。
- Pride is one component, but there could be other explanations and factors
骄傲是其中一个因素，但也可能 存在其他解释和因素。
that explain what motivates a soldier to defend the capital, for example.
例如，这可以解释是什么 促使士兵保卫首都。
Like, what motivates a
比如，是什么激励了
particular person to pay the taxes. And then this is something that we'll
税款应由特定人员缴纳。然后 ，这是我们将要做的事情。
definitely talk about. But just to linger at the big picture,
一定要谈谈。但让我们先从宏观 角度来看待这个问题。
if the Romans from the different periods met,
如果不同时期的 罗马人相遇，
how different would they be from each other? Like, if I
它们之间会有多大的 不同？比如，如果我
brought to you... This is one of those, you know, there's like-
由……倾情呈现。你知道 ，这是那种……
- Yes, yes,
是的，是的
- ... blind taste tests you can do with food.
- ……你可以对食物 进行盲品测试。
- Yes. Pepsi and Coke.
- 是的。百事可乐和可口可乐。
- Pepsi and Coke.
百事可乐和可口可乐。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- If I brought you a Roman from the kingdom period,
- 如果我给你带来一位来自罗马 王国时期的罗马人，
the republic period, the early imperial period-
共和国时期，帝国 早期时期
- I mean, I get asked this in a much more radical form, which is like if you take someone
我的意思是，我经常被问到这个问题，而且问法 要激进得多，比如，如果你带某人
from, like, around 1453 who's a Roman and a subject of this Roman,
大约从1453年起，他是一位罗马人 ，也是这位罗马人的臣民。
and compare, and, and, you know, compare him or have him meet, you know,
然后比较一下，然后，你知道，把他和 别人比较一下，或者让他见见别人，你知道，
in your imagination with someone from the ancient republic. Like, how-
在你的想象中，与一位来自古代共和国 的人在一起。比如，怎么做？
- Yeah,
- 是的，
- ... could they find any kind of agreement on what it means to
他们能否就其含义 达成任何共识？
be Roman and recognize each other as belonging to that polity? This, this
彼此都是罗马人并承认对方 属于该政体？这个，这个
is a very difficult thing to... Like, now, I can point to a
这是一件非常困难的事情……比如 ，现在，我可以指出一个
number of things that they would find eventually. And, you know,
他们最终会发现很多东西 。而且，你知道，
if you told them, "Yo, you're both Romans, you're both from this long history, now you have
如果你告诉他们，“嘿，你们都是罗马人， 你们都来自这段悠久的历史，现在你们有……”
to find, you know, what you have in common," I think they could find things. But
“要找到你们的共同点，” 我认为他们能找到。
before we talk about those, if you wanna get into it,
在我们讨论这些之前，如果 你想深入了解一下，
let's just say that the question can even be posed
这么说吧，这个问题 甚至可以提出来。
about Romans who live at the same time. I mean, if you take a
关于生活在同一时期的罗马人 。我的意思是，如果你采取
senator from the age of Cicero and someone from the
一位来自西塞罗时代的参议员 ，以及一位来自……
slums of Rome, who's maybe the son of a slave
他来自罗马的贫民窟 ，或许是奴隶的儿子。
who was brought from the East by some general a generation ago,
他是上一代人之前被某个 将军从东方带来的。
and put them in a room and say, "Now, you discuss. You're
然后把他们关在一个房间里， 说：“现在，你们来讨论。”
both Romans. What do you have in common?" They might have trouble in coming up with something.
两人都是罗马人。你们有什么共同点 ？他们可能很难想出什么共同点。
Right? So let's not minimize the sheer
正确的？所以，我们不要低估其纯粹性。
diversity of experiences and sort of life experiences
各种各样的经历 和人生体验
of Romans who are living at the same time.
生活在同一时期的罗马人。
The important thing is that a change is always happening, and
重要的是，变化 总是在发生的。
from my standpoint this change is sort of
从我的角度来看，这种变化有点……
cumulative, so it results in Greek-speaking Orthodox
累积性的，因此产生 了讲希腊语的东正教
Christian Romans in Constantinople who at first
君士坦丁堡的 基督教罗马人最初
sight might have little to do with Latin-speaking, you
视力可能与拉丁语系 关系不大，你
know, non-Christians or worshiping the ancient gods, Romans from a
知道，非基督徒或崇拜古代神灵 的人，罗马人来自……
republic in Rome. And those are very, very different situations, and no
罗马共和国。这些情况截然 不同，而且没有
doubt they would look and seem foreign to each other, right? The
他们看起来应该和对方 很陌生，对吧？这
question is, why do we assume that someone like Hadrian, right, an emperor from the
问题是，为什么我们会认为像哈德良这样 的人，对吧，一位来自……的皇帝……
second century sort of a very cosmopolitan figure
二世纪一位非常具有 国际视野的人物
who travels around the empire with his Greek lover and,
他与他的希腊情人一起 游历帝国各地，
you know, writes poems and has a Greek beard and, you know, loves Greek culture and
你知道，他会写诗，留着希腊式的胡子， 而且，你知道，他热爱希腊文化。
has much to do with someone from the Middle Republic who's, you
这与来自中部共和国的 某人有很大关系，你
know some warrior who's chasing down cattle from the Samnites. I
我认识一个正在追赶萨姆尼特人 牛群的战士。我
mean, and yet the way we understand history is that, oh no, those belong together.
意思是，然而我们对历史的理解是， 哦不，它们应该联系在一起。
Hadrian and this ancient Roman from the fourth century BC.
哈德良和这位公元前四 世纪的古罗马人。
But not Hadrian and someone, you know, an emperor a few
但不是哈德良，还有某个 ，你知道，一位皇帝
centuries later who's just like him, bilingual in Greek and Latin, who's
几个世纪后，又有谁像他一样 ，精通希腊语和拉丁语呢？
... kinda cosmopolitan, who, you know, reads the same stuff,
……有点国际化，你知道 ，读的都是同样的东西，
because we posit this rupture between Roman and Byzantine.
因为我们假设罗马和拜占庭 之间存在这种断裂。
- One of the ways we can try to analyze this is, for example, looking at
- 我们可以尝试分析这个问题的方法 之一是，例如，观察……
a very specific role in society across time. So we can look at soldiers,
在历史长河中，它在社会中扮演着非常特殊 的角色。所以我们可以看看士兵们，
how they solve violence, for example. That's one way.
例如，他们如何解决暴力问题 。这是其中一种方法。
So you're making me realize that we can just take 1,000
所以你让我意识到 我们可以只拿1000
different professions and positions in society and really
社会中不同的职业 和地位，以及真正
specifically look at what the experience of the world was like.
具体来说，要看看当时 的世界体验是什么样的。
And so one of them is the view on violence,
其中之一就是对 暴力的看法。
Across time. And, and then the other is the view on the role of the,
跨越时间。然后，另一种观点 是关于……的作用，
the government- ... across time.
政府——随着时间的推移。
- That's an excellent way of putting it. So take soldiers, for example. They swear an oath.
- 这话说得真好。以士兵 为例。他们发誓。
Right? Now, we don't have the oath for every given period.
正确的？现在，我们并没有 每个时期的誓词。
We have some approximations of it, some hints of what it contained, but we know that Roman
我们对其内容有一些大致了解， 一些线索，但我们知道罗马
soldiers swore an oath like, throughout all of the centuries of the
几个世纪以来，士兵们 都像过去一样宣誓效忠。
empire. Sometimes they might add, like, a Christian formula
帝国。有时他们可能会加上一些 基督教公式之类的东西。
to it. Sometime before that, not. But they swore basically to protect the
去它。在那之前，不是。但他们 基本上发誓要保护……
republic or depending on what term they used or the
共和国，或者取决于他们 使用的术语，或者
empire or the emperor. And this is something that they would have
帝国或皇帝。而这正 是他们会拥有的。
recognized very quickly. Like, if, if they met each other over
很快就被认出来了。比如 ，如果他们相遇了……
time and said, "Hey, what was your oath like?" And they recited it this would have made much sense
过了一会儿，他问道：“嘿，你的誓词是什么样 的？”他们背诵了这段话，这很有意义。
to them, right?
对他们来说，对吧？
Or take, for example, a woman who runs a business, right? From any century of the
例如，一位经营企业的女性 ，对吧？从任何一个世纪的
empire. It, it would have been, especially the later you go, the, the more so,
帝国。确实如此，尤其是你 越晚去，就越是如此。
that this woman is enabled to do this by virtue
这位女性能够做到这一点 是出于她的美德。
of Roman law. Of certain, you know, Roman law of
罗马法。当然，你 知道，罗马法
property and inheritance and, and marriage, but
财产、继承和 婚姻，但是
also regulations regarding who can do what and what
还有关于谁可以做什么以及 可以做什么的规定。
kinds of properties women can handle and under what circumstances.
女性能够驾驭的房产类型以及在 何种情况下可以驾驭。
This is something that Roman women had in common that many other cultures did not.
这是罗马女性与其他许多文化 女性所不具备的共同特征。
So I'll give you an example. So for example, in the 10th,
我举个例子。例如 ，在第十章中，
11th century, there are Jewish women who live in the Eastern Roman Empire-
11世纪时，东罗马帝国境内 生活着一些犹太妇女。
... who realize that they have more rights in Roman courts than in
……他们意识到，他们在罗马法庭 上比在……拥有更多权利
rabbinical ones, and they take their disputes to the Roman courts.
犹太教拉比们，他们会 将纠纷提交给罗马法庭。
Now, the thing is that for the Romans, these are property matters-
然而，对罗马人来说， 这些都是财产问题——
... not religious matters. But for the rabbis, these are religious matters. But the
……并非宗教问题。但对拉比们 来说，这些都是宗教事务。但是
Roman courts trump the Jewish courts-
罗马法庭凌驾于犹太法庭之上——
... in the empire, right? And so you end up with a situation where Jewish women have more
……在帝国境内，对吧？因此，最终 导致犹太女性拥有更多权利的情况。
rights-
权利-
... than Jewish women do elsewhere, because where Roman law is not operative.
比其他地方的犹太妇女更甚，因为 在那些地方，罗马法并不适用。
And there you go. Right? Like, these things matter, right? And that's a
好了。正确的？这些事情很 重要，对吧？那是一个
function of imperial law.
帝国法律的功能。
- And this, this would be an interesting actually interplay between the law
——而这，这实际上是法律 之间一种有趣的互动。
and religious institutions- ... Throughout the East- ... uh, Roman Empire.
以及宗教机构——……遍及东方——…… 呃，罗马帝国。
So you argue that even though the personality of the various emperors varied,
所以你的论点是，尽管 历代皇帝的性格各不相同，
as we'll talk about, and as they're often venerated,
正如我们将要讨论的，也正如 它们经常被尊崇的那样，
celebrated, criticized, talked about,
被赞扬、被批评、被谈论
the late Roman Empire was projecting a persona to its
晚期罗马帝国向其自身 塑造了一种形象。
citizens that was consistent throughout its history.
历史上始终如一 的公民。
Can you describe what you mean by this and describe the different detailed
你能解释一下你的意思并详细 描述一下不同方面吗？
characteristics of this persona?
这个角色有哪些特征？
- Yes. So this persona, it's what the governments or the emperor, the court, and the
- 是的。所以这种形象， 是政府或皇帝、朝廷以及……
spokesman, the bureaucracy want their subjects to think,
发言人表示，官僚机构 希望他们的臣民思考：
This whole thing is about. Like, how is power being used, why, and for whom, right?
整件事的起因是……比如，权力是如何被使用 的，为什么被使用，以及为谁服务，对吧？
And they do so in laws that
他们通过法律来做到这一点，
they promulgate throughout the empire. Sometimes they have these laws read in
它们在整个帝国范围内传播。 有时他们会宣读这些法律。
church, for example, or posted publicly. They're definitely eager to
例如，在教堂里，或者 公开张贴。他们肯定很渴望
have them communicated to as many people as possible.
尽可能让更多人 了解这些信息。
But they're also a function of imperial rhetoric so the way
但它们也是帝国主义修辞 的一种体现，所以方式
you praise an emperor, the way you talk about an emperor. You find this
你赞美皇帝的方式，就是你谈论 皇帝的方式。你发现这个
language in petitions, so this is a hugely important
请愿书中的语言，因此 这一点至关重要。
glue for this society, is that anyone could
这个社会的粘合剂 是任何人都可以
basically petition the authorities for let's just say just about anything.
基本上，你可以向有关部门请愿 ，要求几乎任何事情。
That's not technically true, but there's a lot of petitioning going
严格来说，这并不完全正确，但 确实有很多请愿活动正在进行。
on. So, you know, if you think something's wrong or you've been
在。所以，你知道，如果你觉得 有什么不对劲，或者你一直……
treated unjustly, you can petition local officials, even
如果受到不公正对待，你 可以向地方官员请愿，即使
imperial officials. You can petition the emperor, you can... Right? And the
帝国官员。你可以向皇帝请愿 ，你可以……对吧？以及
expectation is that that petition will be read, addressed, and answered. It might not
预计该请愿书将被阅读、 处理和答复。可能不会
be answered in the way that you want, but it will be answered.
答案会以你想要的方式呈现 ，但一定会得到解答。
And those responses contain this language also, right? So these are
这些回复中也包含了这种 语言，对吧？所以这些是
the different media through which the emperors are broadcasting this
皇帝们通过各种媒体 传播这一信息。
persona, and that persona is what? Basically, that the
角色，而这个角色是什么 ？基本上，就是这样
authorities are responsive to the needs of their subjects,
当局会积极回应 民众的需求，
that they are often accountable. In other words, they understand
他们往往要承担责任。 换句话说，他们明白
that they are exercising public power,
他们正在行使公共权力，
and that their mandate is to exercise it solely for the
他们的职责是仅为以下 目的行使该职责：
benefit of their subjects. They keep saying this. Um,
造福其臣民。他们 一直这么说。嗯，
so renouncing any kind of private interest. In other
因此，他放弃了任何形式 的私人利益。在其他方面
words, "We're not doing this for our benefit," say the
他们说：“我们这样做不是为了 我们自己的利益。”
authorities. "We're doing this for your benefit."
当局。 “我们这样做 是为了你好。”
Also that they're proactive. So the emperors are constantly
而且他们还很积极主动 。所以皇帝们总是
saying that, "We're planning ahead.
他说：“我们正在提前做好计划。”
We're trying to foresee what problems you might have, and we are solving
我们正在努力预测您可能遇到的问题 ，并努力解决这些问题。
them at, before you experience them."
在体验它们之前，先了解它们。
And that they are also working very hard. So hardworking. In fact,
而且他们也都非常努力。 非常勤奋。实际上，
the one of the cliches that they keep using is sleepless. The emperors
他们反复使用的一个老套 说法是失眠。皇帝们
keep saying that, "I'm losing sleep over this. I'm not sleeping at night because
我一直说，“我为此失眠了。我 晚上睡不着觉，因为……”
I'm just worrying so much about your problems and how to solve them." Justinian,
我太担心你的问题以及如何 解决它们了。” 贾斯蒂尼安
for example, was publicly known as the sleepless emperor, and not
例如，他被世人称为“ 不眠皇帝”，而不是
because he was a demon whose head floated around in the palace on its own,
因为他是个恶魔，他的 头颅会自己飘到宫殿里。
which some people
有些人
- That's the thing?
原来是这样？
- It was a thing, yes.
没错，确实发生过这件事。
- Okay.
- 好的。
- That's a whole thing.
那可是件大事。
- But sleepless in terms of worked so hard-
但由于工作太努力，我几乎彻夜难眠。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- ... there's no time to sleep.
——根本没有时间睡觉。
- He was a workaholic. That is conceded by even his enemies.
他是个工作狂。就连他的 敌人也承认这一点。
All night he was up just hauling officials in at any old hour to
他整夜没睡，随时都 把官员们叫来。
talk about whatever, you know, wars and architecture and laws and the
随便聊聊，你知道，战争 、建筑、法律等等。
religion and theology and whatever. So the emperors are projecting this image, right?
宗教、神学等等。所以，皇帝们 是在塑造这种形象，对吧？
So that's what I call the persona.
这就是我所说的角色扮演。
Tireless effort to work on behalf of subjects, to do so responsibly,
为人民不懈努力，并以负 责任的态度开展工作，
to be responsive and accountable. In other words,
要积极回应并承担 责任。换句话说，
if some of my officials breaks the law or oppresses
如果我的一些官员 违法或压迫人民
you, I'm giving you instruments, like legal
我给你提供工具 ，比如法律工具。
instruments, by which to hold them to account.
可以用来追究他们 责任的手段。
So that's the persona. It's very consistent,
这就是人物设定。 它非常一致，
And I think it's part of the mechanism of tying the society
我认为这是维系社会 关系机制的一部分。
together. In other words, if subjects think that their emperors are like this,
一起。换句话说，如果臣民认为 他们的皇帝是这样的人，
right, they're more likely to agree to the consensus of essentially paying taxes.
没错，他们更有可能同意 缴纳税款的共识。
- And you draw this distinction between rhetoric and action,
你区分了言辞 和行动，
what the authorities say and what they actually do. So when you say
官方的说法和他们实际 的做法。所以当你说
persona in the modern times, some of that could be reframed as propaganda-
在现代社会，个人形象中的某些 方面可以被重新定义为宣传。
- Yeah.
- 是的。
- ... for example. And propaganda implies that the rhetoric,
- ... 例如。而宣传则 意味着修辞，
that there's a big gap between the rhetoric and the
言辞和实际行动 之间存在巨大差距
action. And one of the things you said you took away from reading Machiavelli is that
行动。你曾说过，你从阅读马基雅 维利的作品中学到的一点是：
we should judge people not by what they say, but by what they do.
我们评判一个人，不应该看他说了 什么，而应该看他做了什么。
So how much of the Roman Empire's government of what they espoused
那么，罗马帝国政府究竟有 多少是他们所信奉的呢？
was merely rhetoric, and how much was true in how they acted?
这不过是空谈，他们的实际 行动又有多少是真心话呢？
- Yes. This is a key lesson I took from reading Machiavelli, and
- 是的。这是我从阅读马基雅维利著作 中汲取的一个重要教训，
I found this a very insightful way of thinking about politics, and
我发现这种思考政治的方式 非常有见地，而且
I would recommend that anybody kind of practice this way of looking at the world,
我建议任何人都可以尝试 用这种方式看待世界。
right? People and states and, you know, powerful people can say
正确的？人民、国家，还有，你 知道，有权势的人都可以说
anything they want to. At the end of the day, what matters is what they actually do.
他们想做什么都可以。归根结底 ，重要的是他们实际做了什么。
And this doesn't mean that what they say is
但这并不意味着 他们所说的话是
irrelevant, even if it's discordant with what they do. But nevertheless,
即使与他们的做法不符 ，也无关紧要。但是，
In the case of the East Roman state,
以东罗马帝国为例，
so my research suggests that the emperors and the authorities
因此，我的研究表明 ，皇帝和当局
were generally sincere in what they said. In other words,
他们所说的话总体上都是 真诚的。换句话说，
I have found that they generally did what they said they were going to do overall.
我发现他们总体上基本都做到 了他们承诺要做的事情。
Not perfectly, obviously. And of course, these are human beings we're talking
当然，并不完美。当然 ，我们谈论的是人。
about. The, right, the human societies, there was a lot of, you know,
关于。对，人类社会，有 很多，你知道的，
corruption, and you name it. Abuse-
腐败，以及其他种种问题。虐待-
... of course. Of course there is. But overall, I think that there was
... 当然。当然有。但总的 来说，我认为……
a sufficient level of understanding that the emperors
皇帝们对事物 的理解程度足以
are in fact doing this, and they were actually incentivized to do this. We can talk
事实上他们正在这样做，而且他们实际上 也受到了激励才这样做。我们可以谈谈
about how. Because they were also in a pretty vulnerable situation too, so they
关于如何。因为他们当时也处于 相当脆弱的境地，所以他们
needed their subjects to be relatively content on this front.
需要让他们的臣民 在这方面相对满意。
- Isn't this surprising to you? So, you know, from the
- 你不觉得这很意外吗 ？所以，你知道，从
outsider point of view, Roman emperors, even in the East Roman Empire,
从局外人的角度来看，罗马皇帝，即使 在东罗马帝国也是如此。
technically have a lot of power.
从技术上讲，它们拥有很大的权力。
You can even say in some cases absolute power, and yet
你甚至可以说在某些情况 下拥有绝对权力，然而
they seem to be awfully worried ... to make everybody in the empire happy.
他们似乎非常担心……如何让 帝国中的每个人都满意。
What explains that? Like what, what explains the small
这该如何解释？比如 什么，是什么解释了小
gap between rhetoric and action in the East Roman Empire?
东罗马帝国言辞与行动 之间存在差距吗？
- A number of things, but ultimately it is that there is no right to the throne.
- 原因有很多，但归根结底 ，王位并非理所当然。
And this is a function of the Roman matrix of politics here. In other words,
而这正是罗马政治格局 的体现。换句话说，
So here's a bit of a paradox.
这里存在一个悖论。
What we call the Roman Republic was the most imperialistic
我们所说的罗马共和国是帝国主义 最盛行的时期。
phase of Roman history. Like this is when the Romans did most of their conquering.
罗马历史的一个阶段。罗马人正是在 这一时期进行了大部分的征服。
What we call the empire is much less imperialistic in this way.
我们今天所说的帝国，从这个意义上讲 ，其实并不那么具有帝国主义色彩。
That's much more defensive in its approach, right? And yet our
这种做法更具防御性 ，对吧？然而我们的
terms are a little mismatched in that way. The empire is more a function of the,
从这个角度来看，这些术语有点不匹配 。帝国的存亡更多地取决于……
That it has an emperor rather than it is engaged in imperialism.
它拥立的是皇帝，而不 是从事帝国主义。
And that emperor emerged out of the republic.
那位皇帝就是从共和国中 诞生的。
But emerged out of the republic in a very strange way. In other words,
但它以一种非常奇怪的方式从共和国中 脱颖而出。换句话说，
not as a dynasty that created the
并非作为一个创建了……的王朝
state. So for example, if you think of the Ottoman Empire, many other empires,
状态。例如，想想奥斯曼帝国 ，以及许多其他帝国，
they... The whole thing existed because this dynasty engaged in conquest and-
他们……这一切之所以存在，是因为 这个王朝进行了征服和——
... was successful in creating the state, and so the dynasty was like at the heart of the
……成功地建立了国家，因此该 王朝就像是国家的核心……
state. But that's not at all the case in the Roman
状态。但在罗马， 情况并非如此。
Empire. The emperor is a figure who emerged within a
帝国。皇帝是一个 在……中出现的人物
republic, and in order to create peace after the
共和国，以及为了 在之后创造和平
civil wars, those emperors had to, for a long time, kind of
内战期间，那些皇帝们不得不 长期处于某种程度的……
pretend that they were not what they really were. Um, basically, you know,
假装他们不是他们真正的样子 。嗯，基本上，你知道的
continuing to flatter the idea of a republic that is, you know, that has a
继续奉承共和国的理念，你 知道，那种共和国拥有……
first citizen maybe. "Oh, no, no, I'm not a king. I'm just, I
或许是第一公民。 “哦，不， 不，我不是国王。我只是，我
have this office and that office and that office."
有这个办公室，有那个办公室 ，还有那个办公室。
"Whatever the Senate has given me." Now, we understand that's a facade, but the
“无论参议院给了我什么。”现在， 我们明白那只是表面现象，但是
fact that they had to create this facade at all is very important.
他们不得不营造这种假象这 一事实本身就非常重要。
- Can we actually just linger on that?
我们真的可以就此多停留一会儿吗？
I mean, how much of this... 'Cause you said they had to create this facade.
我的意思是，这其中有多少是真的…… 因为你说过他们必须营造这种假象。
- Yeah.
- 是的。
- Did Augustus, who started the whole thing, the first emperor of Rome,
——是奥古斯都，这位开启这 一切的罗马第一位皇帝，
did he have to act that way? 'Cause he kept acting like he's not an absolute-
他非得那样做吗？因为他一直表现 得好像他不是一个绝对的——
- Yes
- 是的
- ... monarch, and he could have gone hardcore, destroy the Senate, just full
——君主，他本可以采取更极端的做法 ，摧毁参议院，彻底摧毁一切。
hardcore rule, dictatorship.
铁腕统治，独裁统治。
- Well, then how does he govern then?
那他究竟是如何执政的呢？
- Uh, so he wants to be an effective governor.
- 嗯，所以他想成为 一位高效的州长。
- Oh, yeah.
- 哦，是的。
- And he also wants to not be overthrown.
而且他也不想被推翻。
- Exactly. Because, you know, just because you ended one civil war
- 确切地。因为，你知道，仅仅 因为你结束了一场内战
doesn't mean that there's not going to be another.
但这并不意味着不 会再有另一次。
You have to create a consensus such that people don't want to have another civil war.
你必须达成共识，让人们 不希望再次发生内战。
If he did what you said, which he in theory could have done,
如果他真的像你说的那样做了， 理论上他确实可以这么做，
but that would've just led to more wars, right? So the
但这不只会导致更 多战争吗？所以
problem is that the emperors, even those who come to power through violence, they
问题在于，即使是那些通过 暴力夺取政权的皇帝，他们
can't prevent other people from trying to come to power through violence
无法阻止其他人试图通过 暴力手段夺取政权。
because like I said, no one has a right to the throne.
因为就像我说的，没有 人有权继承王位。
- We should also say one more thing where,
我们还要补充一点，
dare I carefully say this, but it seems like riots and civil wars
我冒昧地这么说吧，这看 起来像是暴乱和内战。
is a feature, not a bug of the system.
这是系统特性，而不是系统漏洞。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- This is a different thing that we have to the modern day,
这和我们现代社会的 情况有所不同，
is because the threat of a civil war, a violent civil war where you
这是因为存在内战的威胁， 一场你……的暴力内战。
overthrow the government and there's just a lot of-
推翻政府，还 有很多——
... death and struggle for power is always a threat.
死亡和权力斗争始终 是一种威​​胁。
That's another incentive that, I guess the stick, not the carrot, but
我觉得这是另一种激励措施，更 像是棍棒而不是胡萝卜，但是……
the stick for the emperor to behave.
用来约束皇帝行为的棍棒。
- Yes. It's the main one. In other words, just take the,
- 是的。这是主要的那个 。换句话说，就拿走，
the thousand years that I study. There's something like 120 civil wars.
我研究的那千年历史。历史 上大约发生过120场内战。
Now, these are usually very swift. They're over quickly,
现在，这些通常都非常迅速 。它们很快就结束了。
and they're never about ideology. So they're not like modern civil wars.
而且它们与意识形态无关。 所以它们不像现代内战。
Right? It's about slavery or the rights of kings or whatever. No, no, no. They're
正确的？它关乎奴隶制、君权神授或 其他什么话题。不，不，不。他们是
solely about who has the power.
一切都关乎谁掌握权力。
All sides have the same ideology. They talk about, you know, the
各方意识形态相同。他们 谈论的是，你知道的，
responsibility of government in the same way, right? They're just competing over
政府也应承担同样的责任， 对吗？他们只是在竞争
who's the best man to do the job.
谁是最适合做这份工作的人选？
Right? And so once you have that situation... And it might not be a
正确的？所以一旦你遇到这种 情况……而且这可能并非……
civil war, it could be a palace coup, it could be a kind
内战，也可能是宫廷政变 ，也可能是某种
of fighting in the capital-
在首都作战——
... something like that. Once everyone's taken their side and you have a winner,
大概就是这样。当所有人都表明 立场，决出胜负之后，
that's the emperor, And you often overthrow the previous regime. I'll give you some
那是皇帝，而你经常会推翻 前政权。我会给你一些
statistics. Something like 46% of the emperors of
统计数据。大约 46%的皇帝
Constantinople are overthrown through violence. 46%. And that's almost half.
君士坦丁堡被暴力推翻。 46%。那几乎占了一半。
Right? So that's a huge, that's a huge number, which means that every emperor
正确的？所以这是一个巨大的 数字，这意味着每一位皇帝
is vulnerable and insecure, and they know it,
他们很脆弱，缺乏安全感，而且他们 自己也知道这一点。
right? So what they have to do is make sure that that doesn't happen to them,
正确的？所以他们必须做的就是确保 这种情况不会发生在自己身上。
and the way to do that is not by arresting
而实现这一目标的方法并非逮捕。
and executing everybody you think might be a threat or just generally behaving
处决所有你认为可能构成威胁 或仅仅是行为不端的人。
like a, you know, a Caligula or a Nero. That will just get you killed.
就像，你知道的，卡利古拉或者 尼禄那样的人。那样做只会送命。
Like, they know this. So the best way to avoid that
他们好像知道这一点。所以 避免这种情况的最佳方法是
fate is to actually do the things that will make
命运就是去做那些 能成就大事的事情。
people happy so that they don't support a rebel if a rebel
人们感到高兴，所以他们 不会支持叛乱分子。
decides to appear. And sometimes rebels would appear.
决定出场。有时 还会出现反叛者。
There's a kind of convention in Constantinople, like if you... Sometimes you
君士坦丁堡有一种不成文 的规矩，比如如果你……有时候你
you think, "Hmm, that emperor's pretty unpopular and I think I can overthrow him." What you would
你会想，“嗯，那个皇帝很不受欢迎 ，我想我可以推翻他。”你会
do is you would march down the center boulevard-
你应该做的就是沿着中央 大道行进——
... And, you know, you'd have your people just call the
……而且，你知道，你会让 你的人打电话给……
populace of Constantinople out to rally, to you know, maybe go to
君士坦丁堡民众出来集结， 你知道，也许会去……
Hagia Sophia, the, the church, and just create a big crowd and call for the
圣索菲亚大教堂，教堂，然后 聚集一大群人，呼吁……
deposition of the emperor and, you know, maybe that would hap- And sometimes it did,
废黜皇帝，你知道，也许会发生 ——而且有时确实会发生。
and sometimes it didn't, and the rebel or wannabe rebel would sort of
有时并非如此，叛逆者或 想成为叛逆者的人就会……
proceed down the Mese, the boulevard, and people would just
沿着梅塞大道（Mese） 走，人们就会……
gradually just disappear, and then he'd be left alone-
他渐渐地就消失了，然后 就只剩下他一个人了。
... and go up to Hagia Sophia as seeking asylum. Right? So that's a bid.
……然后前往圣索菲亚大教堂 寻求庇护。正确的？这就是出价。
That's someone making a bid for the throne, and it just goes disastrously bad.
那是有人觊觎王位 ，结果却惨败。
Other times, the people come out 'cause they hate the emperor, and they drag the emperor out and cut his nose off or
有时，人们出来是因为他们憎恨皇帝，他们 把皇帝拖出来，割掉他的鼻子，或者
whatever. So emperors are
任何。所以皇帝们
constantly trying to prevent that from happening, and the best way to do
不断尝试阻止这种情况发生 ，而最好的方法是……
that is through goodwill.
这是出于善意。
- I'm trying to load in that kind of world 'cause it's a different
我试图融入那种世界， 因为它与众不同。
world than we live in today.
比我们今天生活的世界更广阔。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- There's a constant inner workings of policy development inside government.
政府内部政策制定是一 个持续不断的过程。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- But the check on power is, like, literal, like, we will murder you.
但对权力的制衡是字面意义上 的，比如，我们会杀了你。
- Yes, it depends on the period. Sometimes murder you, sometimes blind you,
- 是的，这取决于时期。有时 杀你，有时弄瞎你。
sometimes cut your nose off, but there were periods-
有时候会割掉你的鼻子 ，但也有时期——
- Thank you for the nuance
谢谢你的细致分析。
- ... No, there were periods that were more civilized. We'll just basically, you'll get retired to a
不，历史上也曾有过更加文明的时期。 基本上，你退休后就会去……
monastery.
修道院。
- Right.
- 正确的。
- Okay. You're right. So here's what elections do.
- 好的。你说得对。 这就是选举的作用。
Elections give a government a mandate for, I don't know, four or five years,
选举赋予政府任期，我 不知道，四五年吧。
and during that period, you may be unpopular, but you're legitimate,
在那段时间里，你可能不受 欢迎，但你是合法的。
right, because of the institutions.
没错，因为有这些制度。
Whereas in Constantinople, we don't have those kinds of institutions.
而在君士坦丁堡，我们 没有这类机构。
We have instead an ongoing referendum.
我们现在正在进行全民公投。
We just call it a perpetual referendum, right?
我们就称之为永无止境 的公投吧？
And in fact, the emperors are, they're conducting opinion polls in a sense
事实上，皇帝们确实在进行 某种意义上的民意调查。
because they appear in public. When they appear in public, everyone is
因为他们会在公共场合露面。当他们 出现在公众场合时，每个人都……
expected to cheer and chant acclamations, right, like,
预计会欢呼雀跃，高喊口号 ，对吧，就像……
Slogans. Right? So you have 100,000 people in the Hippodrome
口号。正确的？所以 ，赛马场里有10万人。
all chanting, you know, "Worthy" or "Many years for you, Augustus" or something
大家都在齐声高喊，你知道的，比如“值得” 或者“奥古斯都，祝你长寿”之类的。
like this. And if that happens, it's great. But if you appear in the Hippodrome and people are,
像这样。如果真能如此，那就太好了。 但如果你出现在赛马场，而人们……
like, sullen or if the chanting is a bit tepid or if they're booing,
比如，气氛阴沉，或者吟唱声有些 冷淡，或者有人发出嘘声。
then you know something's wrong, right?
那你就知道肯定出问题了，对吧？
So you gotta find out what's wrong. It could be something like the grain
所以你得找出问题所在 。它可能类似于谷物。
supply is, you know, not working or
你知道，供应出了问题，或者
whatever. And so emperors are desperate to fix those problems.
任何。因此，帝王们迫切 希望解决这些问题。
- And the Hippodrome is this big gathering place in
而赛马场则是一个大型 的聚会场所
Constantinople, which I guess a lot of people gathered
君士坦丁堡，我想很多 人都聚集在那里。
at and did this kind of cheering or not cheering based on policy and-
是否根据政策进行这种 欢呼或不欢呼——
... and whether the emperor is popular or not. This was democracy.
以及皇帝是否受民众 拥戴。这就是民主。
Uh, I apologize to use that term, but-
呃，很抱歉用这个词，但是——
... in our conception of what that means, because what do we mean by
……在我们对它的含义的理解中， 因为我们所说的是什么意思呢？
democracy in the modern day is that the people somehow have a
现代民主意味着人民 以某种方式拥有……
connection to who leads and how they lead,
与领导者及其领导方式的联系
and this is, the Hippodrome was that connection between the people and the leaders.
而赛马场正是人民与 领导人之间的联系纽带。
- Yes. Now, we can talk about modern democracy if you, if you want. That's a, that's a,
- 是的。现在，如果你愿意，我们可以谈谈 现代民主。那是一个，那是一个，
I have, I have my own views about-
我，我对……有自己的看法。
... modern democracy, and, and, you know, how it works and how
……现代民主，以及，你知道， 它是如何运作的，以及如何
it doesn't and, anyway, whether it is democracy, in fact, 'cause there are other models of
并非如此，而且，无论如何，它是否算是民主 ，实际上，因为还有其他模式。
democracy, like-
民主，就像——
... ancient Athenian democracy, which is a whole other thing. But you're right.
……古雅典民主，那又是另 一回事了。但你说得对。
So it's not just in the Hippodrome. It's wherever people assemble in large
所以它不仅仅存在于赛马场。凡是人们 大规模聚集的地方，都可能成为聚集地。
numbers. So this could be military mustering grounds,
数字。所以这里可能 是军事集结地。
right? So the army. The army is also the Roman people in a way, and the-
正确的？所以，军队。从某种意义上说 ，军队也代表着罗马人民，而且——
in some cases, the most decisive part of it, right? So if an
在某些情况下，这恰恰是其中最关键 的部分，对吧？所以如果一个
army gathers together and they decide they want a different emperor,
军队集结起来，决定拥立 一位新的皇帝。
that's serious, and that can happen out in the provinces too. That doesn't
那很严重，而且这种事在 外省也可能发生。那不是
necessarily have to happen in Constantinople. There's also Hagia
这件事不一定非要在君士 坦丁堡发生。还有圣阿加莎
Sophia, so the people gather in the church, or they gather in
索菲亚，所以人们聚集在教堂 里，或者他们聚集在
public spaces like the Forum of Constantine.
像君士坦丁广场这样 的公共空间。
So this can happen anywhere where a large number of people can gather,
所以，这种情况可能发生在 任何人群聚集的地方。
and it's, I don't know if you wanna call it a democracy as such
而且，我不知道你是否 想把它称作民主政体。
but it is definitely a form of popular, mm, let's say
但它绝对是一种流行的 ，嗯，这么说吧。
consultation and a testing of consensus.
协商和共识检验。
I'll give you another example. So in the 1190s, the emperor, and it's Alexius III,
我再举个例子。所以到了1190年代， 皇帝，也就是阿莱克修斯三世，
he's being threatened by the German emperor. German emperor's basically, "You, you, you pay me a bunch of money or
他受到了德国皇帝的威胁。德国皇帝基本上是这么 说的：“你，你，你给我一大笔钱。”
I'll invade." Just straight up extortion.
我要入侵。” 这简直就是赤裸裸的敲诈勒索。
- Yeah.
- 是的。
- Um, and Alexius decides, "Okay, I'm gonna gather this money. I'm gonna
嗯，然后阿莱克修斯决定：“好吧， 我要筹集这笔钱。我要……”
impose these taxes."
征收这些税款。
And he gathers the people in the Hippodrome, and he says, "You know, we're gonna have the German
他把人们聚集到竞技场，说道：“你们 知道，我们要请德国人来。”
tax." He called it the German tax. And there's such an uproar
他称之为“德国税”， 结果引起了轩然大波。
in the Hippodrome against this that he was like, "Uh, that
在赛马场剧院，他反对这种做法， 就像是说：“呃，那……”
wasn't my idea. I don't know where that came from. No, never mind. We're not gonna have the German
这不是我的主意。我不知道那是从哪里来 的。不，没事了。我们不会有德国人
tax." Fortunately, the German emperor died and, and nothing ever happened,
税收。”幸运的是，德国皇帝 去世了，什么事也没发生。
but it gives you a sense of how emperors, like, literally can backtrack when they see that the
但这让你感受到，当皇帝们看到事情进展 不顺时，他们真的可以改变主意。
people are against something in a matter of policy, right- ... like tax policy.
人们在政策方面反对某些事情 ，对吧……比如税收政策。
So yeah, there was this give and take.
是的，双方之间存在着这种互惠互利的关系。
So institutionally, the emperor might look absolute, as
因此，从制度上看，皇帝可能显得 拥有绝对权力，正如……
you called him earlier. In practice, no. No. The ones that did that didn't end well.
你之前给他打过电话。实际上，并非如此 。不，那些这么做的人结局都不太好。
- And we should say, going to Perplexity here, the Hippodrome of Constantinople
——我们应该说，说到这里， 还有君士坦丁堡的竞技场。
was the main stadium and social center of the Byzantine capital,
曾是拜占庭首都的主要 体育场和社交中心，
used primarily for chariot racing and imperial ceremony,
主要用于战车比赛 和皇家仪式，
and today survives in Istanbul's Sultanahmet district.
如今，它依然屹立在伊斯坦布尔 的苏丹艾哈迈德区。
And the reason I looked this up, I wanted to see how many people. Shaped as
我之所以查这个，是 想看看有多少人。形状
a long U-shaped race course with a central barrier
一条长长的U形赛道，中间 设有障碍物。
and tiered seating, it may have held from roughly thirty
以及阶梯式座位，它可能 容纳了大约三十人。
thousand up to a hundred thousand spectators,
数千至十万 名观众，
though exact capacity is debated because archaeological remains are limited.
尽管确切的容量尚存争议， 因为考古遗迹有限。
That's a lot of people.
那可是很多人啊。
- Thirty thousand is definitely a pretty un- underestimate.
三万绝对不是一个相当 保守的估计。
The Hippodrome is still there. I mean, you can see it from, it's like satellite photos.
赛马场还在。我的意思是，你可以 从卫星照片上看到这一点。
The shape of it is still there.
它的形状还在。
And actually some parts of the built, the, the Sphendone, the, the sling
实际上，建造的部分 ，斯芬顿，吊索
around the southern side is still there. You can walk around it. And it's right
南侧周围仍然存在。你可以 绕着它走一圈。没错。
next to the palace. In other words, emperors didn't have to go far. Now,
就在宫殿旁边。换句话说， 皇帝们不必远行。现在，
sometimes there are events for replacing an emperor. So say the emperor dies in
有时会发生皇帝更迭的事件 。假设皇帝驾崩了
his sleep, and there's no heir. This happens in 491, for example.
他睡着了，而且没有继承人。例如 ，这种情况发生在第 491 号案件中。
And so the people gather in the Hippodrome in order to have a
于是人们聚集在赛马场 ，以便进行一场……
discussion with the court about whom to appoint. Now, in those kinds of contexts, it's
与法院讨论任命人选。现在 ，在那种情况下，它是
entirely possible that there are people also in the, the arena,
完全有可能竞技场 里还有其他人。
like not just in the stands. I think some military units might
不仅仅是在看台上。我认为 一些军事单位可能会
have just been arrayed there rather than in the stands. So you can get more people
只是他们被安排在那里而不是在看台 上。这样你就能吸引更多的人
than what we project might fit in the stands, because they're not having the races
比我们预计的看台能容纳的人数 要多，因为他们没有举办比赛。
on that day.
那天。
- We should say, so like, I think the thing that was emphasized in the first paragraph is the,
- 我们应该说，所以，我 认为第一段强调的是，
the athletic events and the entertainment events, right? Like the
体育赛事和娱乐 活动，对吧？就像
imperial ceremony. But there is a sort of a political gathering
皇家仪式。但确实存在 某种政治集会。
was also popular. The Hippodrome was not just for sport. It
也很受欢迎。赛马场不仅仅是用 于体育竞技的场所。它
was where emperors appeared before the people, where acclamations,
那是皇帝觐见人民的地方 ，是人们欢呼的地方。
public punishments, and political demonstrations took place, and where the
公开惩罚和政治示威 活动频发，而且……
rival circus factions, blues, greens, reds, whites,
马戏团各派系之间的敌对关系 ，蓝队、绿队、红队、白队，
became powerful social and sometimes paramilitary forces.
成为强大的社会力量， 有时甚至是准军事力量。
And this goes on and on and on. So this was a place-
这样的事情就这样没完没了地发生下去 。所以这里曾是一个地方——
- Oh, it's a very important place. Yeah,
- 哦，那是一个非常重要的地方。是的，
- ... for people to speak to the leader.
让民众有机会与领导人对话。
- Yeah. Vent sometimes. Even insult them.
- 是的。偶尔发泄一下。甚至可以侮辱他们。
- Yeah. This is fascinating. I mean, it's human civilization. It's converged
- 是的。这太有趣了。我的意思是，这 是人类文明。它已经融合了
towards a mechanism that has clearly worked, because
朝着一种显然行之有效 的机制迈进，因为
for the empire in the East, stood
对于东方的帝国而言，它屹立不倒。
for a thousand years. So it's, it's fascinating. We as humans,
一千年。所以，这真是 太有趣了。我们人类，
throughout our history, we try to figure out, okay, how do we,
纵观我们的历史，我们一直在努力 弄清楚，好吧，我们该如何……
figure out how to govern
想办法治理国家
large collections of humans in a way that they're represented, in the
大量人类以某种方式 被呈现，在
way that they don't riot, they don't rebel.
他们不会暴动 ，也不会反抗。
Um, in the way that we flourish together as a
嗯，就像我们一起 蓬勃发展一样
people, all this, all this kind of stuff.
人，所有这些，所有这些事情。
So this is a real... The East Roman Empire is a real
所以这是真的……东罗马 帝国是真实存在的。
study of something that seemed to have worked. There are
对一些看似有效的方法 进行研究。有
lessons there even for the modern times, I think. And modern times,
我认为，即使在现代，这些经验 教训仍然适用。而现代，
again, is very early human civilization.
再说一遍，这是非常早期的人类文明。
- From a certain standpoint, yes, we are still early in-
从某种角度来看，是的， 我们仍处于早期阶段。
- Trying to figure it out
正在努力弄明白
- ... trying to figure it out.
——我正在努力弄明白。
Yes. Now, mind you, I'm not advocating for this type of social
是的。请注意，我并不 是提倡这种社交方式。
organization and government. What I'm trying to do as a historian
组织和政府。我作为一名 历史学家试图做的事情
is understand how and why it survived
理解它如何以及为何幸存下来。
and also to find the ways that it worked, because it
还要找出它运作 的方式，因为它
did work. We know that much. We have to start from that. It survived. It
确实有效。我们知道的就这么多。我们 必须从那里开始。它幸存了下来。它
was resilient. There was a lot of,
具有韧性。有很多，
you know, give and take in the exercise of power, and I want to understand the
你知道，权力的行使是有得有失 的，我想了解这一点。
mechanisms of that.
其机制。
- So if we can, before we go to Emperor Constantine the
所以，如果我们可以的话，在我们 去见君士坦丁大帝之前……
First and the founding of Constantinople, can we look at some
首先，关于君士坦丁堡的建立 ，我们能否先看一下一些资料？
maybe seminal events that led up to some of the
或许是一些导致某些事件 发生的开创性事件
topics we'll be talking about? So one of them maybe tell me if this is
我们将讨论哪些话题？所以他们 中的一个或许会告诉我这是否是
not as interesting as I think it is, but the Edict of Caracalla, in 212 AD. So this
虽然没有我想象中那么有趣，但公元 212 年 的卡拉卡拉敕令确实值得关注。所以这
is where,
就是那里，
You described that starting with Augustus in the early imperial period, government
你描述说，从奥古斯都早期帝国 时期开始，政府就……
saw itself as a protector of the Roman citizens,
自诩为罗马公民 的保护者，
which is a minority of the people living in the, in the Roman
这只是居住在罗马的人​​口 中的一小部分。
Empire. It doesn't consider the, the provincials.
帝国。它没有考虑到 省份的情况。
And then you described that the Edict of Caracalla, that
然后你描述了卡拉卡拉敕令 ，
extended full Roman citizenships to basically all,
将完整的罗马公民权 扩大到基本上所有人，
free inhabitants of the Roman Empire. So
罗马帝国的自由居民。所以
what is it? Why was it done? Why is it important?
那是什么？为什么要这样 做？为什么这很重要？
And how did it change the Roman Empire?
它又是如何改变罗马帝国的呢？
- Right. I agree with you that this is, in fact, a very important... It's
- 正确的。我同意你的看法， 这确实非常重要……
a, it's a real turning point in a sense, but it also is part of a process.
从某种意义上说，这是一个真正的转折点 ，但它也是一个过程的一部分。
So for various reasons, the Roman polity tended to bestow its metropolitan
因此，出于各种原因，罗马政体 倾向于授予其都城……
citizenship, that is, Roman citizenship, on its allies,
即罗马公民权，赋予 其盟国公民权。
and eventually in time, on many people that it had conquered.
最终，随着时间的推移， 它也征服了许多人。
And it had various mechanisms for doing so. It could bestow block grants.
它有多种机制来实现这一点。 它可以发放专项拨款。
Sometimes it allowed its generals to bestow citizenship on people
有时它允许其将军 授予人民公民权
they thought would, you know, would be necessary
他们认为，你知道 ，这是必要的。
players for controlling local societies. Sometimes they even
玩家控制地方社会 。有时他们甚至
allowed foreign cities to, like non-Roman cities, to
允许外国城市像非罗马 城市一样，
decide who would get Roman citizenship by
决定谁能获得罗马公民权
basically electing them to certain kinds of offices. Like they, they outsourced a lot of this.
基本上就是选举他们担任某些类型的职务 。和他们一样，他们也把很多工作外包了。
And so you have over time the steady growth of a
因此，随着时间的推移，你 会看到a的稳步增长。
Roman community of citizens who are not all in Rome, and
罗马公民群体，指那些并非全部 居住在罗马的公民，以及
who are not all of Roman origin, whatever that means, but they, they were not descended from
他们并非全是罗马人后裔，无论这意味着 什么，但他们，他们并非罗马人的后裔
people who were from Rome.
来自罗马的人。
And this proceeds, you know, it expands, it expands, it expands.
而且这种情况还会继续下去，你知道， 它会不断扩大，不断扩大，不断扩大。
By Caracalla's time, so early third century AD,
到了卡拉卡拉时代，也 就是公元三世纪初，
we can estimate that maybe at, at most, a
我们可以估计，最多可能只有
third of the free citizens of the empire are
帝国三分之一的自由 公民是
Roman citizens. Everyone else has local citizenship, like you're
罗马公民。其他人都拥有当地 公民身份，就像你一样。
Alexandrian or Athenian or, or whatever. And with... You're subject to those laws.
亚历山大的、雅典的，或者其他什么 的。而且……你必须遵守这些法律。
This emperor, Caracalla, now that's his nickname. His reigning name is Marcus
这位皇帝，卡拉卡拉，这是他的 绰号。他的现用名是马库斯
Aurelius Antoninus.
奥勒留·安东尼努斯。
So just like Marcus Aurelius, it's sa- same name two generations later.
所以就像马可·奥勒留一样， 两代人之后，名字仍然相同。
- Some badass names for emperors, by the way. I don't know if it's the chicken or
顺便一提，这些皇帝的名字都很 酷。我不知道是不是鸡肉的问题
the egg, but just... some epic names.
这枚蛋，不过……有一些史诗级的名字。
- They've been remembered that way, and so we read that back into the name—
人们一直这样记住他们，所以我们也 把这种含义解读进了名字里——
- Yes, that's true.
- 是的，没错。
- ... and absolutely, yes.
——当然，是的。
- But anyway, Caracalla. Yeah.
不过，不管怎样，卡拉卡拉。是的。
- Yeah, so he issues this edict in 212 called the
- 是的，所以他在公元212年颁布 了这项法令，称为……
Constitutio Antoniniana, named after him. Some people at the
安东尼尼宪法，以他的 名字命名。有些人
time called it the Divine Decree,
当时人们称之为神圣的旨意，
which basically extended citizenship to everybody. Now, we don't know exactly why
这实际上将公民权扩大到了所有人 。现在，我们还不清楚具体原因。
he did so. We can guess
他照做了。我们可以猜测
the reasons that he said he did so, and this was for religious
他解释说，他这样做 是出于宗教原因。
reasons. In other words, he wanted people to go to the temples and pray and
原因。换句话说，他 希望人们去寺庙祈祷。
give thanks to the gods for him, for his survival out of a coup.
感谢神明让他从政变 中幸存下来。
Which is whatever. And it's
随便吧。而且是
possible that there was some kind of religious motivation here, and he wanted
或许这其中存在某种宗教 动机，而他想要……
everybody to do so as Roman citizens to honor the Roman gods and something like
所有人都要像罗马公民一样这样 做，以敬奉罗马诸神等等。
that. Other historians at the time said he did it for tax reasons.
那。当时的其他历史学家认为 他这样做是为了避税。
We don't know exactly. There might even have been
我们并不确切知道 。甚至可能曾经有过
a kind of ideology of a unified community across
一种跨越界限的统一 社群的意识形态
the empire playing in his, if not in his mind, in that of
帝国在他心中，即便不是在他的脑海 里，也在他自己的世界里上演。
the jurists, that is the legal advisors that he had. So that's possible. But
法学家，也就是他的法律顾问 。所以这是有可能的。但
less interesting than his motivations, more interesting are the
他的动机固然有趣 ，但更有趣的是……
consequences of this— ... and what it tells us about the Roman community. So
由此产生的后果——以及它告诉我们 关于罗马社会的一些信息。所以
imagine a situation where, like, no modern empire has ever done this really, right?
想象一下，像这样的现代帝国从来 没有真正做过的事情，对吧？
When what's significant about the Roman case is that not only did they extend
罗马案例的意义在于 ，他们不仅扩展了
citizenship to everybody, but they meant it. This is something that had teeth. In
给予所有人公民权，而且他们是认真 的。这是个长着牙齿的东西。在
other words, it meant that the rights and opportunities that were available to
换句话说，这意味着…… 所享有的权利和机会
Roman citizens, say, in the Roman Senate at Rome—
比如说，罗马公民，在 罗马的罗马元老院——
... are now available to everybody. And within a generation, you have a situation
现在所有人都可以使用。短短一代 人的时间，就会出现这种情况。
where, like, all of the emperors are provincials,
比如，所有的皇帝 都是外省人。
right? All the most powerful people in the empire are from the provinces.
正确的？帝国中最有权势 的人都来自各省。
- This is, like, mind-breaking, mind-blowing. This is incredible.
这简直太不可思议了，令人 震惊。这太不可思议了。
The fact that the Roman Empire was able to do this, and it stuck.
罗马帝国能够做到这一点，而且 这种做法一直延续了下来。
- They did it, and they meant it.
他们做到了，而且他们是认真的。
- And they meant it. They implemented it. It was real.
——而且他们是认真的。 他们执行了。这是真的。
That's, that tells you, that's an important thing that tells you a
这说明，这是一件很重要 的事，它告诉你……
lot of information about the populace of the Roman Empire.
包含大量关于罗马 帝国民众的信息。
That the, the fact that it stuck, that the government meant it,
也就是说，它最终得以实施 ，政府是认真的。
that the system encouraged, incentivized the government to mean it.
该制度鼓励并激励 政府认真对待此事。
It's incredible.
真是不可思议。
- Yeah, and there's a law of citizenship, and it, basically it says something like,
- 是的，还有一条公民法， 它基本上是这样规定的：
"Anyone born within the Roman Empire is a Roman citizen."
“凡出生在罗马帝国境内 的人都是罗马公民。”
And the Roman jurists and policymakers who were behind,
而幕后的罗马法学家 和政策制定者们，
This had some very interesting ideas about, you know, creating this kind of
这其中有一些非常有趣的想法，比如 ，如何创造这种类型的事物。
community. Look, like, imagine if, I mean, it's almost
社区。你看，想象一下， 我的意思是，几乎
impossible to, to imagine, but the, the British at the
难以想象，但是 ，英国人
time of the peak of the empire bestowed British citizenship on
在帝国鼎盛时期，英国 公民身份被授予……
everyone, including in India, and, like,
包括印度在内的所有人，以及，
suddenly made positions of power in London available to
突然间，伦敦的权力 职位向他们开放。
people from India, like, including the throne. Like, it's just unthinkable.
来自印度的人，包括王位 。简直难以置信。
And that has to do, you know, with race and colonialism and all kinds of things, right?
你知道，这和种族、殖民主义以及 各种各样的事情都有关系，对吧？
But not in the Roman Empire. So we have a situation where
但在罗马帝国并非如此。所以 我们面临这样一种情况：
the emperors are all from the provinces. The most powerful officials are
这些皇帝都是来自外省的。 最有权势的官员是
all from the provinces. And so a century later,
全部来自各省。 一个世纪后，
when Constantinople is created, this is, it's created,
君士坦丁堡建成之时，也就 是它被建成之时。
right, like, in, in the Bosporus, so, like, where modern Istanbul is,
对，就像在博斯普鲁斯海峡，也就 是现代伊斯坦布尔所在的位置。
in the Eastern Roman Empire. It's created within the preexisting Roman
在东罗马帝国。它是在既 有的罗马框架内创建的。
context, right? It doesn't bring Romanness to the East. It's already there.
上下文很重要，对吧？它并没有把罗马风情 带到东方。它已经在那里了。
And so it's not such a leap to create a center of Roman power
因此，建立一个罗马 权力中心并非难事。
in the East because of that.
正因如此，东方的情况也是如此。
- And you've helped put together a book on the history of intellectual thought in the East Roman Empire.
——而且你还参与编写了一本关于 东罗马帝国思想史的书籍。
But this is the interesting thing here, and I can ask that many
但有趣的是，我可以问 很多人这个问题。
times, but let me ask it here also, is the great man, the
很多时候，但我想在这里也问 一下，这位伟人，是……
great woman view of history.
一位伟大女性的历史观。
Were there, like, Thomas Jefferson or those types of characters in the meetings
会议上有没有像托马斯 ·杰斐逊那样的人物？
as they're executing on the edict or developing
当他们执行法令 或制定法令时
the edict? Is that important, or is it more about the system and the culture and
法令？这重要吗？还是说， 更重要的是制度和文化？
just, uh—
呃——
... is it, how important was it? 'Cause this seems like a revolutionary idea, and when
……它到底有多重要？因为这看起来 像是一个革命性的想法，而且当
we think about the American Revolution and the, the founding documents, it seems
我们想到美国革命 和建国文献，似乎
like a few individuals—
就像某些人一样——
... were really critical about the wording of things, and then words matter
他们对措辞非常挑剔 ，而措辞确实很重要。
because those words create the reality, and then it propagates through time.
因为这些话语创造了现实，然后现实 随着时间的推移而传播开来。
- Yeah. For the edict, I suspect that yes, there were a few people who were behind
- 是的。至于那项法令，我怀疑 确实有一些人在背后操纵。
it, and quite possibly jurists, that is Roman legal scholars.
它，以及很可能还有法学家， 也就是罗马的法律学者。
And, and 212 is in an age of very important
而且，212 正处于一个 非常重要的时代。
Roman legal scholars Ulpian, for example, and others.
例如罗马法学家乌尔比安 等人。
But we just don't have those... We, we have- ... minutes of the meetings for the-
但是我们没有那些……我们， 我们有——……会议记录——
... American Revolution.
美国革命。
Not only do we not know who was in the room, we don't actually even have the whole
我们不仅不知道房间里都有谁， 我们甚至连全部情况都不清楚。
edict. We have a papyrus fragment, this is a piece of ancient paper—
法令。我们有一块莎草纸残片 ，这是一张古代纸张——
... that's mostly torn and mutilated, and we have, like, a bit of a
……那东西大部分都破损不堪， 我们还有，嗯，一点点
paragraph from it.
从中摘录一段。
Um, in Greek, not even the Latin original. And it's kind of torn,
嗯，是希腊语，甚至不是拉丁语 原文。它有点撕裂，
but it actually preserves the key clause. Right? And that's,
但它实际上保留了关键条款 。正确的？就是这样。
that's all we have of the original. We have contemporary sources that
这就是我们所拥有的原件的全部 内容。我们有当代资料显示，
mention it, we have legal documents, but nothing like a,
提到这一点，我们有法律 文件，但没有类似的东西。
Like we can talk about the people involved in it. Or even
比如我们可以谈谈参与 其中的人员。甚至
how it was immediately implemented. Like, suddenly we know everyone in the
它是如何立即得到实施的。突然 之间，我们好像认识了所有人。
provinces, like, there's this explosion in the number of people called
比如，各个省份的人口数量出现了爆炸式 增长，这些人被称为
Aurelius, because that was his Roman family name.
奥勒留，因为那是他的 罗马家族姓氏。
Um, and so when you acquired citizenship from that edict, you became an Aurelius.
嗯，所以当你通过那项法令获得公民权 时，你就成了奥勒留家族的一员。
Right? And there are lots of Aurelii suddenly all over the place. Like, we can see it
正确的？突然间到处都是叫奥雷利 的人。比如，我们可以看到它
immediately. Uh, but we can't actually see the implementation.
立即地。呃，但我们实际上 看不到具体的实现方式。
- But your instinct says that individuals were very important
但你的直觉告诉你 ，个人非常重要。
in the development of that idea and execution of it.
在构思和执行该想法 的过程中。
- Probably, yeah. Yeah. Even though it's part of a long-term process
- 大概是吧。是的。尽管这是 一个长期过程的一部分。
of expanding Roman citizenship, this was a, an explosion, not just an expansion.
罗马公民权的扩张是一次爆发 ，​​而不仅仅是扩张。
- And then you said that one of the important aspects about this edict is
然后您说，这项法令 的一个重要方面是
that giving equal rights to provincials
赋予省民平等权利
was one of the things that helped deal with the
这是有助于应对以下 情况的方法之一：
crisis of the third century, and was the thing that,
三世纪的危机，以及 那件事，
I think you said, quote, "sapped discontent from the
我想你说过，引用一下 ，“削弱了不满情绪
relevant populations," which then minimized the probability of uprisings.
相关人群”，从而最大限度 地降低了起义的可能性。
- Well, now that's a very long-term process.
嗯，那可是一个非常长期的过程。
Now, the third century is chaos, there's a crisis, it's a mess, right?
现在，三世纪一片混乱， 危机四伏，一团糟，对吧？
So what follows the edict is quite a few decades of unrest.
因此，该法令颁布后，随之而来 的是长达数十年的动荡不安。
- Okay, let's put it in mildly.
- 好吧，我们委婉一点。
Let's talk about the crisis of the third century, where
我们来谈谈三世纪 的危机，当时
26 emperors were murdered in a period of 50 years.
50年间，共有26位 皇帝被谋杀。
- Yes. It's tremendous instability.
- 是的。它极不稳定。
- So there's civil wars nonstop. Almost all were,
所以内战没完没了。几乎 所有人都是这样。
of these emperors were generals, and almost all were murdered by their men.
这些皇帝大多是将军，几乎 都被自己的部下谋杀了。
So civil war was the norm, hyperinflation, economic crash, plus there's a plague-
所以内战成了常态，恶性通货膨胀 ，经济崩溃，再加上瘟疫——
... from 249 to 262 AD, which is a pandemic, possibly smallpox or Ebola. It
……公元 249 年至 262 年，爆发了一场 大流行病，可能是天花或埃博拉病毒。它
killed up to 5,000 people a day in Rome alone, devastating the
仅在罗马，每天就有多达5000人丧生 ，造成了毁灭性的打击。
tax base and army recruitment pool. And the empire
税收基础和军队征兵库 。以及帝国
fractured into three pieces, but then Emperor,
分裂成三块， 但后来皇帝，
Aurelian miraculously reconquered them in a period of five years.
奥勒良奇迹般地在五年 内重新征服了他们。
So just a lot of chaos. It deserves the name, the Crisis of the Third Century.
一片混乱。它当之无愧地被 称为“三世纪危机”。
- Yeah, it's a perfect storm. Yeah, I mean, you have a crisis of imperial legitimacy.
- 是的，这是一场完美风暴。是的，我的意思 是，你们正面临帝国合法性危机。
Basically, the army's proclaiming emperors left and right. In an odd sense,
基本上，军队到处都在拥立 皇帝。从某种意义上说，
ironically, this is in part because there are now a lot more
具有讽刺意味的是，部分 原因正是因为现在有更多了。
stakeholders in the Roman tradition, right? There's all of these provincial armies,
罗马传统的利益相关者，对吧 ？到处都是地方军队，
and they're appointing their generals as rival emperors.
他们竟然拥立自己的将军 为敌对的皇帝。
But you also have a serious uptick in foreign invasions.
但外国入侵事件 也大幅增加。
In the north, you have the creation of the Sasanian Persian or
在北方，你会看到萨珊波斯 王朝的建立，或者
Iranian Empire in the east, and this was very, very bellicose.
东方的伊朗帝国，是一个非常 、非常好战的国家。
So lots of foreign defeats. Armies are defeated by
所以输给了很多外国球队 。军队被击败
you know, like, quote, "barbarian enemies." You have eventually
你知道，就像，引用一下，“ 野蛮的敌人”。你最终会
inflation, and you have plague. And so under the pressure, right, of all of those
通货膨胀，再加上瘟疫。所以 ，在所有这些压力之下，对吧？
forces, it almost fell apart. Now, it didn't actually.
在各种压力下，它几乎崩溃了 。但实际上并没有。
Inevitably, there are also historians who downplay the crisis. Of course,
不可避免地，也有一些历史学家 淡化了这场危机。当然，
right, like, and legitimately so, right? We must push back against every of these
对，确实如此，而且理所当然，对 吧？我们必须反击所有这些行为。
characterizations.
特征描述。
- 26 emperors died, bro. What do you-
兄弟，一共死了26位皇帝。你是什​​么-
- That's just the emperors. That's just the emperors. We should be
那只是皇帝们而已。那只是 皇帝们而已。我们应该
- I'm sorry. In 50 years.
- 对不起。 50年后。
- Yeah.
- 是的。
- Every other year, emperor dead.
每隔一年，皇帝就会驾崩。
- Yeah, that's-
- 是的，那就是-
- Civil war
内战
- ... that's political instability at the top, right? But what-
——那就是高层政治不稳定 ，对吧？但是什么？
- Right, that's not-
- 对，那不是-
- ... what are the l- the lives of most people?
……大多数人的生活 是什么样的？
- Sure.
- 当然。
- So if you go to Egypt, for example, which is kind of out of the... Right?
- 例如，如果你去埃及 ，那有点……对吧？
What's going on there? How are people living there? And we can see how people are living in Egypt
那里发生了什么事？那里的人们生活状况如何 ？我们可以看到埃及人民的生活状况。
because we have all these papyrus documents from Egypt.
因为我们拥有所有这些 来自埃及的莎草纸文献。
- That's true.
- 这是真的。
- And for the most part, they don't seem to be experiencing a crisis.
而且，就目前来看，他们 似乎并没有经历危机。
- I mean, this is something you talk about. Constantine, as we'll get to him,
我的意思是，这是你们会谈论的话题 。君士坦丁，我们稍后会提到他。
is one of the most murderous leaders in all of human
是人类历史上最残暴 的领导人之一。
history, if you consider his own family. But
如果把他自己的家庭也算在内 ，那将是一段历史。但
if you're living in the provinces, you know, there's... He's not-
如果你住在外省，你知道， 那里……他不是——
- Oh, yeah, yeah.
- 哦，是啊，是啊。
- ... he's not that murderous.
……他并没有那么嗜杀。
- No, no, no, he's perfectly fine. Yeah, yeah.
- 不，不，不，他很好。 是啊是啊。
- So it's very important to actually remember about what the actual experience of
所以，记住实际体验是 什么非常重要。
the average citizen of the empire is like. Fair. Okay, so but how... Maybe there's
帝国的普通公民就像……公平的。好吧 ，但是怎么做呢……也许有办法
more we could say about the crisis. And then of course, the, the
关于这场危机，我们还有很多 话要说。当然，还有，
crisis is in part resolved by Diocletian as
戴克里先在一定程度 上解决了这场危机。
he does a hard reset on the structure on the Roman system of
他对罗马体系的结构 进行了彻底的重置。
government. So maybe you could speak a little bit more to the crisis that's
政府。所以，您或许可以 再多谈谈这场危机……
important for us to understand, and how Diocletian solves the crisis in 284 AD.
了解这一点对我们来说很重要，以及戴克里 先在公元 284 年是如何解决这场危机的。
- Right. So again, these are processes rather than specific events.
- 正确的。所以，这些是过程 ，而不是具体事件。
- Sure.
- 当然。
- So for example, you mentioned that the empire kind of breaks into pieces.
例如，你提到帝国逐渐 分崩离析。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- And we have what's called sometime the Empire of the Gauls.
——我们还有有时被 称为高卢帝国的政权。
Gaul are modern France and sort of Britain, for a while are, for
高卢地区就是现代法国，某种程度上也算是 英国的一部分，至少在一段时间内是这样。
a decade and a half or so, are kind of like this little separatist-
大约十五年左右，有点像这 种小型分离主义——
empire. So what's interesting about that is that this was
帝国。所以有趣 的是，这是
not an attempt to break away from the empire. In other words,
并非试图脱离帝国 。换句话说，
it's not some discontent provincials who are just tired of Roman
并非是一些心怀不满的外省 人厌倦了罗马。
rule and wanna break away and do their own thing. No.
他们想统治，但又想脱离统治 ，做自己的事情。不。
This is actually just a, it's an attempt by,
这实际上只是， 这是一次尝试，
provincial generals to take the throne, and do so to rule the entire
各省将军将夺取 王位，统治整个
empire. It doesn't work. They get only as far as the provinces that they take.
帝国。它不起作用。他们只能 到达他们占领的那些省份。
And the only way that they know to set up a state is to make it a Roman state.
他们唯一知道的建立国家的方式 就是建立一个罗马式的国家。
Right? Like, that's the total of their political imaginary is like, "Well,
正确的？就好像，他们的政治想象力总和 是这样的，“好吧，
we're just gonna do a Roman thing here."
我们打算搞点罗马式的仪式。
And maybe we'll get, you know, we'll reunite the
也许我们会，你知道 ，我们会重新团聚
empire ourselves, or as happened, Aurelian, that is someone from the other
我们自己建立帝国，或者像奥勒良 那样，成为另一个帝国的统治者。
side, will reunite the empire. But it's always a Roman model. Like, there's,
一方将重新统一帝国。但它始终 是罗马模式。比如，有，
it's almost like there's no alternatives by this point. So that's interesting.
到了现在，似乎已经别无 选择了。这很有意思。
What Diocletian does essentially is,
戴克里先所做的本质上是：
The, the way I characterize it sometimes is that he
我有时是这样 描述的：他
turns the problem into its own solution.
将问题本身转化为解决方案。
In other words, the problem is too many emperors or wanna-be emperors.
换句话说，问题在于皇帝 或想当皇帝的人太多了。
Because there's just more going on. Like, one emperor can't deal with all these problems
因为发生的事情更多了。比如，一个 皇帝不可能解决所有这些问题。
along the frontiers, with all the political problems.
边境地区，充斥着 各种政治问题。
So what he does is he deputizes some of his colleagues, people he was on
所以他的做法是，委任他的一些同事，也就是 他以前在公司的人，来担任他的代理职务。
very good terms with from the army. These are all Illyrians. They're from... By the way,
与军方关系非常好。他们都是伊利里亚人 。它们来自……顺便一提，
for a few centuries, the emperors are all from this region of the former
几个世纪以来，历任皇帝都 来自这个前帝国的地区。
Yugoslavia that's the size of Scotland. Like, that's where they all come from.
南斯拉夫的面积和苏格兰差不多 。他们都来自那里。
- Well, what explains that?
那该如何解释呢？
- Uh, the army.
呃，军队。
- Ah.
啊。
- These are military men. Sometimes hard-drinking military men.
这些人是军人。有时是嗜酒如命 的军人。
Very good at their job like Aurelian, you mentioned, right? So there's a series of
正如你提到的奥雷利安那样，他们工作 能力很强，对吧？所以有一系列
Illyrian emperors who
伊利里亚皇帝
restore stability. And the reason why there's so many Illyrian
恢复稳定性。而伊利里亚人如此 之多的原因就在于此。
emperors is because they worked their way up through the ranks of the army. And,
皇帝之所以能成为皇帝，是因为他们从军队 的普通士兵一步步晋升上来。和，
you know, the regions of Yugoslavia in, at that time are sufficiently,
你知道，当时的南斯拉夫 地区已经足够……
you know, economically underdeveloped that there's a strong incentive for,
你知道，经济欠发达地区 有很强的动机去……
for young men to go join the army because, you know, it's a living.
年轻人参军是 为了谋生。
Um, and so Illyrians become, like, kind of the backbone of the
嗯，所以伊利里亚人就 成了某种意义上的脊梁。
Roman army, and they're described as these, you know, tough Roman conservative
罗马军队，他们被描述 为强悍的罗马保守派。
types. I mean, these are, you know, these are, these are tough
类型。我的意思是，你 知道，这些，这些很难。
military guys. I say that to draw a contrast between, say,
军人。我这么说是为了 对比，比如说，
Hadrian, whom I mentioned earlier-
我之前提到的哈德良——
... you know, who was a much more sophisticated, artsy, poetic,
你知道，他是一位更加成熟、更有 艺术气息、更有诗意的人，
cosmopolitan emperor.
具有国际视野的皇帝。
- Sure.
- 当然。
- Also a hard-ass. You did not wanna mess with Hadrian. But,
——也是个强硬派。你最好 别招惹哈德良。但，
These guys from the third century are military men through and through. Like, their whole
这些来自三世纪的人，彻头彻尾都 是军人。就像，他们的整个
careers are in the army. And they have, like, the military stubble.
职业选择在军队。他们留着 那种军人特有的胡茬。
They've got these thick necks.
它们的脖子很粗。
They look angry. They've got their hands on their swords. Like, they're not
他们看起来很生气。他们已经拔出 了剑。比如，他们不是
projecting an image of sort of-
投射出某种形象——
- Yeah.
- 是的。
- ... calm and sophisticated, you know, bum-bum, you know.
- ……冷静而老练，你知道 ，咚咚，你知道。
- So, military men.
所以，是军人。
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- 是的，是的，是的。
- ... military men from Aurelian.
- ……来自奥雷利亚的军人。
- Yep. So Diocletian gets a gang of them together. They, eventually there are
- 是的。于是戴克里先召集了一群 这样的人。最终，他们会……
four. We call this the Tetrarchy. Um, and he basically allocates them to various,
四、我们称之为四元政治体制。嗯， 他基本上把它们分配给了各种……
um... This wasn't any kind of hard division of the empire.
嗯……这并非帝国 的彻底分裂。
Basically, it was a collaborative project. They each
基本上，这是一 个合作项目。他们各自
went wherever they were needed.
哪里需要他们，他们就去哪里。
- Uh, was it, is it fair to say that there was four administrative zones?
呃，这么说是否准确， 当时有四个行政区？
He allocated each one to a zone?
他把每个人都分配到了一个区域？
- Broadly. I'd say more military zones.
总的来说。我认为应该划定更多军事区。
- Okay.
- 好的。
- Um, so the administration tends to operate, it kind of humming along in the
嗯，所以行政部门的运作方式通常 是这样的：它运转得相当顺畅。
background wherever these emperors happen to be, right? This is a,
无论这些皇帝身在何处，背景 都是如此，对吧？这是，
We're talking about a period of big government now. So Diocletian creates a
我们现在正处于政府权力过大 的时期。所以戴克里先创造了
larger government, possibly a larger army, and in order to pay for that, you need more
更大的政府，可能还有更大的军队， 而为了支付这些开支，你需要更多
systematic and effective taxation-
系统有效的税收制度
- Mm-hmm.
嗯。
- ... which means you need more census, you need more bureaucracy, you need more collect...
这意味着你需要更多的人口普查，你需要更多的 官僚机构，你需要更多的收集工作……
You know? So it is an era of bigger government.
你知道？所以，这是一个政府 规模更大的时代。
- So just to linger on that point-
所以，我想再多谈谈这一点——
- Yeah.
- 是的。
- ... is it fair to say that Diocletian created the deep state? Quote, "deep state."
——……可以说戴克里先创建了深 层政府吗？引用“深层政府”的话。
So the tax collectors, the, the logistics,
所以，税务人员、后勤保障……
the thing that you've kinda hinted at, which is the separation of the civil and the
你刚才暗示的，也就是民事 和民事的分离，
military layer of society.
社会中的军事阶层。
- So the concept of a deep state, I've had discussions about that
所以关于“深层政府”的概念 ，我之前也讨论过。
with experts who work on the idea of the deep state, and I'm
我与研究“深层政府”概念 的专家们在一起，我是
not sure that I would characterize the Roman Empire that
我不确定我是否会这样描述 罗马帝国。
way, in part because while you do have big government, you do have bureaucracy, you
部分原因是，虽然政府规模庞大 ，官僚机构也很多，但你
have, you have bureaucrats who are buried in various echelons, and you
你这里有层层叠叠、官僚主义 横行的各级官员，而你
know, nobody knows exactly what they're doing and things like that,
要知道，没人确切知道自己 在做什么，诸如此类的事情。
you know, I have not come across the idea of some sort of
你知道，我还没有遇到 过某种……的想法。
sinister elements, you know, who are working within the administrative apparatus to
你知道，有一些阴险的势力 在行政机构内部活动。
undermine the emperor.
削弱皇帝的权力。
Like, from a distance occasionally, you might get glimpses of this kind of thing.
比如，偶尔从远处，你 可能会瞥见这类景象。
Diocletian, for example, once complained that, "Nobody ever tells me anything." In other words, like,
例如，戴克里先曾抱怨说：“从来没有人告诉 我任何事。”换句话说，就像，
he's so removed-
他太疏离了——
... in part from the realities of what's going on on the ground that he,
……部分原因是他所 了解的当地实际情况，
felt sometimes he'd lost touch. But I don't find this kind of idea of of
有时他觉得自己与现实脱节了 。但我并不认同这种想法。
undermining imperial power from within the bureaucracy.
从官僚机构内部 削弱帝国权力。
- Yeah, I think the, one of the ways to explain that is because, so, you
- 是的，我认为解释这一点的方法 之一是，因为，所以，你
know, in the modern day,
在现代社会，我们都知道，
democracy in quotes, there's a kind of temporary nature to the leader at the top.
如果把“民主”加上引号，那么最 高领导人的性质就具有某种暂时性。
So it's incentivized the deep state to form.
因此，这刺激了 深层政府的形成。
That, so the deep state thinks of themselves as a thing that
所以，深层政府认为 自己是一个……
propagates long-term periods of time, and then the
长期传播 ，然后
leader is a very ephemeral short, short-term thing.
领导者是一个非常短暂 、易逝的东西。
- Yeah.
- 是的。
- With a, with an emperor, technically-
- 与一位皇帝一起，严格来说——
... you can go for a long time, so it's best to be integrated deeply.
……你可以持续很长时间 ，所以最好深度融入。
With, the bureaucracy should be integrated with the leader. It makes sense.
因此，官僚机构应该与领导人融为 一体。这很有道理。
- Yeah. But also,
- 是的。但是也，
- Fair enough
- 很公平
- ... also in, in, in modern social thought or, or fear is that the deep state might
——此外，在现代社会思想中，或者说在恐惧 中，人们担心的是，深层政府可能会
be undermining, say...
比如说，在暗中破坏……
- Undermining, yeah
——破坏，没错。
- ... the democracy itself rather than, right, rather than... It can cut both ways.
——民主本身，而不 是……它有利有弊。
- But there is a bureaucracy. There is a big government.
但这里存在官僚机构 。政府规模庞大。
- Absolutely. Yeah.
- 绝对地。是的。
- There's a big machinery.
那里有一台大型机器。
- Yeah, compared to before.
是的，跟以前比起来。
- Before.
- 前。
- Yes.
- 是的。
So Diocletian creates these larger bureaucratic structures, and these are the ones that define
因此，戴克里先建立了这些更大的官僚 机构，而正是这些机构定义了……
the society that I study. So as a specialist, I focus on
我所研究的社会。所以作为 一名专家，我专注于
the period after him mostly.
他之后的那段时间主要是。
But he implemented those to solve a lot of these problems.
但他运用这些措施解决 了许多此类问题。
He was mostly successful. So in terms of generating revenue from
他总体上是成功的。因此 ，就创造收入而言
a much more troubled and kind of precarious situation in sustaining large
维持大型企业面临着更加 棘手和岌岌可危的局面。
armies and putting down these rebellions and usurpations. And he was
派遣军队镇压这些叛乱 和篡位行为。而他就是
generally successful at doing that.
通常都能成功做到这一点。
So he created the model that they kept for the next, Well, three centuries or more.
于是他创建了这个模型，他们在接下来的三 个世纪甚至更长时间里一直沿用至今。
- But a lot of the elements of that model lasted even beyond that, right?
但该模式的许多要素在那之后 仍然保留了下来，对吧？
- Yeah, like universal taxation. I'll give you an example. Up until then,
- 对，就像全民征税一样。我给 你举个例子。在此之前，
Italy was exempt from taxes. Italy was the land of the conquerors. The conquerors don't pay
意大利免税。意大利曾是征服者的 土地。征服者无需付出代价
taxes to themselves. The conquerors live off the taxes that others pay,
他们自己缴纳税款。征服者靠 掠夺他人缴纳的税款为生。
right? So Italy was this big tax haven, right?
正确的？所以意大利当时是一 个大型避税天堂，对吧？
Diocletian, Galerius, you know, his guys, these guys are from
戴克里先、伽列里乌斯，你知道 ，他们这些人，这些人来自
Illyria. They're from the Balkans.
伊利里亚。他们来自巴尔干半岛。
Like why is Italy tax-free exactly, you know? That doesn't make any sense. It's a
比如说，为什么意大利免税呢 ？这完全说不通。这是一个
very, very wealthy, prosperous part of the world, and so, no, they
这是世界上非常非常富裕、繁荣 的地区，所以，不，他们
tax Italy. So now, like, not only do all Romans have the same citizenship and
意大利征税。所以现在，不仅所有罗马人 都拥有相同的公民身份，而且
the same law, they all have the same tax system,
适用同一法律，实行 同一税收制度。
and the Diocletianic tax code, as it were, it's not a code, it sounds like
而所谓的戴克里先税法，与其说是法典 ，不如说更像是一部法律条文。
a flat tax, which for us sounds regressive.
单一税率，在我们 看来是累退税。
But by those stand- by the standards of that time, it's actually kind of
但按照当时的视角来看 ，这实际上有点……
progressive in a way.
从某种意义上说，这是进步的。
- Right.
- 正确的。
- It means that, like, even-
这意味着，即使——
- ... elites paid, like, the same, right? Yeah.
精英阶层的收入应该都 差不多吧？是的。
- So how much of all of this, everything we'll talk about in the, in
那么，所有这些，我们将在……中讨论的 所有内容，究竟有多少呢？
the coming centuries is all about taxation?
未来几个世纪都将 围绕税收展开吗？
- I think it's huge. Taxation is the heart of it.
我觉得它太大了。税收是 问题的核心。
- So I mean, the functioning, the success, the flourishing of a society,
我的意思是，一个社会的 正常运转、成功和繁荣。
the way the government works, the way the people are represented, all of it has to do,
政府的运作方式，人民的代表 方式，所有这些都息息相关。
all the civil wars and everything, it feels like taxation is at the core.
所有的内战等等，感觉 税收是问题的根源。
- Yes. Yeah. If you asked me to put my finger on one factor, it would be that.
- 是的。是的。如果非要我指出 一个关键因素，那就是这一点。
- So the taxation system, that feels like the early
所以，税收制度， 感觉就像是早期的
framework for the East Roman Empire.
东罗马帝国的框架。
- It did create a more sort of homogeneous framework, for sure.
- 可以肯定的是，它确实创建 了一种更加同质化的框架。
By the end of the third century, it's pretty much in place. What
到三世纪末，它基本 就成型了。什么
Diocletian does is a universal census,
戴克里先所做的是进行全民人口普查。
and this is continued by his successors. So every
他的继任者们也延续了 这一传统。所以每一个
taxable asset in the empire is censused. And so you can now start to have a budget.
对帝国境内的应税资产进行普查 。现在你可以开始制定预算了。
- Now, there is some element, and then you push back against that,
- 现在，存在一些因素，然后 你会对此进行反抗，
some element of Diocletian where he legally limited social and class mobility in
戴克里先的一些做法限制了 社会和阶级的流动性。
part for the taxation system, and made it, in many
税收制度的一部分，并且 在许多方面都做到了这一点。
cases, illegal to move and illegal to quit your job. For
在某些情况下，搬家是非法 的，辞职也是非法的。为了
example, as I read to guarantee the food
例如，正如我读到的，为了保证食物
supply and land tax, farmers were legally forbidden from
供应税和土地税，农民 被法律禁止……
moving away from the land they worked, so the state always knew who to
他们离开了耕作的土地，所以 国家总是知道该找谁。
tax. And then for soldiers, sons of veterans were
税。然后，对于士兵来说， 退伍军人的儿子们是
legally obligated to serve in the army to maintain troop numbers.
依法有义务服兵役以 维持军队人数。
You argue that these were tax enforcement
你认为这些是税务执法行为。
mechanisms, not a rigid caste system, and so in practice, the
机制，而非僵化的等级 制度，因此在实践中，
empire remained a society of high mobility.
帝国仍然是一个高度流动性 的社会。
- This is a complicated matter.
这是一个复杂的问题。
So let's talk, for example, about soldiers. It's probably
比如说，我们来谈谈 士兵吧。这很可能
the case that most soldiers' sons were expected to succeed them. Like most
大多数士兵的儿子都被期望继承 他们的事业。像大多数
professions where you have an apprenticeship, the son will usually
在一些需要学徒制的 行业，儿子通常会……
succeed, right? There are a number of other
成功了，对吧？ 还有一些其他的
professions that were kind of guild-like in nature like for example, shipping.
有些行业本质上有点像行 会，例如航运业。
Uh, where there were considerable assets involved in order to
呃，其中涉及大量资产 ，以便……
secure contracts for insurance purposes for the ships and so forth,
为船舶等事宜签订保险 合同，确保万无一失。
and it made sense for those assets to be, you know, passed from father to son. In other
这些资产由父亲传给儿子也是 合情合理的。在其他方面
words, and with them comes the obligation to
言语，以及随之 而来的义务
continue in that line of work. Some of these things are inherently, sort of
继续从事该领域的工作。有些事情 本质上就是某种程度上的
hereditary, and I don't think most people would have objected to it.
这是遗传的，而且我认为 大多数人不会反对。
The farmers is probably the only case
农民可能是唯一的例子。
where it might have actually involved some coercion. There was
其中可能确实涉及 一些胁迫行为。有
a category of farmers, and we don't know how many of them, who were,
这是一类农民，我们不知道其中 有多少人，他们是谁？
for fiscal purposes, bound to the land.
出于财政目的，与土地相关。
This doesn't mean they couldn't leave the land, like physically. No one's preventing them from leaving.
但这并不意味着他们不能离开这片土地，比如说 ，不能从地球上离开。没有人阻止他们离开。
But they were fiscally responsible for providing the taxes or rents or
但他们负有提供税款 或租金的财政责任。
whatever because the state wanted to have a secure
总之，因为州政府想要 一个安全的地方。
revenue stream from, say, those lands. And if... Anyway, it's, it's one of these
例如，来自这些土地的收入来源 。如果……总之，它是其中之一。
complicated situations. This did create some limitations on,
情况复杂。这确实 造成了一些限制，
on those people. And it's a topic of current research,
关于那些人。这也是目前 的研究课题之一。
these bound farmers, as it were,
这些被束缚的农民，就好像……
who are tied to the land. It's more of a... You know, someone put it that,
与土地息息相关的人。更像是…… 你知道，有人是这么说的，
you know, most of the time it's people who own the land, and in
你知道，大多数情况下， 土地的所有者是人，而且
this arrangement, it's the land that owns the people.
在这种制度下， 土地拥有人民。
- But you're saying the bigger picture thing is that there was mobility.
但你的意思是，从更宏观的角度 来看，存在流动性。
- Oh, there's considerable mobility.
- 哦，流动性相当高。
- So, so class mobility- ... and physical mobility-
所以，阶级流动性……以及 人身流动性……
... meaning people moved a... And we'll see this as from the West into the
……意思是人们迁移了……我们将看到 这种迁移是从西方进入……
East and Constantinople and all this kind of stuff.
东方、君士坦丁堡以及 所有这类地方。
- Oh, yeah. There's tons of mobility.
- 哦，是的。出行非常方便。
No, no, this is not a society where people are bound really,
不，不，这并不是一个人们 真正受到束缚的社会。
to... We, like, we don't find anybody who's, who's like, "Ah, I
嗯……我们，我们找不 到任何人会说，“啊，我
I really don't want to be a soldier. But my father was a soldier, and I'm obligated to be
我真的不想当兵。但我父亲 是军人，我有义务……
one." Like- ... like, we just don't hear those kinds of complaints-
一。“就像……就像，我们根本 不会听到这类抱怨——”
of people who don't want to be a so- Why wouldn't you want to be a soldier in the Roman Empire?
那些不想成为……的人——为什么 你不想在罗马帝国当兵？
I mean, it's got tremendous perks.
我的意思是，它有很多优点。
- Right. Right. So can we just linger on the why is it that Diocletian
- 正确的。正确的。那么，我们能否继续 探讨一下为什么是戴克里先
was able to stabilize the empire? It's like, you
成功稳定了帝国 ？就像，你
know, the crisis of the third century really threatened to tear apart everything.
要知道，三世纪的危机 真的有可能将一切撕裂。
So why did some of these things that we talked about stabilize?
那么，我们讨论的这些事情中 ，为什么有些会趋于稳定呢？
- Well, Aurelian had already united the empire territorially.
——嗯，奥勒良当时已经 在领土上统一了帝国。
So this is right before Diocletian.
所以这发生在戴克里先之前。
And what Diocletian did was put in place a system that
戴克里先所做的，是建立 了一套这样的制度：
reduced the number of rebellions. Simply by having four big guys with
减少了叛乱次数。仅仅 因为有四个大块头……
four armies, they managed to put out all of those fires, or most of them.
他们出动了四支军队，扑灭 了所有或大部分火灾。
And once you have stability, and he also beat the Persians, I
一旦局势稳定下来，而且他 还击败了波斯人，我
mean, Galerius did so starting to beat back foreign
也就是说，加莱里乌斯 开始击退外国军队。
invasions, that creates a framework for economic stability. People need
入侵，这为经济稳定创造 了框架。人们需要
To, you know, if they're going to invest in, like, land reclamation
你知道，如果他们要投资土地 开垦之类的项目的话。
or expand production, they need to know that, you know,
或者扩大生产规模，他们 需要知道，你知道，
foreigners aren't gonna come rampaging through, marauding through the, you know, stealing their
外国人不会横冲直撞，到处 劫掠，你知道的，偷东西。
cattle and, you know, enslaving them and taking them off to work on
你知道，奴役牲畜 ，把它们带走去干活
agricultural farms in Mesopotamia. Like, they need to know this.
美索不达米亚的农业农场。 他们需要知道这一点。
And if you provide that context of stability, the economic growth, the
如果你提供了稳定的环境 ，经济增长就会发生，
demographic growth will return. And Diocletian created that kind of, that context.
人口增长将会回归。戴克里 先创造了那种环境。
- So that takes us to Constantine but first a quick bathroom break, if I can.
——那么我们就来到了君士坦丁，但首先 ，如果可以的话，我想先去趟洗手间。
- Sure.
- 当然。
- Quick ten-second thank you to our sponsors. Check them out in the description. It really
- 用十秒钟的时间快速感谢我们的 赞助商。详情请见描述。真的
is the best way to support this podcast. Go to
这是支持本播客的最佳 方式。前往
lexfridman.com/sponsors. And now, dear friends,
lexfridman.com/sponsors。现在 ，亲爱的朋友们，
back to our conversation about the Eastern Roman Empire.
回到我们关于东罗马 帝国的话题。
All right, we're back, and let's talk about Constantine
好了，我们回来了，咱们 来聊聊康斯坦丁吧。
and Constantinople. Let's go to the rise of the East Roman
还有君士坦丁堡。让我们一起 回顾东罗马帝国的崛起。
Empire. Who was Constantine? Tell me about his rise
帝国。君士坦丁是谁？请你 谈谈他的崛起之路。
to power and the founding of Constantinople in 330 AD.
公元330年，他获得了权力并 建立了君士坦丁堡。
- Sure. So Constantine was the son of one of Diocletian's colleagues,
- 当然。所以君士坦丁是戴克里 先一位同僚的儿子。
so he comes from within the system.
所以他来自体制内部。
And the system was actually designed to be non-hereditary. In other words,
而且该制度的设计初衷就 是非世袭的。换句话说，
the senior emperors would retire, the junior ones would move up to the senior
年长的皇帝会退位，年轻的 皇帝会继位成为高级皇帝。
position, and then they would recruit two new ones.
担任该职位，然后他们 会招募两名新人。
And they tried to skip the dynastic element. So,
他们试图忽略王朝 因素。所以，
so it would be kind of, let's just say, kinda meritocratic, not
所以它有点像，这么说吧 ，有点像精英统治，而不是
whose son, you know, you were. Constantine was a son. He was passed over,
你知道，你是谁的儿子。君士坦丁 是儿子。他被忽略了。
but the armies liked him. He was actually quite competent.
但军队都很喜欢他。 他其实相当能干。
And so there's a series of civil wars among all of these
因此，这些国家之间 爆发了一系列内战。
successors of Diocletian, and Constantine emerges as the winner.
戴克里先的继任者们 ，最终君士坦丁胜出。
There are periods when there are quite a few of them. There are, like, six at a time, but they gra-
有些时期，这类事件会相当多 。一次大概有六个，但他们……
they gradually dwindle down to one. So
它们逐渐减少到只剩一个。所以
yeah, it's as long as you have the quarterfinals, semifinals, and then the final
是的，只要有四分之一 决赛、半决赛和决赛就行了。
war, and Constantine emerges in 324 as the sole
战争爆发，君士坦丁于 公元324年成为唯一的君主。
ruler of the entire Roman Empire. So that's who he is. He's
罗马帝国的统治者。原来他 就是这样的人。他是
definitely an insider, very, very competent
绝对是内部人士， 非常非常能干。
general at civil war. And he gradually moves eastward.
内战中的一位将军。 他逐渐向东移动。
So as he's conquering his rivals, who are often
所以，当他战胜他的对手时 ，这些对手往往……
his father-in-laws or his brother-in-laws, because these people are all
他的岳父或姐夫，因为 这些人都是
intermarried, and they have alliances, and they fall out. It's one of those kinds of
他们之间通婚，结盟，然后反目 成仇。这是那种类型的
situations. He moves eastward, and by the time he defeats his
情况。他向东进发， 当他击败他的敌人时
last rival, this uh, an emperor called Licinius, in 324 he's in the East. And
最后一个对手，呃，这位名叫李锡尼 的皇帝，在公元324年，他在东方。和
Licinius had his headquarters or one of his headquarters at
利西尼乌斯的总部或其中 一个总部设在……
this town called Byzantium. Byzantium is a
这座城市名叫拜占庭。拜占庭是一个
city right where Constantinople was founded.
这座城市正是 君士坦丁堡的发源地。
And it is at exactly the point where Europe meets Asia, so on the Bosporus.
它正好位于欧洲与亚洲的交界处 ，也就是博斯普鲁斯海峡沿岸。
And it's a very strategic location. It always had been, right? So whoever controls the straits of
而且地理位置非常优越。一直都是这样，对 吧？所以，谁控制了海峡，谁就能……
the Bosporus, yeah, we don't need to explain how important that is.
博斯普鲁斯海峡，是的，我们 无需解释它的重要性。
And Constantine decides to create a city named after himself,
于是，君士坦丁决定建立一座以 自己名字命名的城市。
Constantinople, on that spot, Byzantium. So Byzantium
君士坦丁堡，即拜占庭 。所以拜占庭
essentially ceases to exist as a city and is replaced by Constantinople,
它实际上不复存在，取而代之 的是君士坦丁堡。
AKA New Rome. So it's pretty clear that right from the beginning,
又名新罗马。所以很明显， 从一开始就是这样，
Constantine intended this to be a kind of branch
君士坦丁意图将其 作为一种分支。
office of Rome in the East, a kind of copy and paste of Rome
罗马在东方的办事处，某种 程度上是罗马的复制粘贴。
in the East, and it's a plan that his successors continued, right? Now,
在东方，他的继任者们也延续了 这一计划，对吧？现在，
there are a number of other cities in this,
这里还有其他 一些城市，
Let's say in the generation or two before this,
比如说，在此之前的 一两代人中，
that were also treated as sort of quasi-Romes. Basically,
他们也被视为某种准罗马人 。基本上，
there was this historian in the third century who said, "Well, wherever the emperor
公元三世纪有一位历史学家说：“ 嗯，无论皇帝在哪里，
is, that's Rome," right? 'Cause emperors are now itinerant.
“那就是罗马，”对吧？因为现在 的皇帝都是四处巡游的。
They're no longer staying at Rome. They're mostly on the frontier, and
他们不再住在罗马了。他们 大多居住在边远地区，而且
Constantine is one of these frontier emperors. They will sometimes visit Rome, maybe once or
君士坦丁是这些边疆皇帝之一。他们 有时会去罗马，也许一次或几次。
twice, maybe once a decade, you know, something like this.
大概每十年一次，你 知道，就是这样。
So Rome becomes something that can be sort of copied
因此，罗马就成了某种 可以被模仿的对象。
and pasted in other parts of the empire, and a bunch of other cities get
并粘贴到帝国的其他地区 ，以及许多其他城市。
called, you know, a New Rome, an Other Rome, an
你知道，它被称为新罗马 ，另一个罗马，一个
Alternative Rome, My Rome. And Constantinople
另一个罗马，我的罗马 。以及君士坦丁堡
is the last and most successful of those.
是其中最后一个，也是最成功的一个。
- So maybe can you speak geographically the importance of Constantinople? It's an interesting
那么，您能否从地理位置上谈谈君士 坦丁堡的重要性？这是一个有趣的
place 'cause it-
地方“因为它-
... when you're talking about a land so large as the West and the East, with
……当你谈论像东西方这样 幅员辽阔的土地时，
enemies, with threats from all kinds of different directions, the
敌人来自四面八 方，威胁重重。
location where the emperor sits is important.
皇帝的坐骑位置 很重要。
- Very. So look at Rome,
- 非常。所以看看罗马吧。
right? So it's right in the middle of Italy, right in the middle of the Mediterranean.
正确的？它位于意大利的中心 地带，地中海的中心地带。
Very safe location in a way, but it's very far from the frontiers.
从某种程度上来说，这里是个非常 安全的地方，但距离边境很远。
And this is a period when emperors need to be with the armies, right?
在这个时期，皇帝需要 与军队在一起，对吧？
They're not senatorial emperors who are sitting in Rome having meetings with
他们不是坐在罗马开会 的元老院皇帝。
senators. They are military emperors who are marching along the frontiers,
参议员们。他们是沿着 边疆进军的军事帝王，
mostly with generals rather than civilian administration.
主要由将军而非文职 人员管理。
So they're doing their job. Like, this is the hard
所以他们是在尽职尽责地工作 。比如，这很难
work. They're slogging through the mud of winter campaigns, right?
工作。他们正在艰难地进行 冬季战役，对吧？
Uh, they're not just sitting in a palace enjoying themselves when they could.
呃，他们可不是那种会待在 宫殿里享受生活的人。
But Rome just becomes inconvenient because of that. And if you
但正因如此，去罗马就变得 很不方便了。如果你
look at Constantinople, it is
看看君士坦丁堡，它
kind of halfway between the Danube frontier and the Euphrates frontier.
大致位于多瑙河边界和幼发拉底河 边界的中间位置。
So if you want to prioritize the East or treat it as an equal part of
所以，如果你想优先考虑东方，或者 将其视为与东方同等重要的一部分……
the Roman Empire, as these emperors all did. In fact,
罗马帝国，就像这些皇帝们 所做的那样。实际上，
almost all emperors who had a choice about whether they would stay in the East
几乎所有可以选择 是否留在东方的皇帝
or stay in the West chose the East. There's only one who
或者留在西方，选择 东方。只有一个人
chooses the West, and that's Valentinian later in the fourth century. All the others
选择西方，那就是四世纪后期 的瓦伦提尼安。其他所有人
understand that the East is where it's at.
要知道，东方才是王道。
And Constantinople is right between the Danube and the Euphrates. These are two major frontiers.
君士坦丁堡正好位于多瑙河和幼发拉底河 之间。这是两大前沿领域。
And so it allows emperors to move between the two.
因此，这使得皇帝可以在这 两个国家之间自由穿梭。
And also look at its location north, south, east, west, right? So
还要看看它位于北、南、 东、西四个方向，对吧？所以
north, south, it is the node between the Black Sea and the Mediterranean,
它横跨南北，是黑海和 地中海之间的枢纽。
right? And east, west, it's precisely where Europe meets Asia,
正确的？东、西，正 是欧亚大陆交汇之处。
right? And because there's a break there, so there's a Bosporus, the
正确的？因为那里有一段断裂带， 所以才有了博斯普鲁斯海峡。
Sea of Marmara, the Hellespont, the Roman Empire during the civil
马尔马拉海、赫勒斯滂 海峡、罗马帝国时期
wars, it would tend to break there.
战争时期，那里往往会爆发冲突。
And you would have one emperor on one side in Asia, and you would have another emperor on the other
这样一来，亚洲一边就会有一个皇帝 ，另一边就会有另一个皇帝。
side. And this just kept happening. And
边。这种情况不断发生。和
Constantinople ultimately functions as a kind of clamp that unifies this whole area,
君士坦丁堡最终起到了一种钳制 作用，将整个地区统一起来。
so basically the Balkans and Asia Minor and Syria as a kind of unit,
所以基本上，巴尔干半岛、小亚细亚 和叙利亚作为一个整体，
right? And, you know, what is a new Rome? A new
正确的？那么，你知道 ，什么是新罗马？新的
Rome is, among other things, a new senate, right? And Constantine and his successors
罗马，除其他方面外，也是一个新的元老院 ，对吧？君士坦丁及其继任者
recruit this new senate for the new
为新政府招募这支新的参议院。
Rome. So we're talking about maybe two and a half thousand, 3,000
罗马。所以我们说的可能是 两千五百到三千人。
men, you know, at, at, at its peak, and these are all
男人，你知道，在巅峰 时期，这些都是
recruited from all of these areas. You know, some come from Rome,
从所有这些地区招募人员。你 知道，有些人来自罗马。
but others come from the Aegean region, from Asia Minor,
但也有一些来自爱琴海地区 ，来自小亚细亚，
Eastern Mediterranean. So these are the wealthiest people,
东地中海地区。这些就 是最富有的人，
usually most well-connected elites from the whole Eastern Mediterranean,
通常是来自整个东地中海地区 人脉最广的精英阶层，
and they come together and form a new purpose, common purpose in Constantinople.
他们聚集在一起，在君士坦丁堡 形成一个新的共同目标。
And the empire never breaks there again.
而帝国在那里再也没有崩溃过。
Right? So it, it holds together this part of the world. The
正确的？所以，它维系着 世界的这一部分。这
breaking point now, interestingly, moves to the Adriatic,
有趣的是，现在的转折点转移 到了亚得里亚海。
right? So when, in 395, we talked about East and West kind of splitting.
正确的？所以，在 395 年， 我们谈到了东西方的分裂。
It breaks at the Adriatic 'cause Constantinople is now holding that whole
它在亚得里亚海断裂，因为 君士坦丁堡现在控制着整个地区。
Eastern world together. 'Cause all of these elites, they now, they're
东方世界团结起来。因为所有 这些精英，他们现在，他们
invested in it. They're literally investing in it. They have to invest in it in order to be
投资了。他们确实在投资这个项目 。他们必须投资才能成为
senators in Constantinople.
君士坦丁堡的元老院议员们。
So that's kind of one of the functions that it, that it performs, a strategic function.
所以，这算是它所发挥的功能 之一，一种战略功能。
There's a political function. There's also a cultural one, but you know, we can talk
这具有政治功能。还有一个文化方面的 问题，不过你知道，我们可以聊聊。
about that, too. But that's what you see there on that map, the northwest, east,
关于那件事，也一样。但你在地图上 看到的就是这些，西北部、东部，
south.
南。
- So just to linger on it, so you do a podcast,
所以，就让我再多说几句，比如 你做播客的时候，
Byzantium and Friends, but you're also a guest on podcasts, and I should mention
你主持过《拜占庭与朋友们》节目，同时 也是播客节目的嘉宾，我应该提一下。
you being a guest multiple times on the excellent The
您多次作为嘉宾参加 了精彩的节目。
History of Byzantium podcast hosted by Robin Pierson. I
由 Robin Pierson 主持的拜占庭 历史播客。我
highly recommend people listen to it, to all of your appearances. You have a lot of really
强烈推荐大家去听听，也推荐大家去 听听你的所有演出。你有很多非常
fascinating ones. But the reason I bring all that up is one of the episodes,
引人入胜的。但我之所以提起 这些，是因为其中一集：
you do the fun thing of selecting the top 10 emperors of Byzantium, and
你做了件很有趣的事：选出拜占庭 帝国十大皇帝，然后……
spoiler alert, everybody should go listen to the full list 'cause you
剧透警告，大家都应该去 听完整歌单，因为……
justify all the different options. But Constantine ends up in the number one spot.
请对所有不同的方案进行论证 。但最终康斯坦丁位居榜首。
And so can you just add a little bit more depth why he
那么，您能否再详细解释 一下他为什么会这样？
would be in your number one spot-
会成为你最优先考虑的人——
- Yes
- 是的
- ... now that we're talking about him?
既然说到他了？
- Yes. It's not because I sort of like him as a person, right? I mean-
- 是的。不是因为我喜欢他这个 人，对吧？我是说-
... as you said, he was pretty murderous.
正如你所说，他的确是个杀人狂。
Right? All those wars, so clearly ambitious, murderous, ruthless, basically.
正确的？所有这些战争，显然 都是野心勃勃、血腥残暴的。
- Can you actually speak to the murderous aspect? He seemed to have murdered a
- 你能谈谈谋杀方面的问题吗 ？他似乎谋杀了一个人
lot of people in his family.
他家人口众多。
- Yes, that's because what we call his family were also
- 是的，那是因为我们 所说的他的家人也
alliances of convenience that he made on the way to the top.
他在通往巅峰的道路 上建立的权宜联盟。
And when those alliances or, you know, those, you
而当那些联盟，或者 ，你知道，那些，你
know, those wives or those fathers-in-law were no longer convenient or,
要知道，那些妻子或那些岳父 不再方便了，或者，
or turned against him, he had no hesitation in
或者反过来对付他 ，他毫不犹豫。
removing them. But he's also, you know, he
移除它们。但你知道，他也是……
gets a little extra bonus because he also murdered his own son, Crispus, who was-
他还因为谋杀了自己的儿子克里斯帕斯而获得 了一些额外的奖励，克里斯帕斯当时是——
... apparently a very competent and popular kind of general, and we don't know why.
……显然是一位非常能干且受人爱戴 的将军，但我们不知道为什么。
He executes Crispus soon after defeating Licinius,
击败利西尼乌斯后不久， 他就处决了克里斯普斯。
and then follows it up with the murder of his wife-
然后，他又谋杀了 他的妻子。
... not Crispus' mother, and we don't know why. The funny thing is that when
……但不是克里斯帕斯的母亲，我们 也不知道为什么。有趣的是，当
emperors do this sort of thing, if there's any kind of remotely, like, a
皇帝们会做这种事，如果还 有任何类似的事情发生的话。
good reason, they'll blast it through all of the media, right? Like, "Crispus
理由充分，他们肯定会通过所有媒体 大肆宣传，对吧？比如，“Crispus
was rebelling against me," or whatever. There's nothing.
“他反抗我”，或者诸如此 类的话。什么都没有。
He doesn't even try to justify it, which means it must have been something
他甚至没有试图解释，这 意味着这其中必定有蹊跷。
unjustifiable- Like, I don't know. I can't process it.
不合理的——比如，我不 知道。我无法理解。
- And also, I read that the historians of the time would
而且，我还读到当时 的史学家们会
just ignore that that happened.
就当没发生过这件事吧。
- Yes. Well, sort of. So
- 是的。嗯，算是吧。所以
when Crispus is alive, it's all, like, praising Crispus as, "Oh,
当克里斯帕斯还活着的时候，人们都 在称赞克里斯帕斯，比如，“哦，
Constantine, you great emperor, and your wonderful son who will..." whatever.
君士坦丁，伟大的皇帝，还有你那了不起 的儿子，他将……“随便吧。
And then Crispus is executed, and he just disappears from the, like-
然后克里斯帕斯被处决了， 他就这么消失了，就像——
... they never talk about him.
他们从来不谈论他。
- Yeah. Actually, as another side to a side, I think you mentioned,
- 是的。实际上，作为另一 方面，我认为你提到过，
Whether it's on your podcast or elsewhere, that if, if you had
无论是在你的播客节目中还是其他 地方，如果，如果你曾经
to have a beer with any of the emperors, that you probably wouldn't.
和任何一位皇帝一起喝啤酒 ，你大概都不会这么做。
So it's not like some of the most impactful, some of the
所以它不像某些最有 影响力的，某些
most influential and great emperors that we talk about,
我们所谈论的最具影响力 和最伟大的皇帝们，
they might not be very pleasant people.
他们可能不是很讨人喜欢的人。
- So let's set aside whether you'd like to have a beer with these people. The reason I put
所以我们暂且不讨论你是否愿意和这些人一起喝 啤酒。我之所以这样写，是因为我把……
Constantine at the top of the list is because the decisions that he made were so
君士坦丁位列榜首，是因为 他做出的决定如此重要。
consequential, just important, and
后果严重的，非常重要的，而且
for the most part, not bad decisions. So I couldn't not put him at the
大部分情况下，都不是糟糕的决定。所以 我不能不把他放在那个位置。
top of the list. The, you know, the creating
名列榜首。你 知道，创造
Constantinople and converting to Christianity and setting the empire on a path
君士坦丁堡皈依基督教， 使帝国走上正轨
to conversion, these are major, like, world history level decisions.
对皈依基督教而言，这些都是重大 的、堪比世界历史层面的决定。
Right? Now, not many emperors do that. In fact, Constantine is in,
正确的？现在，很少有皇帝会这样做 。事实上，君士坦丁已经参战了。
like, his own league when it comes to those kinds of decisions.
在这些决定方面，他简直 是独树一帜。
My other criteria for top emperors were basically those who did the job well,
我评判顶级皇帝的其他标准基本上 就是那些把工作做好的人。
right? Not making, you know, these kinds of earth, you know, shattering
正确的？不制造，你知道， 这种地球，你知道，破碎
decisions or, you know, world history changing decisions, but just
一些决定，或者说，一些改变 世界历史的决定，但仅仅是
who performed the role competently with
能够胜任该角色的人
results that impacted the lives of their subjects for the better.
研究结果对受试者的生活 产生了积极影响。
So those are the other criteria that I used.
以上就是我使用 的其他标准。
It's difficult to juggle these different criteria, right, in order to create a
要兼顾这些不同的标准 确实很难，对吧？
systematic list. And by the way, we, historians generally don't do these kinds of things.
系统列表。顺便说一句，我们历史学家 一般不会做这类事情。
But you said it's fun. It is fun.
但你说这很有趣。很有趣。
- It was fun. It was fun.
很有趣。很有趣。
- And it allows you to talk about certain things that you might not otherwise do.
——而且它还能让你谈论一些你 平时可能不会谈论的事情。
So yeah, that's why Constantine was at the top.
所以，这就是君士 坦丁位居顶峰的原因。
- So you mentioned Christianity. That was one other big component of his
- 所以你提到了基督教。那是他性格 的另一个重要组成部分。
rule. What was the role of Christianity in, in Constantine's life,
规则。基督教在君士坦丁的一生中 扮演了怎样的角色？
in the lives of the citizens of the new Roman Empire?
在新生的罗马帝国公民 的生活中？
- At this stage, Christianity doesn't have a role. It actually took the emperors...
- 在现阶段，基督教没有发挥作用 。实际上，这需要皇帝们……
When the emperors took it on board, that is, they made it a part
也就是说，当皇帝们接受它时， 他们就把它纳入了其中。
of the imperial system, then it began to acquire a role
在帝国体系中，它开始 扮演重要角色。
within the system. Previously, it had imagined itself as having its
在系统内部。此前，它 曾设想自己拥有……
own history, like not necessarily part of the
自己的历史，不一定 是……的一部分
empire or affiliated with imperial power. But
帝国或与帝国政权 有关联的。但
after Constantine, it does acquire a role.
在君士坦丁之后，它确实扮演了一定的角色。
- And so actually, one way to ask that question, which is fascinating, 'cause you said that there's
所以，实际上，问这个问题的一种 方式很有意思，因为你说有……
like, there's Rome, and then there's like cultures like,
比如，有罗马，然后还有其他 一些文化，比如……
or traditions like Christianity, or being Greek, that kind of thing.
或者像基督教之类的传统，或者 像希腊文化之类的。
So, one of the ways to ask this question is does Christianity
所以，问这个问题的一种方式 是：基督教是否……
triumph over Rome, or did Rome capture Christianity?
是基督教战胜了罗马，还是 罗马征服了基督教？
- Right. Yes. That's a—
- 正确的。是的。那是一个——
- Which is the mechanism?
- 具体机制是什么？
- I would lean more toward the second. In other words, that the religion was
我更倾向于第二个。换 句话说，这种宗教是
co-opted by the imperial system. Now, there are many areas in which
被帝国体制所吞并 。现在有很多领域
that's not the case and where the opposite happens, so I'm not going to be absolute about it,
事实并非总是如此，有时情况恰恰 相反，所以我不会对此妄下断言。
but I think it's very important to recognize that because
但我认为认识到这一点 非常重要，因为
Christianity generates this narrative of triumph-
基督教创造了这 种胜利的叙事——
...right, which modern historians perpetuate,
……没错，现代历史学家们 也一直沿用这种观点。
and it's framed in very particular ways. In other words, that Christianity triumphs over the
而且它的呈现方式非常独特。 换句话说，基督教战胜了……
ancient religions. Right? So displacing Zeus and Apollo and all of
古代宗教。正确的？所以，宙斯 、阿波罗以及所有……都被取代了。
that, and animal sacrifice is gone, and like, that's because Christianity
那样的话，动物献祭就消失 了，这都是因为基督教。
triumphs, and that's a very narrow way of looking at it. In other words, you pick your
胜利，这是一种非常狭隘的看法 。换句话说，你选择你的
enemy, and then you can defeat that enemy, right?
然后你就可以打败 敌人，对吧？
But if you look in the other direction, there's, like, the Roman imperial state, and you
但如果你往另一个方向看，就会 看到罗马帝国，然后你
cannot say that Christianity either triumphed over it or
既不能说基督教战胜了它， 也不能说它战胜了它。
even tamed it or anything. It actually became part of it.
甚至驯服它什么的。它实际上 成为了其中的一部分。
in many ways that, you know, determined its history for
在很多方面，你知道， 这决定了它的历史。
centuries and, in fact, down to today.
几个世纪以来，事实上，一直延续至今。
So this is very different, for example, from the history of Islam.
所以，这与伊斯兰教 的历史截然不同。
So Islam comes into existence without a
所以伊斯兰教的出现并没有……
preexisting state to receive it and take it on board. It
预先存在的接收和 接受状态。它
creates its own state, right? So the Muslim armies,
它自己创造一个状态， 对吧？所以穆斯林军队，
they conquer this empire, and then they have to sort of govern it.
他们征服了这个帝国，然后 他们就不得不统治它。
They think according to whatever Islamic principles. The Quran doesn't say anything about
他们按照伊斯兰教义思考。 《古兰经》对此只字未提。
running an empire.
经营一个帝国。
So that creates a completely different society, right, where, like,
所以这就创造了一个完全不同的社会，对 吧，在这个社会里，比如，
Islam is a, is really a primary kind of identity and,
伊斯兰教是一种，实际上 是一种主要的身份认同，
like, drives a lot of developments. But Christianity comes into
例如，它推动了很多发展。但 基督教也随之而来。
existence within a very well-developed society and, and
生活在一个高度 发达的社会中，并且
political system. Now, here's the thing.
政治制度。事情是这样的。
We don't know exactly how many Christians existed in the time of Constantine.
我们并不确切知道君士坦丁 时代有多少基督徒。
Well, we speculate maybe 10% of the empire. That might be very
我们推测，或许占帝国 的10%。那可能非常
high, right? But even if it's 10%, it's
很高，对吧？但即使是10%，也是
not a lot, and these are not, like, elites for the most part. Maybe
不多，而且这些人大多也 不是精英阶层。或许
middle, you know, what we loosely call middle class,
中产阶级，你知道，就是我们 通常所说的中产阶级。
a few elites, a few slaves, like this kind of thing.
少数精英，少数奴隶 ，喜欢这种东西。
Mostly urban, and keeping in mind, most of the population is rural.
大部分是城市地区，但需要注意的 是，大部分人口居住在农村。
Right? So pockets of concentrated, you know,
正确的？所以，你知道 ，一些集中的区域
Christian groups in cities. That's what we're talking about. Not terribly
城市里的基督教团体。这就 是我们讨论的内容。还不错
politically powerful.
政治影响力强大。
- So Constantine's conversion to Christianity and moving the empire towards Christianity is
所以，君士坦丁皈依基督教并 推动帝国向基督教化是……
not something where it's a gigantic majority of the people-
并非绝大多数人 都认同的事情——
... or it's a political convenience because it's the elites. It's something else.
或者这只是出于政治便利，因为牵涉到 的是精英阶层。这是另一回事。
I mean, it's, I mean, a pretty revolutionary decision, I would say.
我的意思是，这真是一 个相当具有革命性的决定。
- Exactly. Now, there used to be theories that Constantine did this for, like,
- 确切地。过去曾有理论认为， 君士坦丁这样做是为了……
pragmatic, cynical reasons, that he, like, wasn't a true Christian or anything, but there
出于务实和愤世嫉俗的原因，认为他可能并非 真正的基督徒之类的，但事实并非如此。
was some kind of political gain to be had here. But I have never
这里面肯定有某种政治 利益可图。但我从未
read a convincing account of what exactly that political gain is.
阅读一篇令人信服的论述，了解 这种政治收益究竟是什么。
We now know that there are fewer Christians. They were not
我们现在知道基督徒人数 减少了。他们并非如此
that influential. You can make an argument that bishops are a kind of
那很有影响力。你可以 论证主教是一种……
convenient social influencers, you might say. Like, you can use those.
可以说，他们是方便的社交媒体 影响者。比如，你可以用那些。
They're not a threat to your position.
他们不会对你的地位构成威胁。
Right? So a bishop is not gonna try to take the throne.
正确的？所以主教 不会试图篡夺王位。
So they're not dangerous political operatives in that way. But they
所以从这个意义上讲，他们并不 是危险的政治活动家。但他们
do have some influence over sectors of society, and so that might be
确实对社会某些领域有一定的 影响力，所以这可能是
a... Okay, I see that, but I don't quite see the
嗯……好吧，我明白 了，但我不太明白……
argument for, like, going full Christian,
支持彻底皈依基督教的理由
Just to get the support of some bishops, who actually pretty quickly turn out to be,
只是为了获得一些主教的支持， 而这些主教很快就被证明是……
some of them, more trouble than they're worth.
有些东西弊大于 利。
Anyway, so I have not yet seen a convincing
总之，我还没有看到 令人信服的……
like, political argument for Constantine's decision, which means that you then
比如，为君士坦丁的决定提供 政治论据，这意味着你
fall back on a personal explanation that he did this
他转而用个人解释来 说明他这么做的原因。
because he was a believing Christian, right? And he came out,
因为他是一位虔诚的基督徒 ，对吗？他出来了，
You know, in support of the religion that he held, and that's kind of
你知道，这是为了支持他所信仰 的宗教，这有点……
where most scholars are today. Though, I gotta tell you,
如今大多数学者都身处此地 。不过，我得告诉你，
historians are very uncomfortable about personal choice, like explaining
历史学家对个人选择，比如解释 个人选择，感到非常不自在。
history in terms of these kinds of personal choices.
从这类个人选择的角度来 看，历史是怎样的呢？
Because Constantine's conversion is like, it's massive. It
因为君士坦丁的皈依 意义重大。它
opens the door. It incentivizes so many people to also convert.
打开门。它激励了很多 人也进行转化。
'Cause Romans will generally do what their, you know, rulers
因为罗马人通常会服从 他们的统治者。
will tell them. If we've mentioned Hadrian a few times
我会告诉他们。如果我们 已经多次提到哈德良
Hadrian's, he had this lover, Antinous, Greek boy from Bithynia,
哈德良有个情人，名叫安提诺乌斯 ，是来自比提尼亚的希腊男孩。
who died in an accident in Egypt, whatever, and Hadrian said
不管是谁在埃及死于意外 ，哈德良说道
Basically that Antinous should be regarded as a god throughout the empire.
基本上，安提诺乌斯应该 在整个帝国被视为神。
And he was. We have, like, more statues and busts of Antinous from all of
而他确实是。我们拥有比世界各地更多 的安提诺乌斯雕像和半身像。
these temples all over the empire than I think of anyone else except Hadrian.
帝国境内遍布这些神庙，在我看来，除了 哈德良之外，没有人比他建造得更好。
So yeah, if, if the emperor says, like, "This is a person who's a god now, you know, put
所以，如果，如果皇帝说，“这个人现在 是神了，你知道，放他走吧。”
statues of him everywhere," they will.
“到处都会有他的雕像，”他们会的。
And when Constantine comes out in favor of Christianity, you know, suddenly people
当君士坦丁公开支持基督教 时，你知道，突然间人们
discover that, oh, this is an interesting rite. It's got the support of the emperor.
发现，哦，这是一个有趣的仪式 。它得到了皇帝的支持。
- So one of the things here, going to the Perplexity, Constantine's conversion to Christianity is
所以，这里要讨论的一件事，就是君士坦丁皈依基督教 ，也就是所谓的“迷途指日可待”事件。
usually dated to 312 AD,
通常可追溯至公元312年，
Linked to a visionary experience before the Battle of the Milvian
与米尔维安战役前的 一次幻象体验有关
Bridge. Do you believe that vision, that he had this religious experience before the
桥。你相信他之前有过 那种宗教体验吗？
Battle of the Milvian Bridge? Here it says, "But historians debate
米尔维安桥之战？这里写道：“但 历史学家们对此争论不休。”
both its nature and its sincerity."
它的本质和真诚。
- Well-
- 出色地-
- Do you believe the sincerity of that experience?
你相信那次经历的 真实性吗？
- Before we even get to the sincerity-
——在我们谈到真诚之前——
... is the problem of the sources. This is reported by authors writing later
……问题出在信息来源上。这 是后来的作者们所报道的。
in the aftermath of a victory when the emperor... Like,
在胜利之后，当皇帝 ……比如，
one of them had a dinner conversation with the emperor a few decades later, and he
几十年后，其中一人与皇帝共 进晚餐并进行了交谈，他
said, "Well, let me tell you about the Milvian Bridge." And it's like, okay, I'm not gonna believe that.
他说：“好吧，让我来给你讲讲米尔维安桥的故事 吧。”我当时就想，好吧，我不相信。
I'm not gonna take that at face value, rather.
我不会轻易相信 表面现象。
It's a much more complicated... You know, this is how the emperor
这要复杂得多……你知道， 这就是皇帝的行事方式。
wants things to be remembered.
希望人们记住某些事情。
That's different. Also, Constantine tended to have a lot of religious visions.
那不一样。此外，君士坦丁 还经常出现宗教幻象。
He had had religious visions of Apollo before Christ, and we have
在基督诞生之前，他就曾有过关于 阿波罗的宗教异象，而我们也有
sources that talk about that, too, that he went to this temple in Gaul, and Apollo appeared to
还有一些资料也提到，他去了高卢的 一座神庙，阿波罗在那里显灵。
him in the form of light. Okay, Constantine has a religious vision every time
以光的形式出现。好吧，君士坦丁 每次都有宗教幻象
he kind of wants to shift policies. And his, like,
他似乎想改变政策。 而他的，就像，
profile. Like, when he wanted to break away from his other emperors
轮廓。比如，当他想要 脱离其他皇帝的统治时
who used to go for the, like, they went for this kind of Jupiter/Hercules model.
以前那些喜欢木星/赫拉克勒斯模型 的人，他们喜欢的就是这种模型。
And he shifted to an Apollo model. This is a branding. This is emperors doing
于是他改用了阿波罗型发动机。这是 品牌推广。这是皇帝的所作所为。
branding.
品牌塑造。
- So we should say that, as you've described, Constantine is a
所以我们应该说，正如你所描述 的，君士坦丁是一位
pragmatist. He's very pragmatic.
实用主义者。他非常务实。
- Yeah.
- 是的。
- But you're saying it's fair to believe, based on the
但你的意思是，基于以下事实， 相信这一点是合理的：
evidence, that he actually converged towards being a Christian believer.
有证据表明，他实际上逐渐 成为了一名基督教信徒。
- Yeah. It's very possible, in fact plausible, that he thought
- 是的。他这么想，其实很有可能 ，甚至可以说是合情合理的。
the Christian God had helped him in battle. And,
基督教的上帝在战斗 中帮助了他。和，
you know, for someone like him, that's as good a reason as any to support that god.
你知道，对于像他这样的人来说，这 足以成为他支持那位神的理由之一。
- But he was not, like, a hardcore Christian all the way through.
但他并不是那种从头到尾都 非常虔诚的基督徒。
He was a kind of a spiritual, religious kind of person. He
他是个有精神追求、有 宗教信仰的人。他
thought about religions more generally and just converged towards Christianity as
我开始更广泛地思考各种宗教， 最终逐渐倾向于基督教。
a good religion. He also had ideas about what a good religion is-
好的宗教。他对好的宗教 也有自己的看法——
... and what a bad religion is, that kind of stuff. So he's thinking in this space.
……以及宗教是多么糟糕的事情，诸如此 类。所以他正在思考这个问题。
- He's tending not to be too explicit.
他不太喜欢直白表达。
Depending on the audience. So Constantine remains a pragmatist
取决于受众。所以君士坦丁 仍然是一位实用主义者。
in the sense that he doesn't want to alienate too many of his subjects, right?
从某种意义上说，他不 想疏远太多民众，对吧？
- Mm-hmm. Fair. Mm-hmm.
嗯。公平的。嗯。
- And so he's sometimes a bit coy or elusive about what he's
所以，他有时对自己的真实想法会 有些含糊其辞或难以捉摸。
getting at. When he's talking to Christians, he will talk about Christ. He
正要说。当他与基督徒 交谈时，他会谈论基督。他
will mention Christ. When he's talking to everybody else in, like, a general law,
会提到基督。当他跟其他人 谈论一般法律问题时，
he'll just refer to good religion. And it's like, maybe
他只会提到虔诚的宗教 信仰。感觉就像，也许
you know what I mean, right? But he's not gonna, like, you know, come to Jesus.
你明白我的意思，对吧？但他不 会，你知道的，皈依耶稣。
- Yeah.
- 是的。
- Right?
- 正确的？
- So even at the time when he's, like, supporting the church, like,
所以即使在他支持教会 的时候，比如，
basically institutionalizing the church as part of the imperial
基本上是将教会制度化，使 其成为帝国的一部分。
system, but he's also putting up statues of himself that look like
系统，但他同时也竖立着自己 的雕像，这些雕像看起来像
Apollo in Constantinople, right? So the focal point of
君士坦丁堡的阿波罗 ，对吧？所以，焦点是
Constantine's Constantinople is the Forum of Constantine.
君士坦丁堡即君士 坦丁广场。
And in the middle is this very tall column, and it has a colossal statue of
中间是一根非常高的柱子， 柱子上有一尊巨大的雕像。
Constantine on top, gilded, enormous
君士坦丁位于顶端，镀金，巨大
thing. I don't know, like, eight meters tall or whatever. But it's a
事物。我不知道，大概八 米高什么的。但这却是
repurposed Apollo. It's even, it, like, visibly so. It's naked. It
重新利用的阿波罗计划。甚至，简直 是显而易见的。它是裸体的。它
has the rays coming out of the-
光线从……发出——
... head, right? Right. And everybody knew it was an Apollo. So that's
……头部，对吧？正确的。大家都知道 那是阿波罗号。就是这样。
Constantine in the guise of his old patron god, Apollo.
君士坦丁装扮成他昔日 的守护神阿波罗。
Still, but he's still Christian Constantine, so he's sending all of these
不过，他毕竟还是克里斯蒂安· 君士坦丁，所以他才派出所有这些人。
different messages.
不同的信息。
- I mean, he likes being the god-like figure. I mean, that whole
我的意思是，他喜欢扮演神一样的角色 。我的意思是，整个
statue just is like, "I am the god."
这座雕像仿佛在说：“我就是神。”
- Yeah. It's assimilating yourself to... Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- 是的。这是让自己融入……是 啊，是啊，是啊。
- And I mean, a lot of the Romans, is it fair to say, kinda saw the emperor a little
我的意思是，很多罗马人，这么说没 错的话，对皇帝有点儿……
bit in that light?
从这个角度来看？
- No, yeah. Oh, yeah. They called him divine and-
- 不，是的。哦，是的。他们 称他为神，而且——
... yeah. There's not a hard theology there, right? Like, if you pressed them on the actual
... 是的。这里面并没有什么复杂的教义，对吧 ？比如，如果你把它们按在实际位置上的话。
theology, they wouldn't-
他们不会——
... they wouldn't say the emperor is a god. No. This is mushy.
他们不会说皇帝是神。不 ，这太软绵绵的了。
This gets very, very mushy.
这变得非常非常软弱无力。
- But I mean, a lot of the Christians have a kinda humility before God.
但我的意思是，很多基督徒在上帝 面前都有一种谦卑的态度。
I think when you have an emperor that's god-like, it gets a little weird-
我觉得当皇帝拥有神一般的力量时 ，事情就会变得有点奇怪。
- Yes. Yes
- 是的。是的
- ... in the way you talk about God.
——……在你谈论上帝的方式上。
- It depends on the context. Like, there are contexts in which you are an emperor and
- 这取决于具体情况。比如，在 某些情况下，你就是皇帝，
you're proclaiming your majesty, and then there are more personal contexts where you
你是在此宣告你的威严，但也 有一些更私人的语境，比如你
might be more humble because, I don't know, you're being baptized or
或许会更谦逊一些，因为，我 不知道，你正在接受洗礼，或者
something. Like, those are different contexts.
某物。这是不同 的语境。
- So can you speak to the whole process of the conversion to Christianity, of the-
那么，您能否谈谈皈依基督教 的整个过程，即……
... propagation of Christianity throughout the empire and, and Constantine's role in
……基督教在整个帝国的传播， 以及君士坦丁在其中的作用
that?
那？
- Constantine, or his successors as well, because this was a
——君士坦丁，或者他的继任 者，因为这是一个
gradual process, and it takes a very long time. So let's,
这是一个渐进的过程，需要很长 时间。那么，我们开始吧。
Let's put it into perspective.
让我们换个角度来看。
We probably can't talk about a majority Christian society
我们可能无法谈论一个 基督教占多数的社会。
until maybe the 5th century, or early 5th-
直到公元5世纪，或者5世纪初——
... mid-5th. We don't have data, obviously.
……5 中期。显然，我们 没有相关数据。
And we can't talk about, like, a solidly Christian
我们不能谈论一个 坚定的基督徒。
society until early 6th century. And by solidly, I mean maybe
社会一直延续到6世纪初。我 说的“稳固”是指也许
where the non-Christians are 10, 15%, right? So that's a long time.
非基督徒占10%到15%，对吧？ 那可是很长一段时间啊。
That's, like, five centuries after Jesus. That's half a millennium.
那可是耶稣诞生五个世纪之后 的事了。那可是五百年啊。
So we're talking about a half a millennial process here. It's, it's very long.
所以我们谈论的是一个持续五百 年的过程。它，它很长。
- But it's only a couple of centuries after Constantine. So it takes-
但那只是君士坦丁之后的几个世纪 而已。所以需要——
... about two centuries to really make the Roman Empire Christian
大约两个世纪才真正使 罗马帝国基督教化。
- Yes. So very slow conversion, maybe, maybe up to 10%
- 是的。所以转化率非常低 ，可能只有10%。
tops under Constantine. Then obviously larger and
君士坦丁之下的顶峰 。然后显然更大，
larger groups join the church, even if only nominally, right?
即使只是名义上的，更多的 人也会加入教会，对吧？
Until you get to the sixth century when you're clearly talking about a, you
直到六世纪，你才清楚地意识 到，你指的是……
know, mostly or overwhelmingly Christian society.
众所周知，大部分或绝大多数 是基督教社会。
A lot of this is just done through incentives
很多事情都是通过激励 措施来实现的。
and disincentives, right? So bishops are given
以及惩罚措施，对吧？因此， 主教的职位就此设立。
funds with which to distribute, like, charity and
用于分配的资金 ，例如慈善和
help to communities in distress. They have lists of
帮助处于困境中的社区 。他们有以下清单：
widows and whatever they support. Land is
寡妇和她们所养活的一切。土地是
given to the church by the emperors or in wills so that they
由皇帝或遗嘱赠予 教会的财产，以便他们
can engage in this kind of social policy. And then there are disincentives. So
可以参与此类社会政策。此外， 还有一些不利因素。所以
emperors pass laws that increasingly restrict the exercise of traditional religion.
皇帝颁布法律，日益限制 传统宗教的实践。
Like, you can't perform animal sacrifices, then you can't start doing
比如，如果你不能进行动物 献祭，那么你就不能开始做……
these like tying ribbons to make wishes or, like, all of these
比如用丝带许愿，或者 ，就像所有这些。
things, like going out to sacred trees and doing this or that,
比如去圣树下做这做 那之类的事情，
because they say, "Oh, this is kind of nefarious business," or, like, magic or
因为他们会说，“哦，这有点像是不正当 的生意”，或者，就像魔法一样，或者
whatever it is. And then they just gradually start outlawing it more
不管它是什么。然后他们就 逐渐开始进一步取缔它。
and more, putting restrictions on, like, if you're not a Christian, you can't hold
而且还设置了更多限制，比如，如果 你不是基督徒，你就不能持有……
these high offices or you can't... Your... There's problems with your wills.
否则你就无法担任这些高官 ……你的……你的遗嘱有问题。
So they gradually do it like that.
所以他们就逐渐这样做了。
And this is how you... Yeah, this is... And it works. It works.
这就是方法……对，就是这样 ……而且有效。有用。
- What explains the success of Christianity after Constantine?
君士坦丁之后基督教取得 成功的原因是什么？
Why was it, as a technology, so successful at spreading throughout the empire?
为什么这项技术能够如此成功地 在整个帝国传播开来？
- Christianity developed in a number of
基督教在多个地区发展起来
ways. So it acquired a certain number of forms that were capable
方法。因此，它获得了一定 数量的能够形成的形式。
of appealing to different constituencies.
迎合不同选民群体。
In other words, there was an intellectual side to it,
换句话说，它具有 理性的一面。
The sort of theology, the almost
这种神学，几乎
quasi-philosophical or engagement with philosophical schools that could
准哲学性的或与哲学 流派的互动，可能
draw in, let's say, intellectuals. There is a,
吸引，比如说， 知识分子。有一个，
a public ceremony and ritual aspect where you can organize
公开的仪式和礼仪 方面，您可以组织
communities and cities to have processions or,
社区和城市 举行游行或
like, have ho- all these festivals that take the place of the ancient
比如，所有这些节日 都取代了古代的节日
ones. You have a kind of
一。你有一种
not, it's not secretive, but it's kind of this initiatory aspect
不，这并非秘密，而 是一种入门仪式。
where there's this baptism and you learn a sort of creed,
在那里，人们会接受洗礼 ，并学习某种信条，
and you're initiated into the religion with the prospect of a
你通过入教仪式加入该 宗教，并有望获得……
personal afterlife, right? And that appeals to other kinds
对吧？而这又吸引了 其他类型的人。
of people. There's also ways in which it
人。还有一些其他方式
it integrated itself into the court and the language of power.
它融入了法庭和 权力语言之中。
Also in the army, right? Soldiers now swear an oath to the
你也在军队里，对吧？士兵们 现在向……宣誓效忠
Trinity, right? So it takes all of these different forms that
是三位一体，对吧？所以它呈现 出所有这些不同的形式。
enable it to position itself, you know,
让它能够定位自身，你知道的。
here and there and, you know, in the streets, in the court, in the armies,
这里那里，还有，你知道，在 街上，在法庭上，在军队里，
in the churches, in texts, in books. And so
在教堂里，在经文 里，在书籍里。所以
it has this kind of manifold diversity, right, that makes it very adaptable.
它具有这种多方面的多样性，对吧 ，这使它具有很强的适应性。
- So one of the things you mentioned that
- 所以你提到的其中一点是
Constantine did not anticipate, did not realize that Christianity
君士坦丁没有预料到， 也没有意识到基督教
creates divisions between various groups.
造成不同群体之间的隔阂。
- So in part, this happens when you have,
所以，部分原因是，当你拥有……时，就会发生这种情况。
Religions that make exclusive claims, right? Like, my beliefs are true-
那些宣称具有排他性的宗教，对吧？ 比如，我的信念是正确的——
... and yours are by definition false. Not, not just wrong, but false and
……而你的说法从定义上来说就是错误 的。不仅错误，而且是虚假的。
even kinda evil. Like maybe- ... Satan put them in your mind to-
甚至有点邪恶。也许……是撒旦 把它们放进你脑子里……
... lead you astray, right? And this is inherently divisive. Like, it is.
……误导你，对吧？而这本身 就具有分裂性。确实如此。
So there's this paradox where
所以这里存在这样一个悖论：
Christianity, in contrast to, say, the ancient religions, is both
与古代宗教相比， 基督教既是……
far more polarizing but also far more powerful as a unifying force
更具两极分化性，但 同时也更具凝聚力。
at the same time, right? So ancient religions tended not to
同时发生，对吧？所以 古代宗教往往不会
produce this kind of conflict or identities, right,
制造这种冲突或身份 认同，对吧？
or, or wars or these kinds of things. And they could under certain
或者，或者战争，或者诸如此类 的事情。而且他们可能在某些情况下
circumstances, but for the most part, they were not
虽然情况各异，但大多数 情况下并非如此。
drivers of history in this kind of way. But when you have exclusive claims, then
历史的驱动力就是这样产生的。 但如果你拥有独家权利，那么
suddenly these very communities of, that are sort of
突然间，这些社区，某 种程度上……
consolidated and have this very strong identity,
已巩固并拥有非常强大 的品牌形象，
But you also alienate other groups- ... that you then are in conflict with.
但你也会疏远其他群体——…… 然后与你们发生冲突。
So this is why I for one can't come down on whether,
所以这就是为什么我个人 无法就此做出决定的原因：
you know, Christianity is more of a unifying force or a divisive force in the
你知道，基督教在某种意义上更多的是一 种团结的力量，或者说是一种分裂的力量。
history of the Eastern Empire, because it's, it's both.
东罗马帝国的历史，因为它既是东罗马帝国 的历史，又是东罗马帝国的历史。
- And also trying to figure out whether the unifying or the divisive
——同时也在试图弄清楚， 这究竟是团结的还是分裂的。
aspects are a feature or a bug.
特性要么是功能，要么是缺陷。
Maybe some of the divisive elements is a way for society
或许某些分裂因素是 社会发展的一种方式。
internally to try to, much like the civil wars, to try to figure itself out.
内部试图像内战一样，试图 找出自身的问题所在。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- So sometimes tension and conflict is a good mechanism for figuring out what
所以，有时候紧张和冲突是 弄清楚什么的好机制。
do the people want.
人民想要什么？
- Or what's the truth, right?
——或者说，真相是什么？
- Or what's the truth.
或者说，真相是什么？
- Yeah. So the story that it likes to tell itself is that
- 是的。所以它喜欢讲述 的故事是这样的：
there's this, like, this one original truth, and the
这里存在着这样一种真理， 就像，这唯一的真理，以及
hardcore of true believers is defending that truth at every moment against
真正的铁杆信徒每时每刻都在捍卫真理 ，反对一切反对真理的行为。
all of these evil heretics who are coming in-
所有这些进来的邪恶 异端分子——
... and trying to corrupt it. In reality, what happens is that this truth is
并试图破坏它。实际上 ，事实是这样的：
something that's evolving in the course of the controversies.
这是在争议过程中不断 演变的事物。
And, like, often they don't know that they believed
而且，他们往往并不知道 自己曾经相信过。
that until in retrospect, once they've had the fight and the winner
直到事后回想起来，等到战斗结束 ，决出胜负之后，才会明白这一点。
has this position, oh, now that turns out to have been the position we
有这个立场，哦，现在看来， 那原来是我们之前的立场
always held, right? And this happens again and again and again. You know, a lot
一直都持有，对吧？这种情况一而再、 再而三地发生。你知道，很多
of the time, these Christian theologians
当时的这些基督教神学家
who get into so much trouble and get branded as heretics and sometimes get sent into
那些惹出很多麻烦、被贴上异端标签 、有时还会被送往……的人
exile, they didn't mean any harm.
流放，他们并没有恶意。
They often just were stating what they thought everybody believed.
他们往往只是在陈述他们认为 每个人都相信的事情。
And then when they blurt it out, someone is like, off in Alexandria, is like, "What?
然后当他们脱口而出时，远在亚历山 大港的某个人会说：“什么？”
That's heresy." And then now you're, now you're in trouble. Now you're getting into this fight, and you
“那是异端邪说。”然后你就麻烦了 。现在你卷入了这场争斗，而且你
might win, you might lose. But, like, a lot of them were kind of sort of
可能会赢，也可能会输。但是， 很多时候，他们都有点……
well-intentioned in that way, or they had no intention of starting a fight. But
他们的出发点是好的，或者他们根本 没有挑起争端的意图。但
there's always someone who wants to start a fight.
总有人想挑起 争端。
- Yeah, I mean, sometimes the fights are extremely intense
是啊，我的意思是，有时候 打斗场面确实非常激烈。
over things that I could see on the surface or, like,
那些我能一眼看穿的事情 ，或者，比如，
iconography. It's like, it seems like a very subtle-
图像学。这就像，这似乎 是一种非常微妙的——
...debate, like almost academic. And then
……辩论，几乎像学术辩论一样。进而
a large number of people don't see it as academic. They,
很多人并不认为这是学术性 的。他们，
they do see it like the devil put ideas in your head that are-
他们认为这就像魔鬼在你 脑子里植入了一些想法——
...completely wrong, and it's, it's fascinating how that kind of division can emerge.
……完全错误，而且，这种分歧是如何 产生的，真是令人着迷。
Uh, I mean, I—
呃，我的意思是，我——
The impossible question, and I apologize for asking it, but maybe just
这是一个不可能回答的问题， 我很抱歉问这个问题，但也许只是
worthwhile to try to think about it is, on the grand scale of
值得思考的是，从宏观 的角度来看……
centuries of the East Roman Empire, is religion
几个世纪以来，东罗马帝国 一直以宗教的形式存在。
a constructive or a destructive force
一种建设性或破坏性的力量
for the empire? Did it help it flourish, or did it hold it back?
为了帝国？它促进了它的发展 ，还是阻碍了它的发展？
- This society identified itself increasingly
这个社会日益认同 自身。
with what it saw as orthodoxy. Orthodoxy just means correct belief. I mean—
它所认为的正统观念。正统观念仅仅 意味着正确的信仰。我是说-
...like every religion ultimately thinks it's orthodox, right? That's—
就像所有宗教最终都认为自己 是正统的一样，对吧？那是——
But that's the conventional name, right? Orthodoxy today might be called Greek Orthodoxy.
但那是惯用的名称，对吧？如今的 东正教或许可以被称为希腊东正教。
Um, and I mean, it's such an essential part of the culture.
嗯，我的意思是，这是文化 中非常重要的一部分。
It really is. I can't think of the two of them inde... I mean,
确实如此。我一时想不起 他们俩……我的意思是，
I try to because, as a historian, I have to test the models,
我尝试这样做，因为作为一名历史学家 ，我必须检验这些模型。
you know, and try to see these things as independent of each other.
你知道，要试着把这些 事情看作是彼此独立的。
But ultimately, it's very difficult to
但归根结底，这非常困难。
disentangle them, and I would say that to the degree that
将它们解开，而且我认为 ，在某种程度上……
this is a successful society historically,
这是一个历史上成功的社会。
that its religion definitely contributed to that and played a role in it.
它的宗教信仰无疑对此有所影响 ，并在其中发挥了作用。
Not without cost, right? There are, it mattered to
当然，这并非没有代价，对 吧？确实存在，这很重要
them. They valued it, but things that matter to you have a cost.
他们。他们很珍惜它，但对你来说 重要的东西都是要付出代价的。
And they paid that price. They were willing to pay that price for it.
他们为此付出了代价。他们 愿意为此付出这个代价。
For example, at the very end, they had to choose between Catholicism, Western rule,
例如，在最后时刻，他们必须在天主教 和西方统治之间做出选择。
where they essentially have to compromise on their faith, or
他们实际上不得不在信仰 上做出妥协，或者
rule by Muslims, the Turks, where they would not have to compromise their faith.
在穆斯林和土耳其人的统治下 ，他们不必在信仰上妥协。
And some of them were explicit that they were preferring option B,
他们中有些人明确表示，他们 更倾向于选择B方案。
because the Turks will at least respect our identity. Like, that's a cost.
因为土耳其人至少会尊重我们的身份认同 。这就像是付出代价一样。
- Yeah. But there's other layers, like taxation and-
- 是的。但还有其他层面 ，例如税收和——
...the, the functions of government—
……政府的职能——
... that are connected to religion to the degree it interacts with the
……与宗教相关的程度，取决于 它与……的互动程度
tax system. But it feels like that's the engine
税制。但感觉那 就是引擎。
of the society and religion is more like the cultural layer.
社会和宗教更像 是文化层面。
- Yeah. So this is why I said that I try
- 是的。所以这就是我为什么说我会尽力的原因。
in thinking of the models that we use to understand the
在思考我们用来 理解的模型时
society, not to assume that religion is
社会不应假定宗教是
everywhere and for everything. Now, I have colleagues who do
无处不在，无所不包。现在 ，我的同事们也这样做。
that, and I would disagree with them about this, but you're exactly right. There are
这一点我并不认同他们的观点 ，但你说得完全正确。有
elements of this society that I like to see as their own thing.
这个社会中的某些元素，我希望 它们能保持自身的独立性。
Like the Roman identity, for example. It's not the same as Orthodoxy.
例如，罗马人的身份认同。 这和东正教不一样。
But also the operations of the state. Those are
但也包括国家机器 的运作。那些是
very pragmatic things, and you see them
非常务实的事情，你看它们
intersect with religion in, largely in areas of
与宗教交织在一起，主要 发生在以下领域：
terminology or the vocabulary that they use or, you know, like at the
他们使用的术语或词汇，或者 ，你知道，就像在……
top, but not at their actual functioning.
顶部，但不是它们的实际功能。
So in my field, I'm a historian who's tried
所以，在我的领域，我是 一名尝试过的历史学家
to promote other aspects of the culture as having
宣传文化的其他 方面，例如：
a kind of integrity of their own and not to subsume them all within Orthodoxy.
他们应该保持自身的某种完整性，而不 是将他们全部纳入东正教的范畴。
- So, I mean, again, an impossible way of asking the
所以，我的意思是，再说一 遍，这是一种不可能的提问方式
same question. If you asked a Roman, a million Romans across
同样的问题。如果你问一个罗马人 ，一百万罗马人会告诉你答案。
a thousand years, "Are you a Roman or a Christian?"
一千年来，“你是罗马人 还是基督徒？”
What would be the answer for that?
这个问题的答案是什么？
- Oh, both. Oh, absolutely.
- 哦，两者都有。当然。
- No, you don't get to say both. You're not allowed to do that.
- 不，你不能两个都说 。你不可以这样做。
- Why not? It's the-
为什么不呢？是——
- Well, you're-
- 嗯，你是-
- It's the true answer.
这是正确答案。
- Okay. So you're saying they're really tied together.
- 好的。所以你的意思是说 ，它们之间确实联系紧密。
- Well, they overlap. But if you were to...
- 嗯，它们有重叠之处。但如果你……
And this might be a somewhat more subtle conversation than most of
这或许是一场比大多数对话 都更为微妙的对话。
them would want to have, but if you were to say, "Is Roman and Christian the
他们想要拥有，但如果你问，“ 罗马和基督教是……”
same thing to you?" If they thought about it for a little while,
你也是一样吗？”如果他们 思考了一会儿，
they'd quickly be able to say no. Because there were, I mean, just logically, there
他们很快就能说不。因为，我的意思是 ，从逻辑上讲，确实存在这种情况。
were Christians who were not Romans.
他们是基督徒，但不是罗马人。
The Bulgarians or the Rus or, you know, whoever.
保加利亚人、罗斯人，或者， 你知道的，随便什么人。
There were lots of Christians who were not Roman, and they did not regard them as
有很多基督徒并非罗马人，他们 也不把这些人视为罗马人。
Roman just because they were Christian. Conversely, they knew perfectly well
仅仅因为他们是基督徒，就去罗马人那里 受人迫害。反之，他们却心知肚明。
that there had been Romans who were not Christians, and they knew this how? Because in the
他们怎么知道罗马人中曾经 存在非基督徒呢？因为在
churches like almost every week, they celebrated
教堂几乎每周都会举行 庆祝活动。
martyrs who had been killed by the Roman emperors in the past.
历史上被罗马皇帝 杀害的殉道者。
And so it was, like, the performance of violence by
所以这就像是， 暴力表演……
Roman emperors against Christians was something they remember. They knew perfectly
罗马皇帝对抗基督徒的战争是他们 记忆犹新的一段历史。他们心知肚明。
well. So those two things did not overlap perfectly.
出色地。所以这两件 事并没有完全重合。
And there were some contexts in which you would be more Roman, and there were
在某些情况下，你会更倾向于罗马式 的价值观，而且还有……
some contexts in which you would be more Christian.
在某些情况下，你会 更像个基督徒。
And you find characters who, and I love to do this. I find characters who,
你会发现一些角色，而我喜欢这样 做。我发现有些角色，
As some sources say we didn't pay too much attention to Christian
一些消息来源称，我们并没有 太关注克里斯蒂安。
things. Like, they were just politicians. They were just doing their work. And then
事物。他们只不过是些政客而已。 他们只是在做自己的工作。进而
you find characters who, like, devote themselves. They go all
你会发现有些人会全身心 投入。他们全部
in on Orthodoxy and, like, monasticism and they just don't care about
他们信奉东正教和修道制度 ，但他们根本不在乎
the Roman stuff at all.
完全是罗马的东西。
And that is, in fact, part of the reason why I like this society, is because
事实上，这也是我喜欢这个 社会的部分原因，因为
it has these kinds of options for people to choose. And there's another one. There's the Greek stuff,
它为人们提供了这些选择。还有 另一个。还有希腊那部分，
too, because their language is Greek, their literature is Greek, and so there are people in
也因为他们的语言是希腊语，他们的 文学是希腊语，所以那里有希腊人。
the society who go all in on the Greek stuff. Right?
那些全身心投入希腊 文化的人。正确的？
And I see this society as this kind of laboratory of
我认为这个社会 就像一个实验室
these three elements coexisting in these fascinating
这三个要素共同存在于这些引人 入胜的事物中。
combinations. Usually it's combinations, right? But
组合。通常是组合 ，对吧？但
sometimes you'll find people who are like, kinda try to be purists in one way or
有时你会发现有些人试图在某些 方面成为纯粹主义者，或者
another. And it's the only society in history in
其他。而且它是历史上唯一 一个……的社会
which you can do this, 'cause it's the only society that's Roman and Christian and Greek.
你可以这样做，因为这是唯一一个同时 具有罗马、基督教和希腊文化的社会。
But in different ways, right?
但方式不同，对吧？
- Yeah, unfortunately, I think it's tempting, but it's probably impossible to say
- 是的，很遗憾，我觉得这很诱人 ，但恐怕很难说出口。
if we remove the taxation system, would the, would Roman Empire
如果我们取消税收制度， 罗马帝国会怎样？
be more or less successful? If we removed religion, would it be more or
会更成功还是不太成功？如果我们摒弃 宗教，情况会变得更好还是更糟？
less successful?
不太成功？
- Right.
- 正确的。
- If we removed, uh,
- 如果我们移除，呃，
Greek and kept it Latin all the way through, would it be more or less successful?
如果全部内容都用希腊语，却始终保留拉丁语， 这样的做法会更成功还是更不成功呢？
It's probably impossible to do this kind of analysis 'cause they're all so
这种分析大概不可能进行 ，因为它们都太……
deeply integrated.
深度融合。
- And fundamentally, it also wouldn't be what it was. It would be something different.
——而且从根本上来说，它也不会再是 原来的样子了。这将是不一样的。
- But there is a big temptation, and this is at the core of your work, and to
但诱惑很大，而这正是你工作 的核心所在，也是……
understand why did the East Roman Empire last as long as it did.
了解东罗马帝国为何 能延续如此之久。
And why did the broader Roman Empire last as long as it did?
而罗马帝国为何能 延续如此之久？
- Yeah.
- 是的。
- 'Cause it's, it is one of, if not the most successful empires in terms
因为就各方面而言，它即使不是最成功 的帝国，也是最成功的帝国之一。
of duration and stability in a very dense part of the world.
在世界人口密度极高的地区 ，具有持久性和稳定性。
- That's actually like my next project. I'm starting to write a book
— 这其实是我下一个项目。我 开始写一本书了。
trying to explain just kind of from an analytical standpoint why.
我试着从分析的角度 解释一下原因。
- How did it last so long?
它怎么持续了这么久？
- Yeah.
- 是的。
- A lot of your work kinda hints at it.
你的很多作品都隐约暗示了这一点。
- It's here and there.
这里那里都有。
But you're trying to do more, more systematic. So, and we'll keep hinting at it.
但你正在尝试做得更多、更系统 。所以，我们会继续暗示这一点。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- But to put a bow tie on Constantinople, it went from a
但要给君士坦丁堡打上 领结，那就得从……
very low population of maybe 25,000 people
人口非常少，可能只有25000人。
to 500,000 people in just two centuries. So can you explain how that happened?
短短两个世纪，人口就增长到50万人。 你能解释一下这是怎么发生的吗？
- Well, it didn't happen through just demographic growth
——嗯，这不仅仅是人口 增长的结果。
and reproduction in the city itself. That rate of growth is
以及城市本身的 繁殖。增长率是
impossible for an ancient city. So when I say 20,000, 25,000, that's
对于一座古城来说，这是不可能的。所以 当我说2万、2.5万的时候，那就是
possibly what the ancient city of Byzantium had-
或许古城拜占庭拥有的 就是这种东西——
... when Constantine decided to found Constantinople, and it grew to a city of a half a
……当君士坦丁决定建立君士坦丁堡 时，它发展成为一座占地半个世纪的城市。
million in two centuries. That can only have been done in one way,
两百年内达到百万。这件事只 能通过一种方式实现，
and that is immigration from the provinces. So people must have been moving there,
这就是来自各省的移民。所以 肯定有人搬到那里去了。
In large numbers,
大量地，
Which is a movement that we can't see very clearly in the sources, but
这是我们无法在资料中清楚 地看到的运动，但是
we have to infer it and then try to explain it. So,
我们必须先推断出来， 然后再尝试解释。所以，
Also there's another factor, which is that ancient cities
此外还有另一个因素 ，那就是古代城市
we now know or suspect are
我们现在知道或怀疑的是
what some historians call death traps. In other words, the density
一些历史学家称之为死亡 陷阱。换句话说，密度
of disease is such that ancient cities probably are losing something like
疾病的肆虐使得古代城市可能 正在失去一些东西，比如
1, 2, possibly 3% of their population per year.
每年可能有 1%、2% 甚至 3% 的人口受到影响。
So just in order to stay with a stable population, they have to import people.
所以为了维持人口稳定， 他们不得不引进人口。
Right? Now, they're not like 17th century London. They're not that bad.
正确的？现在，它们和17世纪的 伦敦不一样了。他们没那么糟糕。
- Do diseases and plagues seem to be prevalent?
疾病和瘟疫似乎 很普遍吗？
- Oh, yeah. Now, you know, Roman cities have some corrections
- 哦，是的。现在，你知道， 罗马城市有一些修正。
for these sorts of things, like the way they distribute the water through the city.
对于这类事情，例如他们 如何向城市分配水资源。
Anyway, they, they weren't as bad as they could've been,
总之，他们，他们并没有 想象中那么糟糕。
but there's that. So not only to keep the population steady, but to
但还有这一点。所以不仅 要保持人口稳定，而且
expand it so dramatically means that a lot of people are coming in
如此大幅度的扩张意味 着很多人涌入。
from the provinces, mostly the Greek-speaking provinces. So
来自各省，主要是希腊语 省份。所以
you know, Greece, Asia Minor, and some of the major cities in the
你知道，希腊、小亚细亚 以及一些主要城市……
East that are Greek speaking. And I start to wonder
东部地区，即讲希腊语的地区 。于是我开始想
like, well, how did this happen? Like, who are these people, for one thing?
这到底是怎么发生的？ 首先，这些人是谁？
And then I did some simple calculations. So I mentioned earlier that we
然后我做了一些简单的计算。所以 我之前提到过，我们
have something like two and a half thousand senators-
大约有两千五百 名参议员——
... Who are required initially to reside in Constantinople.
……他们最初必须居住 在君士坦丁堡。
Well, senators don't live in bachelor pads.
嗯，参议员们可不 住在单身公寓里。
Senators have manners. They have household staff, right? In Rome
参议员们很有礼貌。他们家 有佣人，对吧？在罗马
at the time, there's a calculation that a senatorial household
当时有一种计算方法， 认为参议员家庭
was something like 100 people, right? Just servants, slaves,
大概有100人左右，对吧 ？只是仆人，奴隶，
dancing girls, cooks, barbers, whatever, right?
舞女、厨师、理发师 ，什么都行，对吧？
So let's assume sort of conservatively that in Constantinople it's
所以，我们保守地假设，在 君士坦丁堡是……
only 30 people, which it might be low, right? So if you do the math,
只有30人，这可能有点少， 对吧？所以如果你算一下，
you're starting to get something like, I mean, closer to 100,000 people,
你们开始看到，我的意思 是，接近10万人了，
right? And that's just by bringing in senators.
正确的？而这仅仅是通过 争取参议员的支持。
Right? They come with people. So I think this was the nucleus
正确的？他们和人一起来的。 所以我认为这就是原子核。
of the population. Now then Constantine also makes
人口。现在，君士坦丁 也做出了……
provision for possibly up to like 200,000 people to receive the grain dole, the
预计将有多达20万人 获得粮食救济。
bread. So that would've incentivized even
面包。所以那会激励他们……
more people to travel there because there are-
因为有更多人会去那里旅游 ，所以会有更多人去那里——
- So you get free bread.
这样你就能免费吃面包了。
- Yes. And you can't live on that alone, but it is, it's something.
- 是的。光靠这个是活不下去 的，但它毕竟是一份收入。
- Incentive. Is it true that he diverted resources from Rome to Constantinople?
- 激励。他是否真的将资源从 罗马转移到了君士坦丁堡？
- Absolutely. Oh, yeah. That grain, that's coming from Egypt.
- 绝对地。哦，是的。 那些粮食来自埃及。
So New Rome is literally stealing food from the mouth of Old Rome.
所以，新罗马简直就是在从旧 罗马的嘴里偷食物。
Now, Old Rome doesn't starve because they, they divert other, like from North
如今，古罗马不会挨饿，因为他们会 转移其他资源，比如来自北方的资源。
Africa and Sicily, you can feed Rome, right?
非洲和西西里岛，足够 养活罗马了吧？
- But it sends a strong signal to the people living in Old Rome
但这向居住在古罗马的人们发出 了一个强烈的信号。
that, long term, we should probably move.
从长远来看，我们或许应该搬家。
- Some people do move. So we know of some senators who move from Rome.
有些人确实会搬家。所以我们知道有些 元老是从罗马迁居过来的。
It sends a signal about the priorities of the state, like they're investing much
这传递出一个关于国家优先事项的信号 ，比如他们正在大力投资。
more in the East. And that the East would be regarded as an equal parallel
东部地区更多。而东方将被 视为与西方平等的平行世界。
Roman, you know, world. Yeah.
罗马，你知道，世界。是的。
- As we talk about diverting resources, slowly
当我们谈到转移资源 时，慢慢地
the West declines and collapses in 476 AD. So the Visigoths sack Rome in 410 AD,
公元476年，西方衰落并崩溃。公元 410年，西哥特人洗劫了罗马。
and in 476 AD, the last Western emperor is deposed,
公元476年，西罗马帝国 末代皇帝被废黜。
marking the end of the Western Roman Empire.
标志着西罗马帝国 的终结。
High-level question: What is the reason for that decline
高层次问题：造成这种 下降的原因是什么？
and the collapse of the Western Roman Empire? So,
以及西罗马帝国 的崩溃？所以，
nonstop civil wars, as we've talked about, weak emperors.
正如我们之前讨论过的，内战 不断，皇帝软弱无能。
There's an economic money crisis, so shrinking tax base,
当前经济面临货币危机 ，导致税基萎缩。
rising army costs. There was a loss of key
军费开支不断上涨。钥匙丢了。
provinces, especially in North Africa. Reliance on contracted barbarian troops
各省，尤其是北非各省 。依赖雇佣的蛮族军队
as they immigrated more and more into—
随着他们越来越多地移民到——
...the Western Roman Empire. Cascading invasions,
……西罗马帝国。 连锁入侵，
migrations amplified by Hun pressure, and then the East-West split. The richer
匈奴人的压力加剧了人口迁徙 ，随后东西分裂。更富有的人
East survives, the West can't stabilize under— ...that split.
东方得以幸存，西方却 无法在分裂下稳定下来。
- Yeah. The crux of the matter is that barbarian armies, so armies from
- 是的。问题的关键在于蛮族军队 ，也就是来自……的军队
outside the empire, put increasing pressure on it during
在帝国之外，对帝国 施加越来越大的压力
the fifth century. And for whatever reason,
五世纪。不管出于 什么原因，
when the Roman state failed to sort of suppress one of
当罗马国家未能镇压 其中之一时
them and, say, settled them here or allowed them to have here
比如说，让他们定居在这里，或者 允许他们在这里生活。
or couldn't stop them and they took over a province, like the Vandals did in
或者无法阻止他们，于是他们占领了一个 省份，就像汪达尔人所做的那样。
North Africa— ...this created this kind of vicious cycle because then the Roman
北非——……这就造成了这种 恶性循环，因为当时的罗马
state lost access to the resources from those provinces, that
该州失去了从这些省份获取 资源的途径，
is the taxes, and without those resources, they couldn't,
关键在于税收，没有这些资源 ，他们就无法生存。
you know, maintain, mobilize, pay for their armies.
你知道，维持、动员、 支付军队开支。
Then they had fewer armies to handle the next wave of barbarians that
然后，他们就没有足够的军队来 应对下一波蛮族入侵了。
came in. The previous barbarians who settled kind of declared their kind
来了。之前定居的蛮族人某种 程度上宣称了他们的种族。
of independence. They also could not be put down, and so this created a vicious,
独立。它们也无法被制服， 因此造成了一种恶性循环。
cycle that just continued in that way.
就这样循环往复。
It's not rocket science, actually. I mean, you can see it playing out.
其实这并不复杂。我的意思是 ，你可以看到事情正在发生。
Yeah. Now, who these groups are, where they came from, why did they
是的。那么，这些群体是谁？他们 来自哪里？他们为什么会这样做？
cross, that, those are different questions, right?
交叉，那是不同 的问题，对吧？
But from the Roman standpoint, that's how it was experienced. These are
但从罗马人的角度来看，情况 就是这样。这些都是
armies that can defeat a Roman field army- right, in battle. And sometimes they do.
能够击败罗马野战军的军队——没错 ，是在战场上。有时确实如此。
And they then settle and take over territories, and then you lose the revenues,
然后他们定居下来，占领 领土，你就失去了收入。
and so you can't recruit your own armies. And so, anyway, that's the kind of
所以你无法招募自己的军队 。总之，就是这样。
cycle. The East tried to help.
循环。东方曾试图提供帮助。
Occasionally, they would send forces, but they were also subject to some of the same pressures.
他们偶尔会派兵，但他们也 面临着同样的一些压力。
Because remember, the Goths cross the Danube for the first
因为别忘了，哥特人 第一次渡过多瑙河。
time in a major way in 376. Then you have the Battle of
376 年，时间以一种重要的方式 流逝。然后就是……之战
Adrianople a couple years later, where, like, one and a half field armies is just
几年后，在阿德里安堡，大约 一个半野战军就出现了。
annihilated, and the Emperor Valens dies, and the Goths are just, like, kind of loose
哥特人被彻底消灭，瓦伦斯皇帝驾崩 ，哥特人基本上就……松散了。
in the Balkans. And there was then a long war with them, four years.
在巴尔干半岛。然后，我们与他们 进行了长达四年的战争。
It results in a kind of truce where neither side
这导致了一种双方都无法 达成的休战局面。
wins, and the Romans, for the first time, accept the presence of
胜利之后，罗马人第一 次接受了……的存在。
this quasi-independent Gothic army in the territory of the empire.
这支在帝国境内拥有准独立 地位的哥特军队。
This is unprecedented, as I said, and it creates a lot of
正如我所说，这是史无前例 的，而且会造成很多问题。
tensions and dysfunctions. Okay, so why does
紧张和功能失调。好的， 那么为什么……
the East survive and the West does not, right?
东方幸存下来，西方 则灭亡，对吗？
There's... And so the-- Lots of reasons that we can give here, but one of them
有很多原因……所以——我们可以给出 很多理由，但其中一个是……
is the geography that we were talking about earlier. In other words,
这就是我们之前讨论过的地理 环境。换句话说，
the, without a fleet, which they don't have, the Goths can't cross
由于没有舰队（而他们确实没有 舰队），哥特人无法渡海。
over from Thrace or the western Balkans to Asia Minor and go plunder some of the
从色雷斯或西巴尔干半岛到小亚细亚 ，去掠夺一些东西。
more prosperous provinces. So they're stuck in the Balkans.
更繁荣的省份。所以他们 被困在巴尔干半岛了。
They're gradually pushed kind of in toward the western Balkans, which is, like, the worst
他们逐渐被推向西巴尔干地区 ，那里的情况糟透了。
part you, you know, at the time, like, you wanna be in.
你知道，在那个时候，就像 你想成为其中一员一样。
And eventually, they just decide, "Well, you know, it's kinda nicer in Naples."
最终，他们就决定，“嗯，你知道 ，那不勒斯的环境要好一些。”
And so they go to Italy, right?
所以他们就去了意大利，对吧？
Just because there's just a lot more resources there for them.
仅仅因为他们那里 有更多的资源。
And that's one way that the East just kind of manages to...
而这正是东方得以 ……的方式之一。
It doesn't do this deliberately, but it,
它并非故意这样做，但它
the geography kind of pushes these invaders to the West.
地理环境某种程度上将这些 入侵者推向了西部。
- So that's one. So geography is, some of it's sort of the luck of geography and-
这是其中之一。所以，地理学，有些时候 是地理上的运气成分，而且——
... both of the invaders and the geography of the empire.
……既包括入侵者，也 包括帝国的地理环境。
- Yeah.
- 是的。
- But, you know, the East had a lot of invaders since-
但是，你知道，自那时以来，东方 遭受过很多入侵者——
... and was able to still barely at times-
……有时甚至勉强能做到——
... survive the invaders, so... And some of that could be luck. Some of it
……在入侵者的围攻下幸存下来，所以…… 而这其中可能也有些运气成分。一部分
could be about the nature of the invaders and the, the
可能与入侵者的性质 以及……有关
effectiveness of their military, all that kind of stuff.
他们的军事效能，诸如此 类的事情。
- By the way, it worked in the other direction, too. So if you have, like, Persians or Arabs coming
顺便说一句，反过来也一样有效。所以，如果 有波斯人或阿拉伯人来访的话……
into Asia Minor from the East,
从东方进入小亚细亚，
they usually can't cross over into your Balkan provinces.
他们通常无法进入你 的巴尔干省份。
- Mm-hmm. Right.
嗯。正确的。
- So you can fall back on one side or the other side.
所以你可以选择退守 一边或另一边。
They... If you fortified Constantinople so that it's an impregnable bunker,
他们……如果你把君士坦丁堡加固 成一座坚不可摧的堡垒，
which it was, right? So you're holding your command center in
确实如此，对吧？所以你们 把指挥中心设在……
Constantinople. You can alternate between your European or your Asian
君士坦丁堡。你可以交替使用 欧洲风味和亚洲风味。
provinces, depending on where the trouble is. You can call in reinforcements from either
根据问题发生的地点，可能涉及多个省份 。你可以从任一方向呼叫增援。
side. So the East does have that kind of advantage. This is not the reason
边。所以东方确实拥有这 种优势。这并非原因
why it survives for as long as it does, though it is a reason. You know, also,
虽然这其中必有原因，但它终究会 存活这么久。你知道，还有，
they acquire flamethrowers at some point, which- ... those help, too.
他们后来获得了火焰喷射器 ，这……也很有用。
Um, right? Ultimately, I think it's the decision made by local communities
嗯，对吧？最终，我认为这 取决于当地社区的决定。
to stick with the Roman state, like, ultimately. Like, they're
最终还是要和罗马国家站 在一起。比如，他们是
not going to actively side with invaders.
不会主动站在入侵者一边。
And when the trouble passes, they restore ties with Constantinople
当危机过去后，他们会恢复 与君士坦丁堡的关系。
immediately. Like, this is their natural political home.
立即地。这里就像是 他们天然的政治家园。
And, and that's the question that I'm really trying to answer, like, why does that happen?
而这正是我真正想要回答的问题， 那就是，为什么会发生这种情况？
- You know, we should say, just like we've articulated multiple times, that it, the
你知道，我们应该像我们多次 阐述的那样说，那就是，
Roman Empire survives-
罗马帝国幸存下来——
So it's not like the Roman Empire collapsed and another Byzantine Empire was born.
所以，这并不是说罗马帝国崩溃后， 又诞生了另一个拜占庭帝国。
Really, there is a shift that happens, and part of that
确实，会发生一种转变，而这其中 的一部分原因在于……
shift is because of Constantine,
转变的根源在于君士坦丁。
right? It's not just about where the capital is, but I'm sure that
正确的？这不仅仅关乎首都 在哪里，但我确信……
there's just a general move towards that direction from the West to the East.
总的来说，存在着从西向东 的这种趋势。
- Yeah, yeah.
- 是啊是啊。
- And, and that in many ways, you know, weak emperors and the West, the weak leaders,
而且，在很多方面，你知道，软弱的 皇帝和西方，软弱的领导人，
The structure of government, all these kinds of elements put together-
政府的结构，以及所有 这些要素的组合——
... maybe demographic shifts and declines that have to do
或许这与人口结构的 变化和下降有关。
with the fact that the center of the empire has moved.
因为帝国的中心已经 转移了。
- That's right.
- 这是正确的。
- And so ultimately- ... it's not that the West Roman Empire collapsed, it is
所以归根结底……不是西罗马 帝国崩溃了，而是……
that the center of the Roman Empire shifted.
罗马帝国的中心 发生了转移。
And because of that, the historic West collapsed.
正因如此，历史上的 西方文明崩溃了。
- It's quite striking. So for example, already by, like in the 430s, Constantinople is
- 这非常引人注目。例如，早在公元430 年代，君士坦丁堡就已经……
basically codifying Roman law for the West. So Roman
基本上是将罗马法编纂成册， 使其适用于西方。如此罗马
law in Latin is codified in Constantinople, and then sent
拉丁文法律在君士坦丁堡编纂成 法典，然后送往各地。
to the West as, "Oh, here's your law code."
对西方来说，这就像是“哦 ，这是你们的法律条文”。
And this is in the 430s, so after the alleged division between the two, which
这是在430年代，也就是在两 者之间所谓的分裂之后，
like I said, is kind of loose. It's not hard and fast. In the
就像我说的，有点松散 。这并非一成不变。在
6th century, it is the East that reconquers part of the West under Justinian.
公元6世纪，东方在查士丁尼统治下重新 征服了西方的一部分领土。
- Mm-hmm.
嗯。
- And not only that, he also recodifies Roman law on a much bigger
不仅如此，他还对罗马法进行了 更广泛的重新编纂。
scale, and then that law becomes Western
规模，然后这条规律就变成了西方的。
law. So in a certain sense, Roman law as we know
法律。所以从某种意义上说， 我们所知的罗马法
it comes from Constantinople. It doesn't come from ancient Rome. I mean,
它来自君士坦丁堡。它 并非源自古罗马。我是说，
ultimately it comes from ancient Rome, but we don't have those versions of it. We have
它最终源自古罗马，但我们没有 那些版本的文献。我们有
the East Roman versions of it. It is East
东罗马帝国的版本。它是东边
Rome that reconquers Rome. This is a funny inversion, you know,
罗马人重新征服罗马。这是一 种有趣的颠倒，你知道吗？
because Constantinople is situated in a province, Thrace, which always was
因为君士坦丁堡位于色雷斯省 ，而色雷斯省一直以来都是
sort of considered backwards,
某种程度上被认为是落后的，
right? In the time of, like, the early Caesars, if you were in Rome and you
正确的？在早期凯撒时代， 如果你身处罗马，而你
thought, you know, Thrace, it was like, "Ugh." It's like, you know, some sort of, yeah,
当时我想，你知道，色雷斯，感觉就像，“唉 ”。感觉就像，你知道，某种，嗯，
armpit of the Roman Empire or something, you know? But by Justinian's time,
罗马帝国的腋窝之类的，你知道吗 ？但到了查士丁尼时代，
it's complete inversion. Like, the capital of the Roman world, the heart of it
这完全颠倒了。就像罗马世界 的首都，它的中心一样
is there, and Rome is this kind of backwater provincial city in Italy,
确实存在，而罗马是意大利 那种偏僻的省会城市。
you know, that you've just liberated from the Goths, and it's kind of in ruins. There are wolves roaming the
你知道，你刚刚从哥特人手中解放出来， 而那里现在几乎成了废墟。有狼在游荡
streets of the Forum. So this is a complete, you know,
论坛的街道。所以这是一个 完整的，你知道的，
overhaul of the centers of power. It's turned inside out almost.
对权力中心进行彻底改革。 它几乎完全翻过来了。
- And I think it's fair to say that the reason the East...
我认为可以公平地说， 东方的原因是……
Part of the reason the East lasted as long as it did is the topic that we've
东方之所以能延续如此之久，部分 原因在于我们所讨论的这个话题。
mentioned, which is the structure of government. So can we just zoom out once again
前面提到的就是政府结构。 所以我们能再缩小一下画面吗？
and explain the key ways the government functioned in the East Roman Empire,
并解释东罗马帝国政府 运作的主要方式。
and how it evolved over the lifetime of the empire?
以及它在帝国存续期间 是如何演变的？
- Very broadly speaking, there's civilian and military,
广义上讲，分为平民 和军人。
right? And you might actually add the church. It's entirely plausible to treat the
正确的？你甚至可以把教堂也加上 去。完全有可能对……进行治疗
church as a kind of government institution at this time.
教会当时就像一种 政府机构。
But let's just stick with military and civilian.
但我们还是只讨论军用 和民用领域吧。
the military is pretty straightforward, would be recognizable to any student
军队其实很简单明了，任何 学生都能认出来。
of military history. This is how you recruit, organize, equip,
军事史。这就是你如何招募、 组织和装备人员的方式。
pay, and lead soldiers. And the East Roman state tends to have a
支付薪水，并领导士兵。 东罗马帝国往往具有……
larger military, at least paper strength.
更大的军事力量，至少纸面上的实力。
Active is a different matter. Like, how many soldiers you take on a campaign is a different matter,
积极主动是另一回事。比如，一场战役 中你带多少士兵是另一回事。
but how many soldiers you maintain, like, in the provinces generally, right, is a...
但是，你在各省份通常维持 多少士兵，对吧……
It tends to be on the large side for a medieval society, right? So it compares
对于中世纪社会来说，这算是比较大的 规模了，对吧？所以它是进行比较的。
favorably to, say, the Caliphate later on, which is a much
相比之下，例如后来的哈里发 政权，情况要好得多。
more massive territorial entity. So the military is that. It can have anywhere
更大的领土实体。所以军队就是 这样。它可以位于任何地方
between 100,000 at a minimum, at a low point, up to maybe about 250,000 at a high
最低可能在10万左右， 最高可能达到25万左右。
point, depending on the period. It's a lot of people. It's a lot of men.
点，取决于时期。人很多 。有很多男人。
Factor in their families, right? These are also, like, part of the
把他们的家庭因素也考虑进去 吧？这些也算是……的一部分
whole, you know, military economic complex, if you will.
整个，你知道的， 军事经济复合体。
- And they're career military, so, like, this is their job.
而且他们是职业军人，所以 ，这就是他们的工作。
- Yep, yes.
- 是的，没错。
- And is the military for most of the history of the East Roman
——而且在东罗马帝国历史的大部分 时间里，它都是军队。
Empire defensive military?
帝国防御军事力量？
- Mostly, but not always.
大多数情况下是这样，但并非总是如此。
- Yeah. And we'll talk about Justinian.
- 是的。接下来我们来谈谈查士丁尼。
- Sure.
- 当然。
Um, and so then you have the civilian administration. Civilian administration does a number of
嗯，然后就有了文职政府。民事 行政部门开展多项工作
things. Principally, it is to find the funds to pay for this army,
事物。首要任务是筹集资金来 支付这支军队的开支。
which is the single largest expense on the state budget,
这是州预算中最 大的单项支出。
right? And so in order to find those funds, it has
正确的？因此，为了筹集 这些资金，它必须
to have census of the assets, and it has
对资产进行普查，并且它已经
to be able to tax them, and there are lots of different ways of doing that. So
以便能够对他们征税，而征税 的方式有很多种。所以
the civilian administration has a number of tax bureaus,
民政部门下设 多个税务局，
records keeping this sort of thing, also a legal branch for
记录这类事情，也 是一个法律部门
resolving disputes with the imperial fisc. Okay. But the civilian
解决与帝国财政的纠纷 。好的。但平民
administration does a number of other things, too. For example, the whole legal
行政部门还会做很多其他 事情。例如，整个法律
regulation of the, of the empire, the courts, judges, courts of appeal,
对帝国、法院、法官 、上诉法院的监管
Or also issuing laws, keeping records, all,
或者也包括颁布法律 、保存记录等等。
all of this. And those are the main bureaus that
这一切。这些是 主要的机构：
have to do with the subjects of the empire.
与帝国的臣民 有关。
The emperors obviously maintain bureaus that are for things like diplomacy,
皇帝们显然设有负责外交 等事务的机构。
right, or running the palace staff,
对，或者管理宫廷工作人员，
Because the palace is a huge institution, right, with...
因为皇宫是一个庞大 的机构，对吧……
And then there are a number of endowments that, you know, major
此外，还有一些捐赠基金 ，你知道，数额巨大的
churches, Hagia Sophia, for example, has hundreds of staff, clergy to, you
例如，像圣索菲亚大教堂这样的教堂， 有数百名工作人员，包括神职人员。
know, readers to whatever, and so they need to be paid, and so you need
要知道，读者们对任何事物都有不同的看法 ，所以他们需要获得报酬，所以你也需要
endowments. The imperial household, it has expenses, so it needs
捐赠基金。皇室有开支 ，所以需要
endowments, right? So there's a lot of land that's earmarked
捐赠基金，对吧？所以有 很多土地已被划拨出来。
For these kinds of expenses, that requires administration. So,
这类开支需要进行 管理。所以，
this multiplies, right? I mean, go on and on and on and on.
这个数字会成倍增长，对吧？我的意思 是，一直说下去，没完没了。
- And I'm sure the tax code is not a simple flat tax. It's...
而且我确信税法并非简单 的单一税率。它是...
... probably incredibly complicated. So it's just like in the United States,
可能极其复杂。所以 情况和美国一样。
it feels like the majority of the United States is basically lawyers and the IRS.
感觉美国的大部分人口基本上 都是律师和国税局人员。
That's maybe 98%, I think, is lawyers.
我想，其中大概有98%是律师。
- Lawyers.
律师。
- I'm not sure it's scientifically-
我不确定这在科学上是否成立。
- I thought they shrunk the IRS down now to a size that it can't, like, actually do anything.
- 我以为他们已经把美国国税局缩减 到几乎什么都做不了的地步了。
- They shrunk it down...
他们把它缩小了……
- I thought it was just...
我当时以为只是……
- ... to just 90% now.
——现在只剩下90%了。
- 90, just 90.
- 90，只有90。
- No. I think there is something—this is another,
不，我觉得还有点什么 ——这是另一个问题。
Conversation about human nature and about the, the nature of
关于人性以及 本质的对话
governments, but there's something about,
政府，但其中还有一些其他因素，
like I think it's impossible to have an IRS-type organization that doesn't grow.
我认为像美国国税局这样的 组织不可能不发展壮大。
I think maybe with good intentions because you can't— You have to, like...
我觉得或许是出于好意，因为 你不能——你必须，就像……
... everybody always comes to you, "Well, I don't... Here's my special
……每个人都会来找你，“嗯，我 没有……这是我的特别之处。”
case. I want my tax to be lower."
案件。我希望我的税能降低一些。
And they kind of add another line. "All right, if you have...
他们又加了一行。 “ 好的，如果你有……”
... purple hair, you..."
……紫头发，你……”
... the tax decrease. And so you keep adding, and then of course, the more you add,
……减税。所以你就不断地添加 ，当然，你添加得越多，
the more opaque the thing becomes, therefore corruption seeps in
事物越不透明，腐败 就越容易滋生。
or co- you know, maybe not like official corruption, but...
或者，你知道，也许不是像官方 腐败那样，但是……
... corruption light, and then that tax code grows, and
……腐败程度有所减轻， 然后税法开始完善，并且
then all of a sudden you have these big institutions that then-
然后突然之间，你就有了 这些大型机构，然后——
... encourage corruption, and then there's a bureaucracy, and there's a
……助长腐败，然后就会滋生 官僚主义，然后就会……
momentum, and this is just how humans are.
惯性，这就是人类的本性。
- Yes. So this happens in East Roman society too. I'll give you some examples. So,
- 是的。东罗马社会也存在这种情况 。我给你举几个例子。所以，
there's not a tax code as such, but what you-- The way it
虽然没有严格意义上的税法 ，但你——它的方式
operates is through basically exemptions.
其运作基本上是通过豁免来实现的。
So you petition for an exemption. You might be
所以你申请豁免 。你可能是
a monastery, you might be a wealthy la- You might be someone well-connected to the court.
如果你身处修道院，你可能是一位富有的拉奥 ——你可能是一位与宫廷关系密切的人。
You might be a struggling provincial village, and you petition the emperor or
你可能是一个生活困苦的偏远 乡村，你向皇帝请愿，或者
some official, and you say, "Hey, we know we had a bad season," or, "The barbarians came
一些官员会说：“嘿，我们知道我们上赛季 表现不佳”，或者“野蛮人来了”。
through and they took all of our... We can't pay the taxes. Could we have an exemption?"
他们拿走了我们所有的东西……我们 交不起税。我们可以申请豁免吗？
And emperors often are granting these exemptions for very
而且皇帝经常会授予这些特权，但 仅限于非常有限的情况。
specific things, like maybe for this year or for that tax or whatever.
具体的事情，比如今年的事情， 或者那笔税款的事情等等。
The problem is that the emperors are discovering every once in a while that their officials are,
问题在于，皇帝们时不时会 发现他们的官员们……
are granting these exemptions sort of on their own. So every once in a while, the emperors have
他们基本上是自行授予这些豁免权 的。所以，皇帝们时不时会……
to, like, clear house when they have to, like,
比如，当他们不得不 的时候，清理房子，
cancel all of these exemptions and start the whole process again. But,
取消所有这些豁免，然后 重新开始整个流程。但，
later on, when-- once we start to have documentation, like maybe in the 11th century,
后来，当——一旦我们开始有 文献记载，比如可能在11世纪，
we see that every little, well, not every,
我们看到，每一个小的，嗯，不是每一个，
but we have all these monasteries, these little villages, these high officials, and they all have these
但是我们有这么多寺院、这么多小 村庄、这么多高级官员，他们都有这些
documents that give them exemption from this or that or the other thing, and it gets
文件赋予他们豁免权，可以免除这 、那或其他事项，然后就……
so complicated and that's how it works.
事情就是这么复杂，但它就是这样运作的。
- Uh, but it is the engine of society that makes the whole thing work 'cause you
呃，但它是社会运转的 引擎，因为……
have to fund--
必须提供资金——
I mean, there's infrastructure projects, but you have to also fund the army, and the
我的意思是，基础设施项目固然重要 ，但你也得给军队提供资金，还有……
army's necessary to defend against all the military incursions.
军队是抵御一切军事入侵 的必要力量。
A good fraction of the bureaucracy seemed to have been eunuchs,
官僚机构中似乎有相当 一部分人是太监。
which are castrated men. Can you explain why this was a prominent thing?
他们是被阉割的男性。你能解释 一下为什么这件事如此突出吗？
- The eunuchs are part of the household staff of the emperor.
太监是皇帝的 宫廷侍从。
So that would be like, what would it be? The West Wing of the White House or something like this.
所以，那会是什么呢？白宫 西翼之类的地方。
So they are the people who handle the imperial person,
所以他们是负责 侍奉皇室的人。
the bedchamber, the organization of palace life,
寝宫，宫廷 生活的组织，
things like banquets, you know, these kinds of things, the wardrobe.
比如宴会之类的事情，你 知道，还有服装之类的。
And why are they important? So for starters, if you're, like,
它们为什么重要？ 首先，如果你是，
physically with the emperor all day, right? Like,
对吧？整天都和皇帝 在一起。喜欢，
you're handling the meetings, you're... Right? People can come to you and say, "Hey, I need
你负责开会，对吧？人们可能会来 找你说：“嘿，我需要……”
you to put in a good word for whatever," right? So they can
让你帮他们说好话，对 吧？这样他们就可以
get things done. So you bribe them, they get things done. So they're
把事情做好。所以你贿赂他们，他们 就能把事情办成。所以他们是
very useful in this way. They're also kind of hated for that reason.
这样非常有用。也正因为如此 ，他们多少有点招人讨厌。
Right? But they're also kind of there to be hated. In other words, they
正确的？但他们某种程度上也是被人 憎恨的对象。换句话说，他们
soak up a lot of the frustration that people sometimes feel when
吸收人们有时感受 到的许多挫败感
they're not getting, you know, what they want from the court.
他们并没有从法庭那里 得到他们想要的东西。
Okay. That's one thing. Here's the other thing that's more interesting.
好的。这是一件事。还 有一件更有趣的事。
How do you as an emperor make sure that your bureaucracy doesn't displace
作为皇帝，您如何确保您 的官僚机构不会取代……
you? Like, if the bureaucracy is handling all the matters of running the empire,
你？比如说，如果帝国的所有运转 事务都由官僚机构负责，
what do we need you for? Right? Like, the bureaucracy can develop rules of its own-
我们需要你做什么？正确的？例如， 官僚机构可以制定自己的规则——
... for solving all the problems for dealing with
……为了解决所有与 处理……相关的问题
petitions and exemptions and whatever. Like, they can do it. So
请愿书、豁免申请等等 。他们能做到。所以
where's your power exactly? So what the emperors did not want is to
你的权力究竟在哪里？所以皇帝们 不希望看到的是……
be displaced or overshadowed by these kinds of more
被这些类型的更多事物 所取代或掩盖
impersonal institutions. And so they would often set up, like,
非人格化的机构。所以他们 经常会这样安排，
So this could be a bit confusing.
所以这可能会有点令人困惑。
So eunuchs were perfect for this reason because often
所以太监在这个方面非常 合适，因为他们经常
their origin was from outside the empire, or they were former slaves. They
他们的出身地要么来自帝国 之外，要么是以前的奴隶。他们
weren't connected to, like, networks of powerful families.
他们与某些权势家族 的网络没有任何联系。
So you knew that they would generally be loyal to you because they
所以你知道他们通常会对 你忠诚，因为他们
depended entirely on you, the emperor, for their position and their power.
他们的地位和权力完全 依赖于您，皇帝。
And what you would sometimes do is you'd say, "Okay, I'm putting you in charge of,
你有时会说：“好的 ，我让你负责……”
like, this army." Literally, like putting you in charge of an army,
就像这支军队一样。”字面意思 就是让你统领一支军队。
just so that you can counterbalance the kind of
只是为了 平衡这种
networks of established generals, and you'll have, like, a eunuch
通过建立由老练将领组成的网络，你 就会得到一个类似太监的角色。
from my wardrobe. You know, I'm putting him in charge. And so this
从我的衣橱里。你知道， 我让他负责。所以就是这样
kind of shook things up a little bit so that people who were part of a
这多少有点改变了现状，让 那些参与其中的人……
system or a network could never fully count that that could get them all
系统或网络永远无法完全预料 到这种情况会如何发生。
the power that they wanted. They now have to answer to this eunuch from the wardrobe who's, like,
他们想要的权力。他们现在不得不向衣橱 里那个太监交代，他就像……
outside of their system. And sometimes these eunuchs were extremely
在他们的系统之外。而有时 这些太监极其……
competent like Narses, Justinian's general, who
像查士丁尼的将军纳尔塞斯 那样能干的人
defeated the Goths in Italy in this massive battle. Like, this guy was a total
在这场大规模战役中击败了意大利的 哥特人。这家伙简直就是个彻头彻尾的混蛋
hardass. And he was this little old man. He was very old, and he was tiny, and he
铁腕人物。他是个矮小的老头。他 年纪很大了，个子也很小，而且
was a eunuch, and the Goths laughed at him, but he had the last laugh, right?
他是个太监，哥特人嘲笑他 ，但他笑到了最后，对吧？
- Is there some component to them being eunuchs, so they can't
- 他们是否因为是太监 而无法……
propagate the bloodline?
延续血脉？
- Yeah. They can't have their own family, so they can't be, like, looking out for their own
- 是的。他们无法组建自己的家庭 ，所以也无法照顾自己的家人。
offspring. They're kind of isolated individuals who depend entirely on your favor.
后代。他们是些与世隔绝 的人，完全依赖你的恩惠。
- Is it known whether the castration is almost always by force?
- 是否有人知道阉割几乎总是 强迫进行的？
- There are eunuchs in society generally. They're often bishops. They're appointed
社会上普遍存在太监。他们通常 是主教。他们是被任命的。
Patriarch of Constantinople sometimes. They're-
君士坦丁堡牧首有时 。他们是——
... they're in all kinds of positions. Many of them are
……他们处于各种各样的 位置。他们当中许多人是
children who are enslaved and castrated against their will.
被奴役并违背意愿 被阉割的儿童。
Sometimes, however, they are castrated very much according to the will of their families.
然而，有时他们会被阉割，这很大 程度上是出于他们家人的意愿。
Um, in some parts of, like in
嗯，在某些地方，比如在
Caucasia, there were some regions that were famous for producing eunuchs,
在高加索地区，有些地方 以盛产太监而闻名。
also in, in Persia and so forth.
还有在波斯等地。
But also, we are pretty sure that this happened within the empire,
但我们也几乎可以肯定，这 件事发生在帝国境内。
because there were some families that, like, really wanted to place a eunuch at the court.
因为有些家族非常希望在 宫廷里安插一个太监。
Um, so from Paphlagonia, there were a number of... This is in
嗯，所以从帕夫拉戈尼亚 出发，有很多……这是在
northern Asia Minor. And so they would... It was almost like a family strategy.
小亚细亚北部。所以他们就这么做了 ……这几乎成了一种家族策略。
- I mean, it's fascinating. It's fascinating that they had so,
我的意思是，这太有趣了。他们竟然 有这么多，真是令人着迷。
So much representation in the inner circles-
核心圈子里有很多 代表人物——
... of the emperor, and therefore had real influence.
……是皇帝的亲信， 因此拥有实际影响力。
- Oh, yeah. But this was the case always, even in Rome, like in the Julio-Claudians
- 哦，是的。但这种情况一直存在，即使在罗马 也是如此，比如在朱利奥-克劳狄王朝时期。
under-
在下面-
... you know, the first Caesars. There are all these powerful eunuchs, and the,
你知道，就是那些最早的凯撒们。这里 有一群权势滔天的太监，而且，
the senatorial class always hates them. I mean, it's just the s- it's the same dynamic.
参议员阶层总是憎恨他们。我 的意思是，只是……情况一样。
- Uh, one of the interesting things you've said as an aside in one of the many
呃，你在众多言论中的一次插话里 提到的一件很有趣的事。
podcasts that I listened with you is you said that there were no isolated people,
我和你一起听的播客里 ，你说没有孤立的人，
You know, people that are disconnected from the empire,
你知道，那些与 帝国脱节的人，
Maybe who, for example, don't know about the taxes or just don't feel
例如，有些人可能不了解税收 ，或者根本不觉得有必要。
integrated into the system. I mean, that's really interesting to me, that
已集成到系统中。我的意思 是，这真的让我很感兴趣。
there's so much connectivity, there's so much cohesion- ... as an entire peoples.
彼此之间的联系如此紧密，凝聚力 如此之强……作为一个整体民族。
- These people do not exist, these isolated peasants. This is a
这些人并不存在，这些与 世隔绝的农民。这是
myth that I, one day I'm going to write a chapter about this
有一种说法是，总有一天我会 写一章关于这个的章节。
because it's this idea that you occasionally encounter, well, actually quite
因为正是这种想法，你偶尔会遇到 ，嗯，实际上是相当
often in the scholarship, that there are these sort of rural communities out
在学术研究中，经常会 提到这类农村社区。
there somewhere that don't know what's going on in
有些人根本不知道 发生了什么
Constantinople. They might not know, even know who the emperor is. They're cut
君士坦丁堡。他们可能根本不知道，甚至 不知道皇帝是谁。它们被切掉了
off. Maybe a tax official will show up every once in a
离开。也许税务官员 偶尔会出现。
while, maybe not, and they just live their lives on their own,
或许并非如此，他们只是 过着自己的生活。
unaffected by the, say, state, because the medieval state,
不受国家的影响，因为 中世纪国家，
we suspect, is you know, always
我们怀疑，你知道，总是
powerless and can't, you know, affect people's lives. There's
无能为力，也无法影响 人们的生活。有
no proof for these communities at all. At most, you
这些社区根本没有任何证据 。最多，你
might try to find some, like, actual hermits, like,
或许可以试着找找，比如 ，真正的隐士，比如，
actual Christian ascetic hermits who try to go out and find this situation,
真正的基督教苦行隐士试图 走出去寻找这种情况，
and sometimes they're described in the text as, like, oh, so, so-and-so went so
有时文中会这样描述 ：哦，某某去了……
far out into the mountains that, like, not even the tax census people
深入山区，甚至连税务 普查员都到不了。
showed up there, which tells you how they think about what it means to be
他们出现在那里，这说明他们是 如何看待“存在”的意义的。
isolated, right? So this is not a... This is a state in which every
孤立无援，对吧？所以这不是 ……这是一种所有……的状态
arable, you know, piece of arable land has been censused for
可耕地，你知道，一块可耕地 已经进行过人口普查。
centuries. It's not like you can hide a village, right?
几个世纪。你不可能把一 个村庄藏起来，对吧？
And the, the taxation process is not like, what, they visit
而且，税务流程并非 像他们访问时那样。
once a year, give us some coin, and we'll leave. It's actually more like three
每年给我们一些零钱，我们就 离开。实际上更像是三个
times a year. And the taxes is not just coin and
一年几次。而且税收 不仅仅是硬币和
maybe a payment in kind or something, but it's, it's a whole bunch of things like
或许是实物支付之类的，但实际上 ，还有很多其他方面，比如……
services and recruits and all... You're right. And once you
服务和招聘等等……你 说得对。一旦你
start adding all of these things up, it creates a very dense,
把所有这些加起来，就形成 了一个非常密集的……
Institutional matrix in which all communities are enmeshed.
所有社群都交织其中 的制度矩阵。
They can't get out of it. Also, they, they have a church, don't they?
他们无法摆脱困境。而且，他们 ，他们有教堂，对吧？
And if they have a church, they have the calendar. And of course they have the calendar because...
如果他们有教堂，他们就有教堂日历 。当然，他们也有日历，因为……
So, like, how do they organize time and space and
那么，他们是如何 组织时间和空间的呢？
boundaries and all of these things? No, this is all state institutions. How do they pay for anything?
界限以及所有这些事情？不，这些都 是国家机构。他们怎么支付费用？
They have coins. Coins are everywhere. So I think
他们有硬币。硬币无处 不在。所以我觉得
that these institutions structured the way that everyone,
这些机构构建了 每个人参与的方式，
even in village communities, even in the most isolated ones, supposedly,
即使在乡村社区，即使是最偏远 的社区，据说也是如此。
how they thought about things like time and space and value and
他们如何看待时间、 空间和价值等事物？
relations and power and kinship and so forth.
人际关系、权力、 血缘关系等等。
- So what you're saying is taxation is the thing that brings the empire together.
所以你的意思是，税收是维系 帝国团结的纽带。
- It is, principally, yes.
基本上来说，是的。
- I mean, it's- ... it's true, right? This is, like, this is how you know.
我的意思是，这……这是真的，对 吧？这就是，你是如何知道的。
- Yeah. But on top of that is layered things like the economy,
- 是的。但除此之外，还有 经济等诸多复杂因素。
coins, right? But also there's the church.
是硬币，对吧？但还有教会。
- Yeah, and the church is important, just like you said.
- 是的，教会很重要 ，就像你说的那样。
Yeah. And there's churches throughout the empire.
是的。帝国各地 都有教堂。
- Yes, and they have sermons, and they pray for the
是的，他们也会布道 ，也会祈祷。
emperor after this service. No, there are no isolated communities.
皇帝驾崩之后。不， 没有孤立的社区。
- So one of the things I briefly mentioned just would be nice to
所以我刚才简单提到的一件事，如果 能做到以下几点就太好了：
elaborate on is this term of monarchic republic.
详细阐述一下这个术语—— 君主制共和国。
So we've been throwing around words like kingdom and republic and empire and,
所以我们一直在谈论王国、共和国 和帝国之类的词语，
Monarchy. So what is the actual... What's a good applicable term to what this
君主制。那么，实际的……有没有一个 合适的术语来形容这种情况？
thing is- ... the East Roman Empire?
问题是——……东罗马帝国？
- That's an excellent question, and I'm glad you flagged that
- 这是一个很好的问题，我很 高兴你提出了这个问题。
because we call it conventionally Byzantine Empire, and it's neither of those things
因为我们通常称它为拜占庭帝国，但它既 不是拜占庭帝国也不是拜占庭帝国。
really. We talked about Byzantine.
真的。我们讨论了拜占庭帝国。
Now, empire's a bit of a problem because first of all, There's no term in Greek,
现在，“帝国”这个词有点问题，因为 首先，希腊语里没有对应的词。
In the Greek that they use at this period that corresponds to our notion of empire.
他们当时使用的希腊语与我们 今天对帝国的概念相对应。
It's not part of the official terms. It's not even... They didn't even have a term
这并非官方条款的一部分。甚至 ……他们连个术语都没有。
for it. You could have... There's some terms that might mean something like state
为此。你可能……有些术语可能 意味着类似“状态”之类的意思。
Arche maybe or kratos. But for the most part, it's either basileia, which we might
可能是阿尔凯，也可能是奎托斯。但大多数 情况下，要么是 basileia，我们可能
translate as monarchy or politeia, which is polity.
可译为君主制 或政体。
And politeia in Greek, polity, is a Greek translation of Latin res publica.
希腊语politeia（政体）是拉丁语 res publica的希腊语翻译。
Res publica doesn't mean republic the way we mean it for the Romans,
Res publica 指的并非我们今天 理解的罗马共和国。
like a non-monarchical regime, right? That's how we mean, like, the American Republic or, you
就像非君主制政体一样，对吧？我们就是这个 意思，比如，美利坚共和国，或者，你
know. That's a usage that came in later, like during the
知道。这种用法是后来才出现 的，比如在……期间
Enlightenment. In Latin, a res publica is the
启示。在拉丁语中，res publica 指的是……
common affairs, the common interest of a people who are
共同事务，人民 的共同利益
constituted as a political community, regardless of the type of
构成政治共同体 ，无论其类型如何
regime that they have. Like even Cicero could imagine the Roman res
他们所拥有的政权。就像西塞罗 都能想象到罗马的资源一样。
publica governed by a king or by a senate or by a
由国王、元老院或…… 统治的公共领域
democracy. And they continue to use that term. We don't use it
民主。他们继续使用这个 术语。我们不用它
according to Roman norms. We use it according to modern norms, the term republic.
按照罗马规范。我们按照现代规范 使用“共和国”一词。
So they continue to call it a res publica or a polity under the emperors
所以他们继续称其为共和国 或皇帝统治下的政体。
as well, right? And it was understood that the role of the
也是，对吧？人们 普遍认为，角色是
emperor, whether he's Caesar or basileus or whatever, whatever
皇帝，不管他是凯撒、巴西勒斯 还是别的什么，都无所谓。
language, was to serve the polity. They keep saying this.
语言，是为了服务于政治体 。他们一直这么说。
So the terms that occur in the sources most commonly are
因此，文献中最常 出现的术语是：
basileia of the Romans, polity of the Romans, or Romania,
罗马人的王国，罗马人的 政体，或罗马尼亚
which is the proper name of this state. Not empire.
这是该州的正式名称 。不是帝国。
Now, empire. Empire in modern English commonly,
现在，帝国时代。现代英语 中通常所说的帝国，
an empire is a state that's created when one group conquers a bunch of
帝国是指一个群体征服多 个国家而建立的国家。
others and rules them. It could be an ethnic group. It could be an ethnoreligious group.
其他人并统治他们。这可能是一个民族群体 。这可能是一个民族宗教团体。
It could be a political group, whatever. But there's an act of conquest, and
它可能是某个政治团体，或者其他什么 。但其中也包含征服行为，而且
results in a state where one group is ruling over others.
最终导致一个群体统治 其他群体的局面。
That's not how Romania is actually constituted. We've talked about this. It's, for
罗马尼亚的实际政体并非如此。我们讨论 过这个问题。这是，因为
the most part, all Roman citizens ruling like Roman
大多数情况下，所有罗马公民 都像罗马人一样统治。
subjects ruling themselves, through their own government.
臣民通过自己的 政府进行统治。
So it's not an empire strictly speaking. Now, occasionally,
所以严格来说，它算不上一 个帝国。现在，偶尔，
they will conquer other people, right? We talked about the warfare. Sometimes it's not just
他们会征服其他民族，对吗？我们谈到 了战争。有时候，这不仅仅是
defensive. Sometimes it's offensive, right?
防守型。有时候这样做 确实会冒犯人，对吧？
In that case, you do establish a- an imperial
在这种情况下，你确实 建立了一个帝国。
relationship. Like we, the Romans, are ruling over this other group. Could
关系。就像我们罗马人统治 着其他族群一样。可以
be Slavs, it could be Bulgarians for a while, it could be whatever. Or,
可能是斯拉夫人，也可能暂时是保加利亚人 ，什么都有可能。或者，
even some Muslims in northern Syria for a while in the 11th century,
甚至在11世纪，叙利亚北部的一些 穆斯林也曾一度如此。
who-- and you are not Romans.
你们——而且你们不是罗马人。
And that's an imperial relationship. The question is, how many of these imperial relationships do
那是一种帝国式的关系。问题是， 这些帝国关系中有多少是……
you need to decide that, well, we've reached a tipping point, and
你需要做出决定，我们已经 到达了一个临界点，而且
now we're just gonna call the whole thing an empire? Personally, I don't
现在我们就把整个帝国都称为帝国了 吗？就我个人而言，我不这么认为。
think we ever reach that point. I mean, all states, even today,
想想我们是否会达到那个地步。我的意思 是，所有州，即使是今天也是如此。
have like minorities.
像少数族裔一样。
Some of them are part of that state because they were conquered once upon a time.
有些国家之所以成为该国的一部分， 是因为它们曾经被征服过。
But we don't call those states empires necessarily. Even though... Like,
但我们未必会将这些国家称为 帝国。即使……比如，
look at the United Kingdom. Well, Wales was conquered.
看看英国。威尔士 被征服了。
And, you know, the Welsh have their own identity, their own language.
你知道，威尔士人有自己的 身份认同，自己的语言。
I don't know that you would call that now an imperial relationship.
我不知道现在是否还 能称之为帝国关系。
Maybe. I don't know.
或许。我不知道。
- I think there's also a synonymous use of the word empire that refers to
我认为“帝国”一词还有一 个同义词，指的是……
the power that the state has-
国家拥有的权力——
... in the global context geopolitically. So sometimes
……从全球地缘政治 角度来看。所以有时候
empire is used synonymously with superpower, meaning it's one of the primary-
帝国一词与超级大国同义，意味 着它是主要的——
... nations in the world, and it doesn't necessarily have to do with the
世界各国，但这并 不一定与……有关
imperial nature of its history.
其历史具有帝国性质。
- That's true.
- 这是真的。
- Hence the sort of American empire, US empire.
因此才有了美国帝国，即 美利坚帝国。
- Yes. Though you would never characterize the American political regime as an
- 是的。尽管你绝不会将美国 政治体制描述为……
imperial one insofar as it does not have an emperor, for example. But anyway,
例如，帝国没有皇帝 。不过，总之，
yes. The problem is that in my field, we use the term empire
是的。问题在于，在我的领域， 我们使用“帝国”这个词。
conventionally, even when what you just described is
通常来说，即使你 刚才描述的情况是
clearly not happening, like even toward the end. It's not a major world
显然这种情况并没有发生，即使到了 最后也是如此。它不是一个主要的世界
power. It, like, has a few islands in the Peloponnese, and, but we call it
力量。它就像是伯罗奔尼撒半岛上的 几个岛屿，而且，但我们称它为
empire and the emperor, and it's like, it's completely ridiculous. There's not even a
帝国和皇帝，这简直太荒谬 了。甚至连一个都没有
term in their language for that sort of thing.
他们语言中用来形容 这类事物的词。
anyway, we can call things whatever we want, just so we understand what the reality
总之，我们可以随意称呼事物， 只要我们能理解现实就行。
is- ... and what we are using those terms to mean.
是……以及我们使用 这些术语的含义。
I think that's the important thing. Yeah.
我认为那才是最重要的。是的。
- So then let's look at words which are both fascinating, monarchic republic.
那么，让我们来看两个非常吸引 人的词：君主制共和国。
- Right.
- 正确的。
- Why is that a good term for the East Roman Empire?
为什么说“东罗马帝国 ”是一个合适的名称？
- Uh, because they understood it very much to be a polity in the Roman sense
呃，因为他们非常认同 罗马意义上的政体。
of a res publica that was governed by a regime that was monarchical.
一个由君主制政权 统治的共和国。
- So those two elements, there's an emperor dude at the top,
所以，这两个要素，顶端 是一个皇帝，
and it functioned politically like a republic.
它在政治上运作 得像一个共和国。
- Also, the emperor was expected to be working for the republic.
此外，人们还期望皇帝 为共和国效力。
Like, they keep saying this. So, like, this was their conception.
他们总是这么说。所以 ，这就是他们的构想。
You don't find it, for example, in other kinds of dynastic empires,
例如，在其他类型的王朝帝国 中就找不到这种情况。
The ones that don't emerge from within the context of an ancient
那些并非源于古代 背景的事物
republic. So this is another reason why I find this civilization so
共和国。所以，这也是我发现这个 文明如此……的另一个原因。
fascinating, right? I mean, we mentioned the, the Greek and the Roman and the Christian
是不是很精彩？我的意思是，我们 提到了希腊、罗马和基督教。
elements that are kind of jostling together. This is fascinating to me in part
各种元素相互碰撞融合在一起。 这让我觉得很有意思，部分原因如此。
because it's this weird combination of monarchical
因为它是一种奇怪 的君主制组合
power, like in terms of executive institutions— ... and a republican kind of
权力，例如行政机构的 权力——……以及共和式的
baseline ideology on which it operates. Yeah, and they, they
它所依据的基本意识形态 。是的，还有他们，他们
sometimes come to a head.
有时会发展到白热化阶段。
- Is there at all a degree to which it's a military dictatorship?
- 它在某种程度上是军事 独裁政权吗？
Because especially when it's the general in the emperor's seat,
因为尤其当坐在皇帝宝座 上的是将军时，
yes, there's a republic, yes, there's political discussion, but the army has
是的，这里有个共和国，是的，这里 有政治讨论，但是军队却……
a lot of power. So to what degree is it a military dictatorship, as is
强大的力量。那么，它在多大程度 上是军事独裁政权呢？
sometimes talked about when you talk about the Roman Empire?
谈到罗马帝国时，有时 会提到这个吗？
- Yeah, so Augustus' position, for example, and that of his
- 是的，例如奥古斯都 的地位，以及他的
successors is, is talked about as a military dictatorship. In other words, when
继承者们被认为是军事 独裁政权。换句话说，当
push comes to shove— ... and the basis of political power is the army,
到了关键时刻——……而政治 权力的基础就是军队，
then I suppose it's legitimate for historians to talk
那么我想历史学家谈论这些话题 也是合情合理的。
about a military dictatorship. But here's why I don't think
关于一个军事独裁政权。 但我认为并非如此。
the Eastern Roman Empire is a military dictatorship. Even though, again,
东罗马帝国是一个军事独裁 政权。即便如此，
the emperors control the armies, and the armies themselves will often have a say
皇帝掌控军队，而军队本身 也往往拥有发言权。
in who becomes emperor, like through the civil wars that we mentioned.
皇帝的继位者是谁，就像我们 之前提到的内战一样。
Okay. The reason why I don't think it's a military dictatorship is because
好的。我不认为它是军事 独裁政权的原因是：
they almost never, very, very, very rarely use the army as an instrument of social
他们几乎从不、非常、非常、 极少将军队用作社会工具。
control.
控制。
- Is that, isn't that strange to you? Because you see that being done
- 这，你不觉得奇怪吗？因为 你亲眼目睹了这一切。
through so much of human history. And the fact they don't resort to that,
在人类历史的大部分时期。而 他们并没有诉诸那种手段，
I mean, they, for 1,000 years, that's just not a thing.
我的意思是，在过去的1000年里 ，这根本不是事实。
- As a way of keeping down the population, you just don't see it.
——作为一种控制人口增长 的手段，你根本看不到。
And part of the reason for that is I don't think the population needs to be kept down.
部分原因是，我认为 人口不需要被控制。
Like, this gets back to the consensus that we were talking about. The understanding is that the army
这样一来，就又回到了我们之前讨论 的共识上。人们普遍认为军队
is there to protect the Roman people.
其目的是保护罗马人民。
And is often recruited among them. And for most of the period that I study, is like
而且经常从他们当中招募。在我学习的 大部分时间里，情况都是这样的。
lives among them. So when the emperors have to call up the army, they're literally
生活在他们中间。所以当皇帝需要 征召军队时，他们实际上是
calling up soldiers from local villages.
从当地村庄征召士兵。
- It's just incredible that this worked. I guess the civil war thing
简直难以置信，这竟然奏效 了。我猜是内战那件事
is, as a mechanism, is effective. 'Cause you just, throughout human
作为一种机制，它是有效的。 因为你只是，贯穿整个人类
history, I mean, you look at even recent history, it's just a very
历史，我的意思是，即使看看 近代史，也是一个非常
common thing for a authoritarian figure to use the army to suppress people.
独裁者利用军队镇压人民 是司空见惯的事情。
- Yeah, but isn't that dangerous, though? Look at how many modern regimes
- 是啊，但这难道不危险吗？ 看看有多少现代政权
tried to use their own armies against their people who are in a moment of rising up.
他们试图利用自己的军队 镇压正在起义的人民。
- It doesn't last.
——但这不会持久。
- Well, it's a risk. Like the Arab Spring.
- 这确实存在风险。就像阿拉伯之春一样。
Especially in Egypt. And you could, you could tell for those three weeks
尤其是在埃及。而且，在那 三周里，你肯定能看出来。
that Mubarak was trying to decide whether he could
穆巴拉克当时正在 考虑他是否能够
actually count on the army to suppress the protesters or not,
究竟要指望军队镇压抗议者 还是不会镇压，
because you never know what they're going to do if you ask
因为你永远不知道如果 你问了他们会怎么做。
them to fire on a civilian population. It can backfire on you badly.
让他们向平民开火。这样做可能会 给你带来严重的后果。
So I think that is a very dangerous force to use, and
所以我认为使用这种 力量非常危险，而且
even in the context of modern regimes, can result in a regime change.
即使在现代政权的背景下，也 可能导致政权更迭。
- Absolutely, and there's huge wisdom behind that, but, you know, leaders are
没错，这其中蕴含着巨大的智慧 ，但是，你知道，领导者是
not always wise, often not wise.
并非总是明智，往往不明智。
And often maybe they start out wise, but power corrupts them over time,
而且他们起初或许很聪明，但权力 会随着时间的推移腐蚀他们。
and so the fact that this does not happen just over and over and over and over-
因此，事实上，这种情况并没有 一遍又一遍地发生——
... in the East Roman Empire is, is, there's just a signal there that's
……在东罗马帝国，就是， 那里有一个信号，那就是
fascinating. And I mean, this goes to the book that you want to be working on-
迷人。我的意思是，这关系 到你想创作的那本书——
... About why the thing lasts. So.
……关于事物为何能长久存在。所以。
- There's one emperor who does do that, and that's Justinian.
——确实有一位皇帝这样 做过，那就是查士丁尼。
- Mm-hmm. Yeah, he gets wild.
嗯。是的，他玩得很疯。
- Right. Yeah.
- 正确的。是的。
- So let's talk about Justinian. We have to. We have to talk about Justinian.
那么，我们来谈谈查士丁尼吧。我们 必须。我们必须谈谈查士丁尼。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- one of the most impactful Roman emperors in history,
——历史上最具影响力 的罗马皇帝之一，
started as a peasant, and rose in power to become emperor.
出身农民，最终崛起 成为皇帝。
He fought wars of conquest and was very consequential and impactful.
他发动了征服战争，产生 了非常重大的影响。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- So who was he?
那么他究竟是谁？
- All right. So Justinian was the emperor from 527 to
- 好的。所以查士丁尼从公元 527年到公元530年在位。
565, so quite a long reign. He was the nephew of the previous emperor, Justin I,
565年，所以他的统治时间相当长。 他是前任皇帝查士丁一世的侄子。
who was an older man, ruled for just under a decade before Justinian.
他是一位年长的君主，在查士 丁尼之前统治了近十年。
And both of them came from small, poor
他们俩都出身贫寒的小家庭。
agricultural communities in the western Balkans.
西巴尔干地区的 农业社区。
- We should say that Justin I ended up in your worst 10 emperors list.
我们应该说，贾斯汀一世最终进入 了你评选的十大最差皇帝名单。
- Yeah, for one decision. He's not the worst of the worst, but he,
是的，就为了一个决定。他虽然不 是罪大恶极之人，但他……
he made a very, very bad call when it came to church policy, tore the church
他在教会政策方面做出了非常非常 糟糕的决定，撕裂了教会。
apart. He shouldn't have done that,
分开。他不应该那样做。
in my view. But by the way, Justinian's an immensely complicated figure.
在我看来。但顺便一提，查士丁尼 是一个极其复杂的人物。
I found it impossible to decide, first of all, whether to put him on the best emperors or the worst
首先，我发现自己根本无法决定，究竟该把他 列入最伟大的皇帝之列，还是最差的皇帝之列。
emperors.
皇帝们。
- Yeah, you, I mean, you're being spicy. Yeah.
- 是啊，你，我的意思是，你真 够劲爆的。是的。
- Yeah, yeah. You have to be provocative about these things.
- 是啊是啊。你必须在这些 事情上采取挑衅的态度。
And I thought omitting those two would be that, and it, and it was. So,
我当时觉得省略这两个就行了， 而且确实如此。所以，
and here we are talking about it.
而我们现在正在讨论这个问题。
- Yeah, yeah, exactly. The controversy.
- 对，对，没错。争议。
- And through all the systems of social mobility that we've been
——以及我们一直以来所经历 的所有社会流动体系
talking about, Justin ended up emperor.
说起来，贾斯汀最终当上了皇帝。
because of his military background, he just rose through the ranks. He was in the right place at the right
由于他的军人背景，他一路晋升。 他当时正好在正确的地点。
time, became emperor, and then he gradually positioned his nephew,
后来，他成为了皇帝，然后 他逐渐扶植了他的侄子。
Justinian, whose background we do not know. Literally, we do not know anything that
我们对查士丁尼的背景一无所知。 实际上，我们对此一无所知。
Justinian did before the age of something like 38 when he appears on the historical record.
查士丁尼在历史记载中出现时大约 是 38 岁，那时他还没有去世。
Same background. We know where he came from, but we don't know what he was
背景相同。我们知道他来自哪里，但 我们不知道他究竟是什么人。
doing, although, like, was he an active soldier for decades? We don't know.
虽然他曾是一名服役数十年的现役军人，但 他确实在做这件事吗？我们不知道。
Probably not. He comes equipped with,
可能不会。他配备了……
like, a knowledge of something like Roman law and some Christian
例如，了解一些罗马法 和基督教方面的知识。
theology. That seems to be, like, what he knew.
神学。这似乎就 是他所知道的。
And then Justin positions him to become his
然后贾斯汀安排他 成为他的
successor eventually, kind of reluctantly, but he does.
最终他还是成为了继任者，虽然 有点不情愿，但他确实做到了。
Justinian also marries Theodora, who's a woman who's a
查士丁尼还娶了狄奥多拉 为妻，狄奥多拉是一位女性。
former sex worker, which is a controversial choice.
曾从事性工作，这是一 个颇具争议的选择。
By this point, he's a senator and is holding all of these top generalships,
到那时，他已经是参议员，并且 身兼所有这些高级将领职务。
and then he becomes emperor.
然后他就成为了皇帝。
- She was also very influential, yes?
她也很有影响力，对吗？
- Very powerful, yes.
——确实非常强大。
- Very powerful.
非常强大。
- Under his, yeah, during his reign. So the interesting thing about Justinian's
是的，在他统治期间。所以，关于 查士丁尼的有趣之处在于……
choice of, let's say, associates, and that includes his wife,
比如说，他可以选择的同事， 其中也包括他的妻子。
is that he seems to have just gone for people he, like, he thought were talented-
他似乎只是挑选了他 认为有才华的人。
... or that would be good for him as a ruler, rather than
或者说，这对他的统治来说 是件好事，而不是……
their social class or prestige. And so he accumulates
他们的社会阶层或声望。于是 他开始积累财富。
around him quite a motley group of odd, sometimes like these kinds of,
他身边聚集了一群形形色色的 怪人，有时就像这些人一样，
disreputable people. But they did what he wanted them to, and they were, they, with
声名狼藉的人。但他们照他 说的做了，他们，他们，和
lasting consequences for world history. So he has an eye for talent,
对世界历史产生深远影响 。所以他很有识人眼光。
and, and he doesn't hesitate to pick people that others might look down
而且，他毫不犹豫地选择那些 其他人可能瞧不起的人。
on if he thought they could get the job done.
他想知道他们是否 能完成这项任务。
And these are some of the attributes that enable him to be as successful as he
而这些特质也正是他取得如此 成功的原因之一。
was. So that's his background.
曾是。这就是他的背景。
He's a Latin speaker primarily, but he knows Greek, too.
他主要讲拉丁语，但 也懂希腊语。
- So here he is and he, but he had, so like I mentioned, the wars of conquests.
所以他来了，他，但是，就像我 提到的，他发动了征服战争。
He also overhauled the Roman law.
他还对罗马法律进行了全面改革。
- He appoints a committee-
他任命了一个委员会。
... As one does- ... To just take the whole of Roman law and condense it
……就像人们常做的那样——…… 把整个罗马法浓缩成……
into what today we call the Corpus Juris Civilis, which is the,
也就是我们今天所说的 《民法大全》，
the body of Roman civil law. And this was a massive work of codification,
罗马民法体系。这是一 项浩大的编纂工作，
And it is our main source for Roman
它是我们了解罗马历史的主要来源。
law. Like overwhelmingly, what we call Roman law
法律。就像我们所说的罗马法一样 ，绝大多数情况下都是如此。
is what Justinian's committee, and specifically this character called Tribonian,
这就是查士丁尼委员会，特别是 这个名叫特里博尼安的人物所关注的。
who was a very accomplished jurist said it was.
一位成就卓著的法学家 说确实如此。
- Mm-hmm. And that, did that persist through time? Did that last?
嗯。那么，这种现象是否一直持续至今 呢？那段时期持续多久了？
- Yes, still to this day. When you study Roman law, you're studying
- 是的，直到今天依然如此。学习 罗马法时，你实际上是在学习
Tribonian's committee.
论坛委员会。
- And so in terms of our modern society, how much of impact did that have,
那么，就我们现代社会而言，这 产生了多大的影响呢？
this codification, this stable law that ran the East Roman Empire?
这部法典，这部维系东罗马 帝国的稳定法律？
- Well, I mean, Roman legal concepts pervade
嗯，我的意思是，罗马法律概念无处不在。
everything from philosophy to political thought to actual Roman, uh, legal
从哲学到政治思想，再到罗马 的实际法律，无所不包。
practice. I mean, depends on what country you're in. So in many of the countries of Europe,
实践。我的意思是，这取决于你所在 的国家。所以在欧洲很多国家，
it is the,
它是，
you know, current law. And it is to some degree. I mean, I'm, I'm exaggerating.
你知道，就是现行法律。某种程度上确实 如此。我的意思是，我有点夸张了。
But legal scholars have to study Roman law. Even, even,
但法学学者必须研究 罗马法。即使，即使
law students have to do that.
法学院学生必须这样做。
Not in, so much in countries like the United States or Britain, which have the so-called
在美国或英国等拥有所谓“自由市场” 的国​​家，这种情况并不常见。
common law system. But ideas in Roman law about, for example,
普通法体系。但罗马法中 的一些观点，例如，
property, right, ownership, things like this,
财产、权利、所有权 等等。
these were hugely important in formulating ideas, for example, about sovereignty
这些对于形成诸如主权 等概念至关重要。
in political thought. Yeah, it's one of the most important and
在政治思想方面。是的，这是 最重要的事情之一，而且
influential acts of committee work ever done in Constantinople.
君士坦丁堡历史上最具 影响力的委员会工作。
- So, going to Perplexity here and looking at some aspects of the
所以，接下来我们来看一下Perplexity 网站，以及它的一些方面。
Justinian's laws, they include a systematic structure of private
查士丁尼的法律中包含一套 系统的私人法律体系。
law, persons, things, actions, strong protection of
法律、人、物、 行为、强有力的保护
property and contracts, detailed family and inheritance
财产和合同， 详细的家庭和继承
rules, and a hierarchical status-based view of
规则，以及基于层级 状态的视图
persons. These elements became the template for later civil
人。这些要素成为后来 民事的模板。
law systems. And some overall structures, tripartite schema, law
法律体系。以及一些总体 结构、三方模式、法律
organized around personae, legal subjects, things, and procedural
围绕人物、法律主体 、事物和程序组织
actions. Essentially who, what, and how of—
行动。本质上，就是 谁、什么以及如何——
...private law. And it goes on. I mean, a lot of the things I'm reading here really
...私法。而且这种情况还在继续。我的 意思是，我在这里读到的很多东西真的
sounds like what we think of as law. Marriage.
听起来就像我们通常理解 的法律。婚姻。
- Look, most of it's about property.
你看，大部分都跟房产有关。
- Marriage is a legal status. Lawful matrimony required
婚姻是一种法律地位 。需要合法婚姻
conformity to rules about age, citizenship, and
遵守有关年龄、公民身份 和……的规定
cognatum or prohibited degrees, incest rules, adoption
近亲结婚或禁忌亲属关系、 乱伦规则、收养
relations, et cetera. All that kind of stuff.
关系等等。诸如此 类的事情。
- Oh, yes. Who you can marry, who not.
- 哦是的。你可以和谁结婚，不可以和谁结婚。
- What was their view of homosexuality?
- 他们对同性恋的看法是什么？
- Well, I mean, Justinian thought it caused earthquakes.
嗯，我的意思是，查士丁尼 认为它引发了地震。
- Oh, did it?
哦，是吗？
- Yes.
- 是的。
- Did it?
真的吗？
- Wow. That's fascinating.
- 哇。真令人着迷。
- Um, no, for him no, for, for... So for Christian emperors
嗯，不，对他来说不，对，对…… 所以对基督教皇帝来说
or Christian authorities, this is a, a reprehensible immoral act.
在基督教权威人士看来，这是一 种应受谴责的不道德行为。
Um, depending, it, it could be punished.
嗯，视情况而定，它可能会受到惩罚。
Um, Justinian did try to punish it pretty brutally. I mean,
嗯，查士丁尼确实曾试图对其进行 相当残酷的惩罚。我是说，
ultimately lethally. Um, however, this gets really tricky
最终致命。嗯，不过 ，这其实挺棘手的。
here because what counts as a homosexual act is not clear to everybody, right?
因为对于不同的人来说，什么才算是同性恋 行为并不那么清楚，对吧？
And in addition to which, there... This is a society that generally will not go
除此之外，还有……这是 一个通常不会去的社会。
after, let's say,
比如说，之后
Scandals or deviance or however you wanna call it, like systematically.
丑闻、越轨行为，或者随便你怎么 称呼，反正就是有系统地发生。
This is not like some-- There's no inquisition.
这跟某些情况不一样—— 这里没有宗教裁判所。
There's no social police. If there's some sort of scandal and this comes out,
没有社会警察。如果出了 什么丑闻，这件事曝光了，
then it's a problem. But they're not actively going to track down,
那这就成了个问题。但 他们不会主动去追踪，
hunt down, monitor, survey, interrogate
追捕、监视、调查、审问
people about their sex lives. I mean, it is in a way, despite
人们谈论他们的性生活。我的意思 是，从某种意义上说，尽管如此
having views that we, we may not agree with about sexuality,
他们可能持有与我们不 认同的关于性方面的观点
uh, it was, it was, it was generally humane in the way of just kind of leaving
呃，总的来说，就这么 离开而言，还算人道。
people alone.
独处的人。
- I mean, that said, there's some... I'm just on Perplexity, looked
我的意思是，话虽如此，还是有一些…… 我只是在Perplexity上随便看看。
up Justinian Roman law view of sexuality. They're pretty harsh on, like adultery
查士丁尼罗马法对性行为的看法。他们 对婚外情之类的行为相当严厉。
and just getting freaky with it.
然后就玩得很疯。
- No, Justinian was more zealous in this matter, definitely.
不，查士丁尼在这件事 上肯定更加热衷。
- Even though he married a sex worker.
尽管他娶了一名性工作者。
- Well, sex work wasn't illegal.
- 嗯，性工作并不违法。
- Right, but it's a bit spicy.
- 对，不过有点辣。
- Yes. And in fact, it was illegal for a senator to marry
- 是的。事实上，参议员 结婚是违法的。
someone from such a disreputable profession.
出身于如此声名狼藉 的行业的人。
And he got his uncle to pass a law changing that rule- ... so that he could.
于是他让他的叔叔通过了一项法律， 改变了那条规则——……这样他就可以……
- Well. Love knows no bounds.
- 出色地。爱没有界限。
- Actually, Justinian kind of says that in one of his laws.
事实上，查士丁尼在他的某 部法律中也提到过这一点。
- Oh, wow.
哦，哇。
- No, he clearly loved her. There, there's no question.
不，他显然很爱她。 这一点毋庸置疑。
- This actual love. I mean, this, you have to like this guy. Starts as a peasant.
这是真正的爱。我的意思是，你肯定 会喜欢这个人。出身农民。
Surround himself by all kinds of weirdos just because they
他身边围绕着各种各样的 怪人，仅仅因为他们
were good at what they did, and it doesn't really matter, class or not.
他们都很擅长自己所做的事情 ，阶级与否其实并不重要。
- Yes, but there's a lot to be said against him, too. Um, I like so much.
- 是的，但也有很多不利于他 的地方。嗯，我非常喜欢。
- Let's get into it. So he did launch wars of conquest.
让我们开始吧。所以他确实 发动了征服战争。
What was his view of war and conquest, and what maybe what
他对战争和征服的看法是什么 ？他可能还有什么其他看法？
are the things we should mention in terms of expansionary wars?
我们应该从扩张战争的角度 来讨论这些事情吗？
- He thought he was authorized by God to reconquer the lost provinces of the Western
他认为自己受上帝授权，可以 重新征服西方的失落省份。
Roman Empire, and when he did so, that was proof that God favored him.
罗马帝国，而当他做到这一 点时，就证明上帝眷顾了他。
And he was generally opportunistic about it and for the most part, kind
他在这方面通常比较投机取巧 ，而且大多数时候还算和善。
of successful in that he intervened in the most
他之所以成功，是因为 他介入了最……
critical moments of the histories of these barbarian, you know, kingdoms in the
这些蛮族王国历史上的关键 时刻，你知道，在……
West, and exploited their weaknesses and took them
西方，并利用他们的弱点 ，占领了他们。
over. Now, in the process, many of these provinces were ravaged by
超过。然而，在此过程中，许多 省份都遭受了蹂躏。
war Italy for decades. He overstretched his resources, leaving his
意大利与战争持续数十年。他过度扩张 资源，导致资源短缺。
successors with a much more dangerous situation to defend.
继任者们将面临更加 危险的局面。
and he disbanded certain armies that were meant to protect Constantinople,
他还解散了某些原本用于 保卫君士坦丁堡的军队。
sent them to Italy, for example. This weakened the home front.
例如，把他们送到意大利。 这削弱了国内战线。
So he left a very difficult legacy for his successors in that way.
所以，他以这种方式给继任者留下 了一个非常棘手的难题。
Plus, some of the provinces that he conquered were so like
此外，他征服的一些 省份与……非常相似
Italy, I don't think it could even pay for itself after a certain point.
我认为，到了某个阶段，意大利 甚至可能无法实现收支平衡。
so I'm not sure that some of those decisions were the best ones. North
所以我不太确定其中一些 决定是否是最佳选择。北
Africa, yeah, probably that paid off. Italy and southern Spain, not so sure.
非洲，嗯，可能确实奏效了。意大利 和西班牙南部，不太确定。
- So that's one of the big criticisms is even though there was conquest,
所以，其中一个主要的批评 是，即使存在征服，
it was overextended, and- ... those lands were not economically stable.
它过度扩张，而且……那些 土地的经济状况并不稳定。
- Yeah, and
是的，而且
- Broke. AKA.
破产了。又名。
- Conquest is not just good, you know, in itself. I mean, this is...
征服本身不仅仅是好事，你 知道的。我的意思是，这……
I know that some rulers in history are called the Great simply because they conquered
我知道历史上有些统治者被称为“大帝”， 仅仅是因为他们征服了世界。
something. But that's, no, that's not enough. I mean, I know that rulers do this,
某物。但这还不够。我的意思 是，我知道统治者会这样做，
but if we're to compare them to each other we should at least
但如果要将它们进行比较 ，我们至少应该
expect that they have a plan or that it works out well in the end, let's
假设他们有计划，或者最终结果 会很好，那就这样吧。
say, and I don't think that many of these did.
也就是说，我认为这些 人中很少有人这么做。
- I should say that as far as historians go,
- 我应该说，就历史学家而言，
I think you don't give too many points on the conquest front.
我认为你在征服方面 得分不高。
- Personally, I? No, I don't.
就我个人而言？不，我没有。
- Yeah, so your value comes from is a leader implementing lasting
是的，所以你的价值来自于你作为 领导者所展现出的持久领导力。
change, like a stable-
改变，就像一个稳定的
- Was he good for his subjects?
他为他的臣民做了好事吗？
Were they living better because of him than otherwise?
他们因为他而过 上了更好的生活吗？
- And also, like, longer, like, the long- term nature of it, not just-
而且，更长远一点，比如，这件 事的长期性，不仅仅是——
... not just, like, a temporary thing.
……不仅仅是暂时的事情。
- Right. Are you strengthening institutions that benefit your subjects?
- 正确的。你们是否在加强 有利于民众的制度建设？
That. And some he did, some not. So look, in order to send
那。有些他做了，有些他 没做。所以你看，为了发送
those armies west to make the conquests, he stripped the
那些西征的军队， 他剥夺了……
east of armies, so the Persians could just march in and, like, destroyed
东面有敌军，所以波斯人可以直接 开进，然后摧毁他们。
Antioch. Like, that's a major strategic failure,
安提阿。那可是个 重大的战略失误。
and I don't think you get a pass for conquering North Africa by surrendering Syria.
我认为，通过割让叙利亚 来征服北非是不可的。
- He did rebuild Constantinople and reconstructed the Hagia Sophia.
他重建了君士坦丁堡，并修复 了圣索菲亚大教堂。
- Yes, after he and his soldiers set fire to it. Yes. I-
- 是的，在他和他的士兵放火烧毁 它之后。是的。我-
in the Nika insurrection. So this is when the people of the capital rise up against him,
在尼卡起义中。于是，首都 的人民起来反抗他。
and there's, like about 10 days of street fighting, and he brings in some armies,
然后，大概持续了10天的巷战 ，他还调来了一些军队。
and eventually he orders his armies to slaughter the
最终他下令 军队屠杀了
protesters, leaving more than 30,000 dead. Like, this is an
抗议者造成超过3万人死亡 。比如，这是一个
enormous number. And a lot of Constantinople
数量极其庞大。还有君士 坦丁堡的很多地方
burned in the process, and yeah, he rebuilt it. So his building is
在这个过程中被烧毁了，是的， 他又重建了它。所以他的建筑是
considered one of his great points. He built Hagia Sophia, for example, which
被认为是他的一大优点。例如 ，他建造了圣索菲亚大教堂。
is a magnificent church, like, hands
这是一座宏伟的教堂，就像……双手
down. It's just a fascinating monument to study,
向下。它真是一座值得研究 的迷人古迹。
too. And yeah, that was, that was him, too. I'm trying
也。是的，那也 是他。我想
to give you a sense here that the good and the bad are mixed in such equal measure
让你体会一下，这里好的和坏 的成分几乎是各占一半。
that, like Buridan's ass, I can't decide which- ... which bale of hay to put him on.
就像布里丹的屁股一样，我不知道 该把他放在哪一捆干草上。
- But there's a grand scale to the good and the bad.
但好事和坏事之间 是有规模的。
- Yes, yes.
- 是的，是的。
- For many people, that's what makes for a, uh-
对很多人来说，这就是 造成……的原因。
... top 10 emperor list. Uh, what about the plague?
……十大皇帝榜单 。呃，那瘟疫呢？
- Well, he wasn't responsible for that at least.
- 嗯，至少这件事不是 他的责任。
- All right.
- 好的。
- The plague of Justinian- ... AKA 541 AD. So some historians claim
- 查士丁尼瘟疫 - ...又称公元 541 年。所以一些历史学家声称
that it killed half the population and ruined the empire.
它导致一半人口 死亡，并摧毁了帝国。
You are skeptical on this view.
你对这种观点持怀疑态度。
- Yes. So this is a bubonic plague.
- 是的。所以这是鼠疫。
Um, which lasts more or less for two centuries. It
嗯，这大概持续 了两个世纪。它
comes and it goes, and it's kind of endemic to large parts of the
它时而出现，时而消失，而且这在很 大一部分地区都是普遍存在的现象。
world. 541 is when it starts to break out in
世界。 541 是它开始 爆发的时候
the empire, in Constantinople and other cities, and it spreads.
帝国在君士坦丁堡和其他城市 建立，并不断扩张。
There's been a lot of debate about this recently because now we've
最近关于这个问题有很多 争论，因为现在我们有
actually isolated the pathogen. It's Yersinia pestis. Like, we know this.
实际上已经分离出了病原体。这是鼠疫 耶尔森菌。比如，我们都知道这一点。
Just as of, like, a generation ago, this was just guesswork.
就像上一代人一样， 这完全是猜测。
But now there's all of this new, like, laboratory science work that's come in to
但现在涌现出了很多新的、比如 实验室科学方面的工作。
fill in some of the gaps in history.
填补历史上的一些空白。
- That's so cool.
太酷了。
- It is. It is. There are lots of discussions about that. And
- 这是。这是。关于这个 问题有很多讨论。和
so the study of diseases and virology have just become much more important lately.
因此，疾病和病毒学的研究 近来变得更加重要了。
It still doesn't tell you, however, like mortality rates and historical
但它仍然无法告诉你死亡率 和历史数据等信息。
impact. Like, for that, you still need standard old-fashioned
影响。比如，为此，你仍然需要 传统的标准方法。
non-laboratory historical work.
非实验室历史研究。
And there's a debate about the impact of this plague. It's ongoing, I should say that.
关于这场瘟疫的影响，目前存在争议 。应该说，这件事还在进行中。
And some scholars argue for a kind of maximalist position
一些学者主张采取一 种极端主义立场。
of 50%. I think that would have brought this society to a halt.
50%。我认为那会使这个 社会陷入停滞。
Just logistically speaking. And so I believe in a much more moderate impact.
仅从后勤角度来说。所以我认为 应该采取更为温和的影响方式。
- And the real impact is what? The tax base shrinks?
真正的实际影响是 什么？税基缩小了？
- Oh. Oh, yeah. The tax base would shrink instantly.
- 哦。哦，是的。税基 将立即缩小。
You wouldn't be able to recruit armies. You know, there would be massive social
你将无法招募军队。你知道，那 将会是一场大规模的社会运动。
dislocation. Like what happens in the, in the Black
错位。就像在黑色 世界里发生的事情一样
Death in Europe in the 14th century. Like, we have very good records
14世纪欧洲的死亡情况。比如， 我们有非常好的记录。
for what happened to those societies, and basically everything that they were doing stopped for a few
对于那些社会所发生的一切，基本上他们 所做的一切都停止了一段时间。
years until they sort of tried to put things back together again. This
多年以后，他们才试图把 一切重新拼凑起来。这
does not happen in the 6th century.
六世纪并没有发生这样的事。
In fact, Justinian is at that time waging war on something like
事实上，查士丁尼当时正在 对类似这样的事物发动战争。
four or five different fronts.
四五个不同的战线。
If you read the narratives of those wars, there's no pause. There's
如果你阅读那些战争的叙述，你会 发现其中没有任何停顿。有
no, there's no impact from the plague on the
不，瘟疫对…… 没有影响。
conduct of those wars. They just continue on.
这些战争的进行方式 。他们继续前行。
Taxation continues. The courts continue. Like, you just don't see it in
税收仍在继续。庭审仍在继续。 比如，你根本看不到它
the narrative, and so I think that there's a much less
叙事方式，所以我认为存在 一个较少的问题。
impact than, certainly than 50%, yeah.
影响肯定超过 50%，是的。
- So this sets the stage for a tumultuous 7th century.
这就为动荡不安的七世纪 埋下了伏笔。
- Yeah, you could call it that. Yes.
- 是的，你可以这么称呼它。是的。
- So what is the legacy of Justinian, in terms of how he left the empire
那么，就他留给帝国的遗产而言， 查士丁尼究竟留下了什么？
leading into the 7th century?
进入7世纪？
- Well, he left it overextended, so his successors
- 嗯，他把公司过度扩张了，所以 他的继任者们
had to deal with many more problems along many more fronts,
不得不处理更多 方面更多的问题，
With fewer military forces concentrated in what we might call the
由于较少的军事力量 集中在我们所谓的……
homeland of the Eastern Roman Empire.
东罗马帝国的故乡。
And so that made the, the center vulnerable too, and so you start
因此，这也使得中心变得 脆弱，于是你开始……
to get raids into the Balkans and, you know, it enters a kind of vicious cycle
发动对巴尔干地区的袭击，你知道 ，这就陷入了一种恶性循环。
again.
再次。
now, not all of this was Justinian's fault. I mean, the plague definitely had some
当然，这一切并非全是查士丁尼的错。我 的意思是，瘟疫肯定有一些影响。
impact. But I wouldn't blame everything on his
影响。但我不会把所有 责任都推到他身上。
successors, as is sometimes done, like they mishandled the situation.
继任者有时会被 指责处理不当。
He... Yeah, he left them a very difficult situation to deal with.
他……是啊，他给他们留下 了一个非常棘手的局面。
- So speaking of which, let's talk about Heraclius.
- 说到这个，我们来谈谈 赫拉克略吧。
He didn't make, he didn't make your list either, which is a shocker
他没入选，你的名单上也没有 他，这真是令人震惊。
for a lot of people. Perhaps you can describe the nuance of that, but
对很多人来说。或许您可以描述 一下其中的细微差别，但是
he took over the Roman Empire on the verge of
他接管罗马帝国 时，正值……
extinction. Persians at the gates, treasury empty. So maybe first tell the
灭绝。波斯人兵临城下，国库 空空。所以或许首先要告诉
full saga of the Roman-Persian War that threatened the empire's existence.
完整讲述了威胁罗马帝国存亡 的罗马-波斯战争的史实。
- Sure. Well, he wasn't entirely, you know,
- 当然。嗯，他并不完全是，你知道的，
free of blame for the situation that he inherited.
他无需为继承 的局面承担责任。
He was in part responsible for it. So he doesn't get a pass on that.
他对此负有部分责任。所以他在 这件事上也不能逃脱惩罚。
So Heraclius is basically a rebel and a usurper. So
所以希拉克略基本上就是一 个叛乱者和篡位者。所以
for various reasons Rome and Persia are at war starting around 602.
由于各种原因，罗马和波斯从 公元602年左右开始交战。
and the, the Persian shah at this time, Khosrow II,
而当时的波斯沙阿 ，霍斯劳二世，
has basically decided on a policy of conquest,
基本上已经决定采取 征服政策，
not just raiding. Like, I'm gonna go in and take your people,
不仅仅是掠夺。比如，我要进去 把你们的人都带走。
some cattle, and some statues, and take them to, you know, Mesopotamia.
带上一些牛和一些雕像，然后 把它们运到美索不达米亚去。
He starts what... I mean, I think there's some evolution in his thinking and his
他开始做什么……我的意思是，我认为 他的思想和行为方式有所演变。
planning about this, but pretty soon during the
正在计划这件事，但 很快在……期间
600 and the aughts, he realizes that there's
到了600年代和2000年代 ，他意识到……
potential for actual permanent territorial gain here, and his armies start moving
这里有可能获得永久性的领土扩张 ，他的军队开始进军。
in. And the Roman Emperor is this guy called Phocas, who is himself a usurper,
而罗马皇帝名叫福卡斯， 他本人就是一个篡位者。
a military background, and he now faces a rebellion
他有军人背景，现在 却面临着叛乱。
by Heraclius, who, whose base is in North Africa at this time, like around Carthage.
希拉克略，当时他的基地在 北非，比如迦太基附近。
And they have a civil war for three years, 608 to 610.
他们之间爆发了三年的内战 ，从公元608年到610年。
That civil war that Heraclius initiates
希拉克略发动的那场内战
causes a diversion of Roman armies to the civil war away
这导致罗马军队被 分流到内战中。
from the Persian front. So it's a massive gift to the Persians.
来自波斯前线。所以这对波斯人 来说是一份巨大的礼物。
Plus, a lot of the fighting takes place in Egypt, and Egypt was a
此外，很多战斗都发生在埃及 ，而埃及当时是一个……
province that had up until that point not really been harmed by war. Now it is,
在此之前，该省份并未真正遭受 战争的蹂躏。现在是了。
right? So Heraclius's forces, he's not in Egypt, but his backers,
正确的？所以希拉克略的军队，他本人不 在埃及，而是在他的支持者那里。
are fighting a civil war in Egypt, so that province is
埃及正处于内战之中 ，所以那个省份是
now, you know, ravaged in part. The
现在，你知道，部分地区遭到了破坏。这
Persians make tremendous gains in the east. Heraclius heads straight for
波斯人在东方取得了巨大的 胜利。赫拉克略径直走向
Constantinople during all of this, and to make a long story short, he manages
在此期间，他一直待在君士坦丁堡 ，长话短说，他最终成功了。
to take Constantinople, execute Phocas, and become emperor,
攻占君士坦丁堡，处死福卡斯 ，成为皇帝。
right? But now he's facing a problem that's much worse than it was
正确的？但现在他面临的问题 比以前严重得多。
when, before he started the rebellion. The reason why Heraclius is sort of
在他发动叛乱之前。赫拉克 略之所以有点……
lionized in some... Well, actually, there's a very long tradition of doing
在某些方面被奉为英雄……嗯，实际上 ，这样做有着非常悠久的传统。
this, which goes back to the Middle Ages. In the Western Middle Ages, Heraclius was sometimes
这可以追溯到中世纪。在西方 中世纪，希拉克略有时
considered, like, the first crusader.
被视为，就像第一次十字军东征一样。
- Oh, interesting.
哦，有意思。
- Yeah, yeah. So there's all this medieval literature about Heraclius as being a
- 是啊是啊。所以有很多关于希拉克略的 中世纪文献，把他描述成一个……
a proto-crusader type and all that,
一种类似十字军东征的先驱者之类的角色，
For reconquering, like, Jerusalem from the Persians and
例如，从波斯人 手中夺回耶路撒冷和
restoring the True Cross and all that. So he had this kind of
修复真十字架等等。所以 他有这种……
aura, and I think his modern
他的气场，我认为他现代的
admirers are basically just continuing... I mean, they might not know it,
仰慕者们基本上只是在继续……我的意思是， 他们可能自己都没意识到这一点。
but they're kind of continuing this very, very long tradition of treating Heraclius as
但他们某种程度上延续了将赫拉克 略视为……的悠久传统。
this heroic holy warrior. Anyway, from my standpoint,
这位英勇的圣战士。总之 ，从我的角度来看，
it's a complete wash. In other words, yes, he
完全扯平了。换句 话说，是的，他
does beat the Persians and he gets, like,
击败波斯人后，他得到了，比如，
in my view, full credit for that, though he did it with, I think, the
在我看来，他应该为此获得完全 的赞誉，尽管我认为他是用……
help of some Turkish allies from Central Asia. These were, I think,
得到了来自中亚的一些土耳其盟友 的帮助。我认为，这些是……
the major component of his success at the very end. But no,
这是他最终取得成功 的关键因素。不，
no. So he held the Persians off and ultimately defeated them, yes.
不。所以他抵挡住了波斯人的 进攻，最终击败了他们，是的。
And then he loses everything to the Arabs.
然后他把一切都输给了阿拉伯人。
- So the Arab conquests are 630s and 640s, but the Persian War is 602 to 628.
- 因此，阿拉伯人的征服发生在公元630年代和640年代 ，而波斯战争发生在公元602年至628年。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- So what can be said about this what seems to be a pretty costly war, I guess
那么，对于这场似乎代价相当惨重 的战争，我们还能说什么呢？
Persians
波斯人
- So the war was costly initially only for the Romans.
所以，战争初期只有罗马人 付出了惨重的代价。
the eastern provinces were conquered by Persia. That means Syria,
东部各省被波斯征服。也就 是说，叙利亚。
Palestine, Egypt. So that's a loss.
巴勒斯坦，埃及。所以这是一笔损失。
You lose all that revenue, and then they start raiding into Asia Minor.
你失去了所有收入，然后他们 就开始劫掠小亚细亚。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- By the way, this is exactly what the Arabs would do, you know, just a couple decades
顺便说一句，这正是阿拉伯人 几十年前会做的事。
later. They would conquer Syria, Palestine, Egypt, and they would start raiding into Asia Minor.
之后。他们将征服叙利亚、巴勒斯坦 、埃及，并开始入侵小亚细亚。
So almost like this phase of East Roman history begins
所以，东罗马历史的这一 阶段几乎就此开始。
already during the Persian invasion. It's just a kind of a prelude. It was, in
早在波斯入侵时期就已如此。 这只是个序曲。那是，在
fact, the Arabs that would do that for the next few centuries.
事实上，阿拉伯人在接下来 的几个世纪里都这么做了。
So Heraclius, it takes him a very long time to get organized,
所以赫拉克利乌斯需要很长 时间才能把一切安排妥当。
In fact, something like 15 years, and it's not
事实上，大概有15年了 ，而且并非如此。
entirely clear, like, what he's doing all this time. Um,
完全清楚，他这段时间 都在做什么。嗯，
but he ultimately manages to defeat the Persians by waging these really
但他最终通过发动这些真正 的战争击败了波斯人。
spectacular, weird campaigns in the East. He
东方的奇特而 精彩的战役。他
decides to strike into the Persian heartland,
决定进攻波斯 腹地，
as it were. Well, first in the Caucasus region, and then he goes into
就好像是这样。首先是高加索 地区，然后他去了……
Mesopotamia. So not to try to defeat their armies that
美索不达米亚。所以不要 试图击败他们的军队。
are rampaging around Asia Minor or even besieging his capital
他们正在小亚细亚肆虐， 甚至围攻他的首都。
in 626. The Persians and the Avars, this people from... This
公元626年。波斯人和阿瓦尔人 ，这个来自……的民族
nomadic warrior group that settled in roughly modern
定居在大致现代的 游牧武士群体
Hungary, they're besieging Constantinople. Heraclius doesn't even go.
匈牙利正在围攻君士坦丁堡。赫拉克 略甚至都没去。
And he's just kind of preparing his armies in the East, and he strikes the
他正在东方集结军队 ，然后发动进攻。
Persians right where it hurts, and this now begins to
波斯人正中要害， 而现在这一切开始……
degrade the Persian heartland and their infrastructure
破坏波斯核心地带 及其基础设施
because remember, both of these empires are going to be in shambles by the time the Arabs come
因为记住，到阿拉伯人到来时， 这两个帝国都将分崩离析。
along, and this is what enables the Arabs to conquer them so quickly. I mean, they've
正是这一点，使得阿拉伯人能够如此迅速 地征服他们。我的意思是，他们已经
destroyed each other
互相摧毁
in these wars. And eventually Heraclius calls in his Turkish allies, and they
在这些战争中。最终，希拉克略 召集了他的土耳其盟友，他们
go on a field trip through Mesopotamia, and
去美索不达米亚 进行实地考察，
this causes a coup in, in Persia, and Khosrow is killed.
这导致波斯发生政变 ，霍斯劳被杀。
- Is there something to be said, a little bit of texture to the
- 有什么需要说明的 吗？一点点质感？
motivations of the different empires and the different groups involved? So the
不同帝国和不同派系的 动机是什么？所以
East Roman Empire, the Persian Empire, and the Islamic
东罗马帝国、波斯帝国 和伊斯兰帝国
Caliphates, were they after conquering? Were they
哈里发政权追求的是征服 吗？他们是吗？
after expansion? Were they after more like raiding
扩张之后呢？他们追求 的更像是掠夺。
for financial benefits? What was the motivation?
为了经济利益？ 动机是什么？
- So in the past, the Persian Shahs basically were interested in raiding, and
所以，过去波斯沙阿们 主要热衷于劫掠，
they also had an interest in manpower. So all of those Mesopotamian
他们对人力资源也很有兴趣。所以 所有这些美索不达米亚人
agricultural estates won't till themselves. So they were kind of
农业庄园不会自己耕种 。所以他们有点……
insatiable for agricultural workforces and specialized craftsmen and people like that.
对农业劳动力、专业工匠以及 类似人员的需求永无止境。
so they would go into the empire and get them.
所以他们会进入帝国 境内去抓他们。
But in this phase, it seems that Khosrow
但在这个阶段，霍斯罗似乎……
II is taking really to heart the idea that the Persian
II 非常认真地把波斯人 的想法放在心上
Empire should really extend to the Mediterranean
帝国的版图应该真正扩展 到地中海地区。
as it did in, like, Achaemenid times, right, in, in ancient history, the empire
就像在阿契美尼德王朝时期那样 ，对吧，在古代历史上，帝国
that Alexander conquered. So it seems that the, the Sassanians,
亚历山大征服的那片土地 。所以看来，萨珊王朝
this is this dynasty, this Iranian dynasty that's ruling the Persian
这就是这个王朝，这个统治 波斯的伊朗王朝。
Empire, of course, they were aware of the Achaemenids, but sometimes they
帝国当然知道阿契美尼德 王朝，但有时他们
would have these claims to reviving the former greatness of the Iranian Empire.
他们会声称要复兴伊朗 帝国的昔日辉煌。
So, you know, bathing in the Mediterranean Sea is something
所以，你知道，在地中海 游泳是一件很惬意的事。
that many Near Eastern monarchs, you know,
你知道，很多近东君主都是如此。
they did this as a sign of success. Anyway, for the Romans, it was sheer survival,
他们这样做是为了庆祝成功。总之，对 罗马人来说，生存才是最重要的。
Just desperate survival 'cause they knew that this was a war
他们只是为了求生而拼死挣扎， 因为他们知道这是一场战争。
that could end the Roman state.
那可能会导致罗马帝国的灭亡。
- I mean, they're already on the verge of being ended.
我的意思是，它们已经 濒临终结了。
And here, their defensive wars of survival.
在这里，他们为了生存而进行 的防御性战争。
- Yeah. So it's pretty clear that initially the goal of Arab Muslim warfare is to
- 是的。因此，很明显，阿拉伯穆斯林 战争的最初目标是……
unify Arabia. That is, that all Arabs should be
统一阿拉伯。也就是说， 所有阿拉伯人都应该是
Muslim and should be unified into this religious kind of state, whatever, that
穆斯林应该统一到一个宗教国家 ，无论如何，就是这样。
the prophet and his successors had created. Now, then they start striking out,
先知及其后继者所创造的。然后 他们就开始屡屡失手，
Into Rome and into Iran. It's not entirely clear, like, why. Now,
进入罗马，进入伊朗。原因 尚不完全清楚。现在，
there are obvious reasons. Like, I mean, we don't-- It's not, like, a
原因显而易见。我的意思是， 我们不——这不是，像……
huge historical mystery why a, you know, recently
一个巨大的历史谜团， 为什么，你知道，最近
formed successful army will decide to take on two very weak opponents-
组建了一支实力强劲的军队，决定 迎战两个非常弱小的对手。
... who are on their doorstep. Like- ... this is not, you know, complicated.
……就在他们家门口。 比如……这并不复杂。
- Yeah, they're pretty effective at military- ... conquest.
- 是的，他们在军事征服 方面相当有效。
- Yeah. But they're striking both empires from a direction that those
- 是的。但他们攻击这两个帝国的方向 ，与那些人所采取的方向截然不同。
empires had never prepared to defend from. Arabia was just
帝国从未做好过防御 准备。阿拉伯半岛
not, "Oh, you might get some occasional raiders, but you're never gonna get an
不是，“哦，你可能会偶尔遇到一些 袭击者，但你永远不会遇到……”
army that's coming out that can potentially conquer you." So
一支即将出动、有可能 征服你们的军队。”
the defensive orientations are all wrong.
防守方的策略完全错误。
And these two empires have gone through this massive war,
这两个帝国经历了 这场大规模战争，
that has destabilized them. They're, they're low on manpower, low on
这导致他们的局势不稳定。他们 人手不足，资源匮乏。
resources. The outcome is almost kind of inevitable. I don't think there's a
资源。结果几乎是不可 避免的。我不认为有
great mystery.
巨大的谜团。
- And the effect of that is they stripped away the richest provinces
其结果是，他们剥夺 了最富裕的省份。
of the Roman Empire.
罗马帝国。
- Yes, Egypt in particular.
是的，特别是埃及。
That's, that means now you can't feed Constantinople. Like we talked about the grain from Egypt,
也就是说，现在你们没法养活君士坦丁堡了。就 像我们之前谈到的埃及粮食一样，
right, that came to Constantinople. You don't have that now.
没错，那东西传到了君士坦丁堡 。你现在没有那个。
And so that means that the population of Constantinople will decline
因此，这意味着君士坦丁堡 的人口将会减少。
dramatically over the next few decades.
接下来的几十年里，情况将发生巨大变化。
- So how, how does the empire rebuild itself,
那么，这个帝国该 如何重建自身呢？
you know, restabilize? Because it's not, it doesn't collapse there, right?
你知道，重新稳定下来？因为事实并非 如此，它不会在那里坍塌，对吧？
- Yes.
- 是的。
- It stays, it survives. There's interesting low
它留了下来，它存活了 下来。有有趣的低
points for the empire where it still survives.
对于这个帝国仍然存在的地方 来说，这是值得称道的一点。
- This is one of them.
这是其中之一。
- And that is as interesting as the survival at the top,
——而这和如何在顶峰 生存一样有趣。
and the flourishing survival at the bottom is also super
而底层人民的蓬勃发展 也令人惊叹。
interesting. So how do-- What happens? How does it kinda stabilize?
有趣的。那么该怎么做——会 发生什么？它是如何稳定下来的？
- Very slowly. This is a painful process, and it takes them centuries, you could say.
非常慢。这是一个痛苦的过程，可以 说需要几个世纪的时间。
First you gotta stop the bleeding, just try to hold the line.
首先你得止住血，努力 守住血流线。
It takes them decades to just to hold a line. Like, they get
他们花了数十年时间才守住一 条防线。比如，他们会得到
pummeled by the Arabs for decades in the seventh century until finally by, 6-
在七世纪，阿拉伯人对这个国家进行 了数十年的蹂躏，直到最后，6-
660s, 670, they finally begin to beat them.
660分、670分，他们终于 开始战胜他们了。
Beat them on land and hold the line, on the sea.
在陆地上击败他们，在 海上守住防线。
And so we now have an investment in fleets.
因此，我们现在对 车队进行了投资。
Eventually, you get the Greek fire, which is the flamethrowers.
最终，你会得到希腊火 ，也就是火焰喷射器。
And when the Arabs try to take Constantinople, these
当阿拉伯人试图攻占 君士坦丁堡时，这些
attempts are defeated, like, twice, and that
尝试失败了，比如 两次，而且
ensures the survival of this, of the Roman state in some form.
这确保了罗马国家以某 种形式延续下去。
- How were the flamethrowers used?
火焰喷射器是如何使用的？
- Ah, yes. This is an interesting question. We're still kind of debating that.
- 啊，是的。这是一个有趣的问题。 我们还在讨论这个问题。
- Oh, it's not fully understood.
- 哦，这个问题还没有完全解决。
- Well, it's a state secret.
- 这是国家机密。
They didn't want this getting out, so they kept it pretty well. The fact
他们不想让这件事泄露出去， 所以保守得很严实。事实
that we're debating it will tell you that they were pretty good at keeping secrets.
我们正在讨论这件事，这说明 他们很擅长保守秘密。
So possibly through a pressure valve. Right? So you have this flammable compound
所以可能是通过压力阀。正确的 ？所以你这里有一种易燃化合物
whose preparation and components is also a state secret.
其制备方法和成分也 是国家机密。
So there's specialized-- There's a corps of engineers that prepares this and
所以有专门的——有一支工程 兵团负责准备这些，
deploys it.
部署它。
Um, and it's possibly through a heated pressurized container with a spigot,
嗯，也可能是通过一个带龙头 的加热加压容器来实现的。
let's say, that unleashes this thing through a nozzle, and it's lit and
假设它通过喷嘴喷出这东西 ，而且它还点燃了。
basically spews flaming napalm
基本上就是喷出燃烧的凝固汽油弹
on other ships, and it will continue to burn even when it's on the water.
在其他船只上，即使船只在 水上，它也会继续燃烧。
Right? On the top. So, like, you can't, like, swim away or anything. So it's
正确的？在最上面。所以，你 没办法游走什么的。所以是
this very, very destructive weapon. Terrifying. They used it
这种威力极其巨大的武器 。太可怕了。他们用了它
against Vikings too. This is much later. So once the Vikings show up-
对阵维京人时也是如此。这是很久以后 的事了。所以一旦维京人出现——
... Like, when they would raid attacked
比如，当他们发动袭击的时候
Constantinople in the 940s, then again in the 1040s-
君士坦丁堡在940年代，然后 在1040年代再次——
... Yeah, the Romans used Greek fire fleets to just incinerate the...
……是啊，罗马人利用希腊的火舰队 把……烧成了灰烬。
And that'll teach Vikings.
这下维京人该长记性了。
Yes. If you're in that situation, you'd rather serve under
是的。如果你身处那种境地，你 宁愿在……之下服役
the emperors than attack them.
然后皇帝们就攻击他们。
- And so this is a kind of nuclear weapon level state secret.
所以，这属于核武器级别 的国家机密。
- They even had it in hand grenade form.
他们甚至还研制出了手榴弹形式的这种武器。
- This is a real thing?
这是真的吗？
- Oh, yes.
- 哦是的。
- Hand grenade form.
- 手榴弹形态。
- Yes. So it's a, it's like a clay container,
- 是的。所以它就像 一个陶土容器，
with the compound, and it has, like, some sort of
这种化合物具有 某种性质
fuse that you light on the outside and you throw it. Now,
点燃外面的保险丝 ，然后扔掉。现在，
you throw it... You can throw it against people, but it's not gonna be that effective.
你把它扔出去……你可以把它 扔向别人，但效果不会太好。
Maybe you burn a person, whatever. You just wasted a hand grenade for, you know, one
也许你会烧伤一个人，诸如此类。你刚才浪费了一 枚手榴弹，你知道，就为了这么一个目标。
person. It's most effective against things like, uh, siege engines.
人。它对付攻城器械之类 的东西最有效。
Uh, so you, you throw that on a wooden frame and, you know, yeah.
呃，所以你就把它放在木框 上，然后，你知道，是的。
- This is incredible. So this is one of the things that's finally stabilized,
这太不可思议了。所以这是最终 稳定下来的事情之一。
Stopped the bleeding from a military perspective.
从军事角度来看 ，止住了血。
- Yeah, eventually. Now, now remember, they've pulled the armies back into Asia Minor,
- 是的，最终会的。现在，记住，他们 已经把军队撤回小亚细亚了。
so they're, they're beginning to defend and fortify Asia
所以他们开始保卫和 加强亚洲的防御。
Minor. Now you have to find ways to pay and support and feed all of these soldiers, and
次要的。现在你必须想办法支付、 供养和照顾所有这些士兵，而且
this is a whole administrative- it's a wrenching
这完全是行政上的——这令 人痛心疾首
administrative readjustment. But they go through it. It takes them a long time.
行政调整。但他们最终都经历了 这一切。这需要很长时间。
Eventually, they emerge with a different kind of strategic logistical system.
最终，他们发展出了一种不同 的战略物流体系。
- Just a smaller, harder- ... core- ... of the empire.
——只是帝国的一个更小、更强大 的……核心……而已。
- That's right. Very militarized.
- 这是正确的。高度军事化。
- Very militarized. And then in the eighth century, the, the second Arab siege
高度军事化。然后到了八世纪，发生 了第二次阿拉伯围攻。
of Constantinople, that somehow fails.
君士坦丁堡，但不知何故失败了。
- In the early eighth century, yes, that was the second siege.
- 是的，那是八世纪 初的第二次围攻。
- Yeah, the early eighth century. So why, why did it fail? Can you
- 是的，八世纪初。那么，为什么 会失败呢？你可以吗
tell the story of that siege? That was really the empire hanging by, by a thread.
讲讲那场围攻的故事？那真 是帝国岌岌可危的时刻了。
- Yes, but it happened to have a very competent man in charge. This is,
- 是的，但恰好由一位非常 能干的人负责。这是，
uh, Leo III, and he's an emperor who has- he's a usurper. He's just
呃，利奥三世，他是一位篡位 者，是一位皇帝。他只是
seized power. They knew that this massive Arab attack was
夺取政权。他们知道这次 大规模的阿拉伯袭击是
coming, and so it's quite possible that the Roman
即将到来，因此罗马人 很有可能
elites, you know, preferred to put someone
你知道，精英们更喜欢安插自己人。
capable in, in power at that moment. The city was very well prepared.
当时有能力，在位。这座城市 准备得非常充分。
I encourage people in the audience to, to go and read the, the sources that we have for that.
我鼓励在场的各位去阅读 我们掌握的相关资料。
You, you can find many accounts of it online. It, it was just very, very
你可以在网上找到很多相关的描述 。它，它就是非常，非常
well done. He also had Bulgar allies.
做得好。他还有保加尔盟友。
So these are the, the Bulgars who had just, you know, crossed the Danube just, like, just
所以这些就是刚刚渡过多瑙河的保加尔人 ，你知道，他们就刚刚……
a few years earlier actually and settled south of the Danube, you
实际上，几年前你就定居 在了多瑙河南岸。
know, where eventually, you know, Bulgaria emerged. So he had Bulgar allies,
你知道，最终，保加利亚就是从那里诞生 的。所以他有保加尔盟友，
and he used the, the Greek fire very, very strategically. He used his
他非常巧妙地运用了希腊火 。他利用了他的
own fleet. He contained the Arabs to certain places where they kind of
自有舰队。他将阿拉伯人限制在 某些地方，在那里他们……
starved and wore them down. Yeah, it's just very well done.
饿死他们，耗尽他们的体力 。是的，做得非常好。
- From a military perspective.
- 从军事角度来看。
- Well, was there, was it the, the walls, the navy, the weather, the
嗯，那里有吗？是那些城墙 、海军、天气吗？
diplomacy, just good luck that helped Constantinople hold?
是外交手段，还是仅仅是运气， 才让君士坦丁堡得以守住？
- I don't see much role for good luck there. I mean, I think he had it all pretty planned out.
- 我觉得运气在这里起不了多大作用。 我的意思是，我觉得他早就计划好了。
It was all of the elements that you mentioned. And yeah, he, he just deployed them very,
正是你提到的那些因素。是的，他， 他只是非常迅速地部署了他们，
very astutely and went on to rule
他非常精明，并最终统治了国家。
after that for another 20-some years, and his son continued. Um,
此后又持续了二十多年，他的 儿子也继承了他的事业。嗯，
they, they formed a dynasty. It was-- We call it the Isaurian dynasty, though they were not from
他们建立了一个王朝。它——我们称之为 伊苏里亚王朝，尽管他们并非来自……
Isauria.
伊苏里亚。
- And then from that, the fascinating thing that we mentioned about religion,
然后，由此引出了我们之前提到 的关于宗教的迷人之处，
there was a whole stretch of time marked by intense
有一段很长的时间， 充满了强烈的……
internal religious conflicts over iconoclasm.
因破坏圣像而引发 的内部宗教冲突。
Maybe you can clarify this, but so iconoclasm, of course, is whether
或许你可以解释一下，但当然， 破坏偶像运动究竟是什么？
sacred images, icons, should be venerated or destroyed.
神圣的图像、圣像应该受到 尊崇，或者被摧毁。
This had major political and theological stakes. The
这具有重大的政治 和神学意义。这
seemingly smallest things can have the biggest of conflicts.
看似微不足道的小事，也 可能引发最大的冲突。
- Yeah. You've been in an Orthodox church.
- 是的。你去过东正教堂。
Have you seen all the icons and the just painting everywhere?
你有没有看到到处都是 的圣像和绘画作品？
Every space that you can imagine is covered in either icons or
你能想象到的每个空间都 布满了图标或符号。
images or iconography of saints. All right. That's a result of this.
圣徒的图像或圣像画。好 的。这是由此造成的结果。
No, that's not what Christian churches used to be like, at least not in Constantinople.
不，基督教教堂以前不是这样 的，至少在君士坦丁堡不是。
But his dynasty basically tried to limit,
但他的王朝基本上试图限制……
Or remove images from churches, and ultimately that
或者从教堂移除图像 ，最终达到目的。
policy failed. And the other side that
政策失败。而另一方面……
wanted images or liked images, or let me put it differently, thought that images
想要的图片，或者喜欢的图片， 或者换句话说，认为的图片
were not only appropriate but helpful in the context of Christian
在基督教的背景下，这些说法 不仅恰当，而且很有帮助。
worship prevailed. And so gradually the churches began
崇拜盛行。于是， 教会逐渐兴起。
to fill up with icons, lots of icons. They're almost like, you know, like a
填满图标，大量的图标。它们 几乎就像，你知道，就像……
catchword for Orthodox, you know, devotion. Um,
东正教的口号，你知道 的，虔诚。嗯，
I have icons at home. You have a little corner in the house and you have little iconography.
我家里有图标。你在家里有个小角落 ，摆放着一些小小的装饰品。
Um, anyway, I mean, as a secular Orthodox person, but I... even I can't get away
嗯，总之，我的意思是，作为一个世俗的东正教徒 ，但是……即使是我也无法摆脱这种境地。
from them.
来自他们。
- But that has serious consequences. I mean, that was-
但这会造成严重的后果 。我的意思是，那真是——
... serious. It was an extremely serious internal religious conflict.
... 严肃的。这是一场极其 严重的内部宗教冲突。
- Well, okay, so one asterisk on that. In my research, I did not find a
- 好吧，这里要补充一点。在我 的研究中，我没有发现
popular interest in this matter. Like-
公众对此事非常关注。喜欢-
- Oh, interesting
哦，有意思。
- ... yeah, I don't-
——是啊，我不——
- So this is an overblown-
所以这是被夸大的
- Yes. Yes, socially completely overblown.
- 是的。是的，社会层面完全被夸大了。
- Oh, this is one of those things where religious folks will write the
哦，这是宗教人士会 写的那种事情之一。
story of history.
历史的故事。
- That's it. Got it.
- 就是这样。知道了。
- Ah.
啊。
- You got it.
答对了。
I could not find... There were, like, a few emperors, and there's some bishops
我找不到……好像有几个 皇帝，还有一些主教。
and abbots and monks. Like, I don't know, maybe 100, 200
还有修道院院长和僧侣。比如说 ，我不知道，大概100，200吧。
people are, like, seriously invested in this, and they're going at it.
大家都很认真地投入其中 ，并且全力以赴。
But these are the people who write the texts.
但这些人正是文本 的撰写者。
But they never mention, for example, that, oh, you know, the people of
但他们从未提及，例如， 哦，你知道，那些人
Constantinople, they rose up, and they demanded icons or not icons or
君士坦丁堡，他们起义了，他们要求 要么有圣像，要么没有圣像。
anything like that.
诸如此类的事情。
Nah, never. So in my view, this is one of those controversies that's
不，绝不。所以在我看来， 这是那种……争议之一。
only a few people really, really cared-
只有极少数人真正关心这件事。
... about it, and unfortunately, they're the ones who wrote the sources.
……关于这件事，不幸的是 ，他们正是撰写这些资料的人。
- So you always have to,
所以你总是必须这样做，
Be very careful to consider the sources when you're reading about
阅读相关内容时，务必 仔细核查信息来源。
anything involving religious events.
任何与宗教活动有关的事情。
- Or any kind of events.
或者任何类型的活动。
- But certain things are more intensely, People are more intensely passionate about-
但有些事物，人们对它们 的热情更加强烈——
... and therefore they're going, that bias is going to-
……因此，他们会认为 这种偏见将会——
- Yeah, yeah
- 是啊是啊
- ... bleed into the way you report the history.
——……影响你叙述 历史的方式。
- Yeah. And not only that, when emperors changed their policy,
- 是的。不仅如此，当 皇帝改变政策时，
almost everyone fell into line. They switched positions.
几乎所有人都服从了 。他们交换了位置。
It's like, "No, yeah, whatever. Put the images, take the images," like, whatever.
就好像，“不，好吧，随便吧。 放图片，拍图片吧，”之类的。
I mean, like this isn't, they did not see this as central. Some people did,
我的意思是，好像这件事不是重点似的，他们并没有 把这件事看得那么重要。有些人确实这么做了。
and they got very worked up about it.
他们对此非常激动。
Anyway, but in the end, the pro-icon position won,
总之，最终，支持偶像 的立场还是占了上风。
and their view just began to fill up the space.
他们的视野开始逐渐 填满整个空间。
Like, like it literally was filling up the churches, and it still does.
就像教堂里真的挤满了 人，现在依然如此。
- The thing is, we somehow took on the impossible task of talking about a thousand-
问题是，我们不知何故承担了谈论 一千件事的不可能完成的任务——
- It'll defeat you, man. It'll defeat you every time.
它会打败你的，伙计。它每 次都会让你失败。
- I mean, there's a reason why you really wanna do a thousand-hour
我的意思是，你之所以想花一千个 小时做这件事是有原因的。
podcast on this, right?
关于这个话题的播客节目是吧？
As, as, as you do, as there's so many incredible conversations about every
正如你所做的那样，关于每一 件事都有许多精彩的对话。
single emperor, every single nuanced detail of the emperors. It really is a, is
一位皇帝，皇帝的每一个细微 之处。它确实是一个，是
a thriving civilization. It's a thriving empire which in it
一个繁荣的文明。这是 一个繁荣的帝国，它
contains so many lessons for even the modern times. But anyway,
即使在现代，它仍然蕴含着许多值得 借鉴的经验。不过，总之，
you have written one of the books is Streams of Gold, Rivers of
你写的一本书是《黄金之 流，河流之河》。
Blood: The Rise and Fall of Byzantium, 955 AD to the First Crusade. So this
《血脉：拜占庭的兴衰，公元955年 至第一次十字军东征》。所以这
period has... We talked about survival and some low
这段时期已经过去了…… 我们讨论了生存和一些低
points. This is a period where, once again, there's some flourishing.
积分。这是一个再次 迎来繁荣的时期。
So by the 10th century in the Macedonian era, the empire is back.
因此，到了马其顿时代的 10世纪，帝国又重新崛起。
It's wealthy, it's culturally confident, and under emperors like Basil II,
它富裕，文化自信，并且在像巴西尔 二世这样的皇帝统治下，
Who I think is in your top 10 list.
我认为你心目中的前十名是……
it is expanding again, and this is a period that you
它正在再次扩张，而这是 一个你……的时期。
describe in part in your book, Streams of Gold, Rivers of Blood. So how did
在你的著作《黄金之河，鲜血之河》中对 此有部分描述。那么，情况如何呢？
Byzantium go from surviving to expanding again?
拜占庭帝国会从苟延残喘走向 再次扩张吗？
- So I wrote that book in part in order to test myself and see if I
所以我写那本书的部分原因是为了 测试自己，看看我是否……
could write narrative.
可以写叙事文。
So I hadn't written a history narrative book up until that point. Everything
所以在那之前，我还没有写 过历史叙事类书籍。一切
I wrote was sort of analytical, right?
我写的算是分析性的吧？
And it was successful enough that a few years later, my editor asked me to
而且它非常成功，几年 后，我的编辑请我……
write the big history, the new Roman Empire-
书写宏大的历史， 新罗马帝国——
- Yeah
- 是的
- ... the thousand page-
——……一千页——
- Of the whole thing
——关于整件事
- ... of the whole thing. And so I set for myself the
——整个事件。于是我给 自己设定了目标
task of explaining in this book, Streams of Gold, Rivers of Blood,
本书的任务是解释《黄金 之河，鲜血之河》
a very particular period that was marked by a
一段非常特殊的时期 ，其特点是
sudden turn to conquest again after a long period of more or less defensive war. 955,
经过长期或多或少的防御性战争 后，突然再次转向征服。 955，
there's a new military leadership is appointed, and
新的军事领导层 已经任命，
the Romans go conquering again, especially in Cilicia,
罗马人再次开始征服， 尤其是在西里西亚地区。
northern Syria, and Cyprus, and the Caucasus, and then eventually also Bulgaria.
叙利亚北部、塞浦路斯、高加索 地区，最终还包括保加利亚。
And then right afterwards, they have this generation plus
然后紧接着，他们 就有了这一代。
period of stability and prosperity, and
一段稳定繁荣的时期，以及
then they're hit by a triple whammy. These are three new
然后他们又遭受了三重 打击。这是三个新的
attackers. So it's primarily the Seljuk Turks coming in from the
攻击者。所以主要是塞尔柱 突厥人从……
east, some Pechenegs coming down from the north over the Danube,
向东，一些佩切涅格人从 北方越过多瑙河而来，
And the Normans in southern Italy.
还有意大利南部的诺曼人。
And under the pressure of this three-part attack, the,
在这三重攻击 的压力下，
you know, this expansionist what had become more imperial state buckles.
你知道，这种扩张主义已经演变 成一个更加帝国主义的国家。
And enters another one of these crises, just like the one we
于是，我们又陷入了另一场危机，就 像我们之前经历的那场一样。
described for the seventh century. You know, survives it by the skin of its teeth.
描述于七世纪。你知道 ，它侥幸活了下来。
And goes on again to rebuild and become prosperous, wealthy, and powerful
然后再次重建，变得繁荣 、富有和强大。
again, as it does throughout its history.
正如它历史上一直做的那样。
It's these cycles. So I just wanted to describe that iteration of that-
就是这些循环。所以我只是 想描述一下那个版本——
... that process, and that's what I do in that book.
……这个过程，也是我在 那本书里所做的。
- So I think the traditional view, In this perfect storm of the 11th century
所以我认为传统的观点是， 在11世纪这场完美风暴中
is that it was more to do with the internal sort of moral decay and,
也就是说，这更多地与内在 的道德沦丧有关，而且，
Civilian emperors neglecting the army, this internal stuff.
文官皇帝忽视军队 ，这些内部问题。
And you make the case that it's the external stuff, the
你认为问题出在 外部因素上，
three-prong attack, like you said, Normans in the west,
正如你所说，三管齐下的 进攻，西部的诺曼人，
the Turkic steppe people in the north, and in Central Asia, the Turks in the east.
北部的突厥草原民族，以及中亚 的突厥人，东部的突厥人。
Can you describe that, the three forces in the case that that was the
你能描述一下，在这种情况下 ，三种力是如何发挥作用的吗？
main reason why it hit a low?
导致其价格跌至低点的主要原因是什么？
- Well, this is also a methodological problem, right? In other words, when you're looking
- 嗯，这也是一个方法论问题，对吧 ？换句话说，当你在寻找的时候
at a society that suddenly faces a bunch of problems, and you could, you know,
在一个突然面临诸多问题的 社会里，你可能会……
reasonably make the case for a kind of decline or a crisis, is your instinct,
你的直觉是，要合理地论证 某种衰退或危机的存在。
it's your first instinct to suppose that there must be something wrong in the
你的第一反应很可能是，这里面 肯定出了什么问题。
internal mechanisms of that society that, you know, led it to fail,
你知道，导致那个社会走向 失败的内部机制
which is what my field has done traditionally.
这正是我所在领域 历来所做的。
Uh, in part because of the decline and fall model, right, of this
嗯，部分原因是由于这种衰退 和衰落模式，对吧。
society, we're kind of primed to think that there was something wrong with it.
社会上，我们似乎已经习惯性地 认为这其中肯定有什么问题。
It's a long story. Or is it reasonable to say that a society
说来话长。或者说， 一个社会是否合理呢？
that does not seem to have any, like, particularly serious structural flaws
它似乎没有任何特别 严重的结构缺陷。
is hit by external, you know, challenges that it
受到外部挑战的冲击 ，你知道，它
couldn't realistically have foreseen or prepared for such that, you
你不可能预见或预料到这种情况， 也不可能为此做好准备。
know, it, it couldn't cope with them and, as I said, buckled.
我知道，它无法应对它们，而且 ，正如我所说，它崩溃了。
And I think that's what happened. I think that's the,
我想事情就是这样发生 的。我认为那就是……
main narrative. Not that there weren't problems. There were. But
主线叙事。当然，也并非 没有问题。有。但
no state can, I mean, medieval or ancient, can realistically survive
任何国家，我的意思是，无论是中世纪的 还是古代的，都不可能真正生存下去。
the simultaneous attack of three very different kinds of
三种截然不同的 攻击同时发生
enemies, the Normans or, like, these knights...
敌人，诺曼人，或者像 这些骑士一样……
Like a new type of Western warfare that is just all about, you know,
就像一种新型的西方战争，其全部 意义就在于，你知道的，
grinding the enemy to bits. But who are also
将敌人碾成碎片 。但他们也
terrorists. Like, they're straight up terrorists.
恐怖分子。他们简直 就是恐怖分子。
- Normans are fascinating because, I mean, there's...
诺曼人很迷人， 我的意思是……
... there's a Viking component too-
……其中也包含维京元素——
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- 是的，是的，是的。
- ... with the Normans.
——与诺曼人一起。
- Yeah, yeah.
- 是啊是啊。
- That's a whole... So they have, they have three different kinds of enemies.
那真是一整套……所以他们 有三种不同的敌人。
- Yes. The Pechenegs, who's, you know, a, a
- 是的。佩切涅格人，你知道，他们是一个，一个
totally different type of, you know, probably mostly nomadic horsemen.
完全不同类型的骑兵，你知道， 他们可能大多是游牧骑兵。
And then the Seljuk Turks who are
然后是塞尔柱突厥人，他们是
also mostly nomadic horsemen, but who are coming in from Central Asia
也大多是游牧骑兵， 但他们来自中亚。
with vast reserves of manpower behind them. In fact,
他们背后拥有庞大的人力资源 储备。实际上，
either intending to or, as it happens, effecting a demographic change in not just
无论是意图还是实际上，都造成 了人口结构的变化，而不仅仅是
demographic, but ecological too, because they basically, when they
人口统计学上，但生态学上也是 如此，因为它们基本上，当它们
move into Asia Minor, they're transforming or terraforming,
他们进军小亚细亚，正在 进行改造或地球化进程。
Agricultural land into pasturage.
将农田改为牧场。
And, and they're just backed by reserves of manpower
而且，他们背后还有 人力储备支持。
that no other enemy of the empire has had yet.
这是帝国其他任何敌人 都未曾拥有过的。
Uh, so yeah, how do you, how do you cope with these situations? I mean, they're, it's very,
呃，所以，你是如何应对这种情况 的？我的意思是，他们，这非常，
very difficult, and it's a wonder that they survived it at all. Now, they also have
非常艰难，他们能活下来简直 是个奇迹。现在他们也有
internal problems, and I'm not gonna sort of try to sweep these under the rug,
内部问题，我不会试图 掩盖这些问题。
right? In particular, we're seeing the end of the Macedonian
正确的？尤其值得注意的是， 我们正在目睹马其顿帝国的终结。
dynasty. This is a dynasty that had lasted for about two centuries, and
王朝。这是一个持续了 大约两个世纪的王朝，
this has a kind of politically destabilizing effect. New
这会产生某种政治不稳定 的影响。新的
emperors, and there are a lot of, like, childless old men in this period,
皇帝们，而且这一时期有很多 没有子嗣的老人。
are relatively insecure. They don't have this sort of a dynastic glitz behind
相对缺乏安全感。他们背后没有 这种王朝的光鲜亮丽。
them, and so they're tending to, to buy a lot of political support,
他们，所以他们倾向于这样做 ，以收买大量的政治支持。
like hand out these exemptions, give cash, you know, titles to
比如发放这些豁免权，给现金 ，你知道，还有所有权证书
anyone who will support them, and this, of course, causes a budget problem. Like, they
任何愿意支持他们的人，当然， 这会导致预算问题。比如，他们
don't have enough money after a while. And then they have to start raising all of these armies to deal with all of
过了一段时间后，钱就不够用了。然后他们就不得不 开始组建所有这些军队来应对所有这些……
these problems, and that just increases the pressure on the budget, and
这些问题只会增加预算 压力，而且
so there is an internal problem as well, yeah.
所以也存在内部 问题，是的。
- So you mentioned this loop of thriving and then having to survive,
所以你提到了这种繁荣 与生存之间的循环，
surviving, that happens a few times- ... throughout the history of the Roman Empire.
幸存下来，这种情况在罗马 帝国的历史上发生过几次。
It seems that societies in general oscillate in that way.
社会似乎普遍都会 以这种方式波动。
Is there something particular you could say about the oscillations,
关于这些振荡现象，您 有什么特别想说的吗？
the loops that the Roman Empire goes through?
罗马帝国经历的那些循环 往复的过程？
- Yes. Now, I don't think this is an oscillation. At least that's not how I think of it in my own
- 是的。现在，我认为这不是一种振荡 。至少我个人不是这么想的。
mind. Um, so as I explained, the crises that this, this
头脑。嗯，正如我解释过的 ，这场危机，这场危机
polity, this state, this society that it undergoes
政体，这个国家，以及 它所经历的这个社会
are dis- there are a discrete number of them. I can tell
是离散的——它们的数量是 离散的。我看得出来
you what they are, and we've talked about most of them so far.
你知道它们是什么，而且到目前为止 我们已经讨论过其中的大部分了。
They don't last very long, and they are all sudden challenges that appear
它们持续时间不长，而且 都是突如其来的挑战。
from the outside. In other words, they're exogenous shocks,
从外部来看。换句话 说，它们是外生冲击。
that they can't really have prepared for.
这是他们始料未及的。
These shocks cause massive territorial loss,
这些冲击造成了 巨大的领土损失，
which requires adjustment, right? But they don't last
这需要做出调整，对吧 ？但它们不会持久。
that long. In other words, the Romans almost always, at some point,
这么久。换句话说，罗马人 几乎总是在某个时候
figure out how to hold a line, how to consolidate their position, regroup-
想办法守住阵地，巩固 阵地，重新集结——
and put their economy and their society back on a trajectory of revival, regrowth,
并使他们的经济和社会重新 走上复苏、再增长的轨道，
and eventual reconquest. Always. Every single time, except the last time, right?
最终收复失地。总是。每次都 是这样，除了最后一次，对吧？
And for me, this poses the following kind of dilemma,
对我而言，这就带来了 以下这种两难困境：
which I can answer. And the dilemma is, should we define the
我可以回答这个问题。而难题 在于，我们是否应该定义……
society by these brief crises of exogenous shocks,
社会受到这些短暂的 外生冲击危机的影响，
or should we define it by the centuries-long, sometimes,
或者我们应该用几个世纪以来 ，有时是……来定义它？
periods of regrowth, consolidation, and stabilization, which are endogenous.
内生的再生、巩固 和稳定期。
Nobody came from the outside to help them rebuild.
没有人从外来帮助他们 重建家园。
Uh, and my answer is unequivocally the latter. So
嗯，我的答案毫无疑问 是后者。所以
I see this as a society whose internal organization primes it to stabilize
我认为这是一个内部组织结构使 其能够稳定下来的社会。
and embark on steady growth. Slow and gradual, but steady.
并开始稳步发展。缓慢 而渐进，但稳步前进。
And that's what I would like my field to explain more, and I'm
而这正是我希望我的领域能够 更详细解释的内容，我是
gonna try to do so in the book I mentioned that I'm writing
我打算在我提到的那本正在 写的书中尝试这样做。
on, like, the longevity or the resilience of this society.
比如，这个社会的长久 发展或韧性。
And not try to center the crises,
不要试图将危机作为中心议题，
which I see as being from the outside. Like, these aren't...
我认为这是从外部视角来看 的。比如，这些不是……
Of course, they're part of its story, but they're not coming from it.
当然，它们是故事的一部分，但 它们并非源自这个故事。
What's coming from it is the stability, and I think that's the more
它带来的是稳定性， 我认为这才是最重要的。
interesting part of this society.
这是社会中有趣的一部分。
- Yeah, so the, you know, these peak-to-peak histories,
- 是的，所以，你知道，这些 峰峰值历史记录，
as you can think of them, they miss the machinery in the valleys. Institutions,
你可以想象，他们会想念山谷 里的机械设备。机构，
incentives, daily life, all of these things. The politics, the religion.
激励机制、日常生活，所有 这些因素。政治，宗教。
You have a bunch of revisionist history ideas in your work. You're
你的作品中有很多修正 主义历史观点。你是
challenging the field.
挑战该领域。
- Yes. You could say that.
- 是的。你可以这么说。
- In the best possible way. So just to linger on it, what
以最好的方式。所以，就让 我们再多想想吧，什么
are, what are some of the things that historians miss? So this is a big one, right,
那么，历史学家们会忽略哪些方面 呢？所以这可是件大事，对吧？
that you're speaking to, which is, like, focusing too much
你正在和谁说话，就 好像，太专注了
on specific moments versus on the broad structural underpinnings
着眼于特定时刻与着眼于 广泛的结构基础
of, of an empire, of a society.
属于，属于一个帝国，属于一个社会。
- Right. So what you alluded to there is a critique
- 正确的。所以你刚才提到 的是一种批评
of what we might call short histories of Byzantium, which is a kind
我们可以称之为拜占庭 简史的一种
of genre of a book. Right? This isn't necessarily, like, what my other
书籍的类型。正确的？这不一定 就是我其他方面的情况。
revisionist ideas are about. The more important ones are things
修正主义思想是关于…… 更重要的是事物
like the monarchical republic that we talked about. In other words, that there's
就像我们之前讨论过的君主制共和国 一样。换句话说，存在……
actually a broader spectrum of political participation.
实际上，这代表了更 广泛的政治参与。
Um, that emperors are having to look over their shoulders all the time. That there is a
嗯，皇帝们总是要时刻 提防着别人。确实存在
deeper matrix of Roman Republican thought there. Like, that's one
那里蕴含着罗马共和国思想更深 层次的结构。比如，那是一个
revisionist idea. Another one is about Roman identity,
修正主义观点。另一个问题 是关于罗马人的身份认同。
just like who are these people?
这些人到底是谁？
And no, they are Romans, and in fact, it's kind of an ethnic identity after a
不，他们是罗马人，事实上 ，这是一种民族认同。
certain point. Like, those kinds of ideas.
某个点。比如，类似的想法。
The criticism of the peak to peak kinds of books.
对那种从头到尾、跌宕 起伏的书籍的批评。
So if you're trying to condense 1,200 years into 120 pages
所以，如果你想把1200年的历史 浓缩成120页的话。
or even, you know, even 200 pages,
或者，你知道，甚至200页，
there's no way to do so realistically and give a sense of the whole
现实中不可能做到这一点，也 无法展现整体情况。
terrain. In other words, what these books do is they go, they jump from,
地形。换句话说，这些书的 作用就是跳跃式地转换，
from highlight to highlight, and these highlights are sometimes things like,
从亮点到亮点，这些亮点 有时是这样的：
you know, everything Justinian did because it's so extravagant, to the crises.
你知道，查士丁尼所做的一切都是 因为太奢侈，以应对危机。
The crises are, of course, dramatic moments that you can't skip.
危机当然是戏剧性的时刻 ，你无法错过。
And you can't get a sense from these books as to
你无法从这些书中 了解到这一点。
how all of this is interconnected in the valleys, right?
山谷里的这一切是如何相互 关联的，对吧？
In the crags, down there. Like, what are the mechanisms that are
就在下面那边的峭壁上。 例如，有哪些机制是……
connecting these peaks together? And that's how I tried to write
将这些山峰连接起来？我 就是这样尝试写作的。
the big history, The New Roman Empire, is to tell the story by
这部宏大的历史著作《新罗马帝国 》讲述的正是这样一个故事：
casting light in those darker places. That is, to show how
照亮那些黑暗的地方。也就 是说，为了展示如何
especially institutions and ideologies sort of
尤其是制度和意识 形态之类的
tie, you know, people's lives together. That
你知道，就是把人们的生活 联系在一起。那
is, tie people to institutions and to the broader history that surrounds
就是将人与机构以及更广泛 的历史联系起来。
them. So that the reader can get a sense when
他们。以便读者能够 感受到何时
I'm, when I'm recounting specific events or either of, you know,
当我回忆具体事件或者两 者之一时，你知道，
greatness or of a success or a failure, that they can understand
伟大、成功或失败 ，他们都能理解。
roughly why these things are happening, right? Look, there's no perfect
大致来说，这些事情发生的原因是什么 ？你看，世上没有完美。
answer. A short book will just not tell you these things. A long book,
回答。一本篇幅较短的书是不会告诉 你这些事情的。一本很长的书，
well, is a long book.
嗯，这是一本很长的书。
- Well, in some sense, I mean, this, in this, even in this very conversation, I think we did a pretty
嗯，从某种意义上说，我的意思是，就这 次谈话而言，我认为我们做得相当不错。
good job of looking at the valleys, at the structure, at the institutions.
很好地分析了各个环节 、结构和制度。
And that gives you a sense of the whole underpinnings.
这让你对整个基础 有了大致的了解。
And so it's, it's beautiful. It's a beautiful way to see history, especially for
所以，它很美。这是一种欣赏 历史的美好方式，尤其对于……
societies that have lasted as long as- ... as the, as the East Roman Empire has.
像东罗马帝国那样 延续至今的社会。
- But it did take us a few hours.
但这确实花了我们几个小时。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- Yes. You're right. But it requires that you actually spend some
- 是的。你说得对。但这需要 你实际花一些时间。
time to look in there, yeah.
是时候进去看看了。
- What's, what's a few hours among friends?
和朋友在一起几个小时又算得了什么呢？
- No, no, no, that's... I agree.
- 不，不，不，那是……我同意。
- Uh, so zooming out and asking once again,
呃，那我再缩小一下视角问问，
the old we're getting a little close to last call at a bar,
以前常说的“酒吧 快要打烊了”，
I'm gonna ask you the big question. We asked it before about the
我要问你一个重要的问题。我们 之前问过这个问题。
collapse of the West Roman Empire.
西罗马帝国的崩溃。
When did the decline of the East Roman Empire begin for you? Throughout this loops,
你认为东罗马帝国的衰落是从什么 时候开始的？在这一系列循环中，
when, if you were to predict, Would you be able to say where this is gonna be over?
如果让你预测，你能说说这件 事会在什么时候结束吗？
And what led to that decline and the
导致这种衰落的原因是什么？
collapse? So of course, the collapse is finally in 1453 AD.
坍塌？所以，崩溃最终 发生在公元 1453 年。
- Right. That's actually a very good question. In other words, um,
- 正确的。这确实是个很好的 问题。换句话说，嗯，
not looking at all of the previous crises that caused loss of territory,
暂且不考虑之前所有导致 领土丧失的危机，
like, you know, you lose Egypt, you lose Syria, you lose Palestine, you lose
你知道，你失去了埃及，失去了叙利亚 ，失去了巴勒斯坦，你就失去了
Eastern Asia Minor, you lo- right? But at what point could you
小亚细亚东部，你懂的？但是， 在什么情况下你可以……
say there's no coming back from this?
你说这件事已经没有回头路了吗？
Right? I would say early 14th century. Somewhere between 1300 and 1350,
正确的？我认为是14世纪早期。大约 在1300年至1350年之间，
the sources of resilience begin to dry up, and you have a number of
韧性来源开始枯竭 ，你有很多
setbacks. They lose Asia Minor to the Turks by 1300, roughly,
挫折。大约在公元1300年，他们将 小亚细亚割让给了土耳其人。
which means that you can now no longer draw upon the
这意味着你现在 无法再利用
two wings, as it were, the European side and
仿佛有两个翼， 欧洲一方和
the Asian side, which they could always do. They're confined to Europe.
亚洲方面，他们一直都可以 这样做。它们仅限于欧洲。
And then you have a series of civil wars, you have the Serbian
然后就爆发了一系列内战 ，比如塞尔维亚内战。
expansion and you have the Black Death, and they never recover from that.
扩张之后，黑死病爆发，他们 再也没有从中恢复过来。
In 1300, you think of this, you look at it and you think, "That's a
到了1300年，你想到这个，你看着 它，然后你会想，“那是一个……”
tiny little Balkan state."
“一个微小的巴尔干国家。”
Okay, it goes from Constantinople to the Adriatic in this
好的，这条路线从君士坦丁堡 延伸到亚得里亚海。
just sort of ribbon, right, this, this corridor that just stretches
就像一条带子，对吧，这 条走廊一直延伸下去。
across the Balkans. And yet, it's not that much smaller than England
遍及巴尔干半岛。然而，它 其实比英格兰小不了多少。
and has about as much, if not more, revenue, because they're still able
而且收入即便没有超过，也几乎 一样多，因为他们仍然能够
to raise cash, because taxes.
筹集资金，因为要缴税。
Right? So the emperor's still able to pull in a lot of gold. Um,
正确的？所以皇帝仍然能够 攫取大量的黄金。嗯，
and his territory is not, you know, completely insignificant.
而且他的领地也并 非完全无关紧要。
It's not what it, you know, the Roman Empire used to be. But I don't think that it's
它已经不是以前的罗马帝国了 。但我认为并非如此。
completely lost. Then they have some civil wars. Then one
彻底迷路了。然后他们之间 爆发了内战。然后一个
emperor- um, a rebel makes a deal with the Serbs, surrenders half that
皇帝——嗯，一个叛军与塞尔维亚人 达成协议，割让了一半的领土。
territory. Okay, after that, game over.
领土。好了，之后游戏就结束了。
What's surprising is it takes the Turks that long. 1453, that's another century.
令人惊讶的是，土耳其人竟然花了这么长 时间。 1453年，那又是另一个世纪了。
Right? It didn't need to be. It looks like they might have
正确的？本来不必如此 。看起来他们可能已经
had it wrapped up like 50 years after- uh, you know, like by 1400.
大约 50 年后就解决了——呃， 你知道，大概到 1400 年左右。
But then accidental events happened. This is Timur, Tamerlane comes-
但随后发生了一些意外事件。这 是帖木儿，帖木儿来了——
... from Central Asia, trounces the Turks, breaks up their empire. So they go
来自中亚的……击败了土耳其人， 瓦解了他们的帝国。于是他们就走了
into a cycle of, you know, rebuilding, and so that's why it takes
进入一个重建的循环 ，所以才需要
another 50 years. Anyway, but I'd say by the 1340s, game over.
再过50年。总之，我觉得到 14 世纪 40 年代，游戏就结束了。
- And so why did it collapse? What are the things in the ground, when you zoom out,
那么，它为什么会倒塌呢？镜头拉远 后，你会看到地面上有什么东西？
the thing that ate away at the, I like this term, sources of resilience?
是什么侵蚀了——我喜欢用这个 词——韧性的来源？
- Oh, foreign invasions. There's no question. It's just-
哦，外敌入侵。毫无疑问 。只是——
- It's just invasions
这只是入侵而已
- ...it's foreign invasions, those which they could
——……是外国入侵，他们可能 发动的那些入侵。
not cope with. They coped with lots of them.
无法应对。他们应对 了很多这样的事情。
But, you know, it, all it takes is to lose to one,
但是，你知道，只需要 输给一个人就够了。
and you lose some part of your territory. And if you keep losing enough,
你失去了一部分领土。如果 你一直输得太多，
you won't have anything to fall back on, and that's what happens.
你将没有任何退路 ，而这就是后果。
- So really, you know, if there's no significant external invasions,
所以说，如果没有重大 的外部入侵，
the East Roman Empire, the fundamentals, the taxation system,
东罗马帝国概况、 基本情况、税收制度
the way the, the policies were developed, the way the politics was done, the way
政策的制定方式，政治运作 的方式，以及其他种种。
the representation was done, all of that, this empire could have lasted
一切就绪，这个帝国 本可以延续下去。
for another thousand years.
再过一千年。
- Absolutely. I'm absolutely convinced of this because
- 绝对地。我对此深信 不疑，因为
you never see movements to split away.
你从未看到任何分裂的行动。
That is, there's no separatist movements, at least not on the part of
也就是说，至少在……一方 ，不存在分离主义运动。
any Roman provincials. There's one separatist movement, which is Bulgaria.
任何罗马行省居民。保加利亚 存在一个分离主义运动。
We mentioned Bulgaria was conquered, right, in 1018. There's
我们之前提到过保加利亚 是在1018年被征服的，对吧？
a couple of independentist movements rebellions. Um,
几次独立运动 叛乱。嗯，
eventually one succeeds in 1185, so just under two centuries.
最终在 1185 年成功，用 了将近两个世纪。
So Bulgaria is the only part of this empire that
所以保加利亚是这个 帝国中唯一一部分
actively seeks to break away and does so.
积极寻求脱离并成功脱离。
But for the rest of the 1,200 years, you don't find provincials wanting
但在接下来的1200年里，你不会 发现地方居民有所欠缺。
to leave this system. However much they complain about the taxes,
离开这个系统。然而，无论 他们如何抱怨税收，
they don't want to leave, and they make no move to do so. You also never have
他们不想离开，也没有要离开 的打算。你也从来没有过
a moment when the center loses its ability to tax its territories,
中央政府失去对其领土 征税能力的时刻。
right? You don't have, like, widespread peasant uprisings or
正确的？你不会遇到像大规模 农民起义之类的情况，或者
provinc- or, right, agricultural rebellions or these kinds of things,
省级——或者，对，农业 叛乱或诸如此类的事情，
Which happens in every other one of these empires. They also never decide
这种情况在其他所有帝国中都 会发生。他们也从未决定过。
to partition it. The Franks partition theirs, right, like after Charlemagne.
将其分割。法兰克人按照查理曼大帝 的统治方式划分领土，没错。
No. There are no, like, Roman
不，没有像罗马人那样的。
warlords that try to carve out a piece of the territory for
试图瓜分领土 的军阀
themselves and rule it independent. Nope, that doesn't happen either. So
他们自己独立统治。不，这 种情况也不会发生。所以
if you're looking at the kinds of factors that cause states to fail,
如果你要探究导致国家 失败的各种因素，
fragment, you know, become ungovernable, these never happen.
你知道，分裂、变得无法控制 ，这些事情从来不会发生。
- This is so incredible. This is truly incredible.
这太不可思议了。这 真是太不可思议了。
In the history of human civilization, just an incredible study of
在人类文明史上，这简直是一 项不可思议的研究
what human societies can form. So, so what, what,
人类社会能够形成什么？ 所以，所以呢，什么？
what, what are the whys? Why? Why? Why was it so stable?
什么？为什么？为什么？为什么 ？它为什么如此稳定？
- Well, now look, there are other stable... Like, for example,
- 嗯，你看，还有其他一些稳定 的……比如，例如，
The, the British monarchy. That's been around for quite a while.
那，英国君主制。这种情况 已经存在很长时间了。
- Yeah, that's true.
- 是的，没错。
- Right? States like Portugal, Japan, they have one thing in common.
- 正确的？像葡萄牙、日本这样的国家 ，它们有一个共同点。
They're all tucked away at the edges.
它们都藏在边缘地带。
Like, they're off, they're little islands or whatever. They're not like, right?
就像，它们与世隔绝，像一座座小岛什么 的。他们不是那样的，对吧？
We're talking about a society that was right in the-
我们谈论的是一个正处于 ……的社会。
- In the, yeah
是的，在……
- ... middle of one of the main corridors of empire building and new religions
——位于帝国建立和新兴宗教发展 的主要通道之一的中心地带
in the world. This is the most dangerous neighborhood, right,
在世界上。这里是最 危险的街区，对吧？
that you can possibly live in.
你可能可以居住的地方。
So no wonder it didn't survive. Like it would've been
难怪它没能存活下来 。就像它本该有的样子
extraordinary if it had. But absent those forces,
如果真是如此，那就太不可思议 了。但如果没有这些因素，
I don't see any forces of internal
我没看到任何内部力量。
decomposition that would have imperiled it, you know, significantly.
你知道，那种分解 会严重危及它的生命。
- So what, I mean we've talked about a lot of it, but what, just to, like,
所以呢，我的意思是，我们已经谈 了很多，但是，就想说的是，
return to it, why was there no internal
回到正题，为什么没有内部原因？
sources of decomposition. Like why, why did it work so well?
分解源。为什么，为什么 它如此有效？
Why did the people feel represented? Yes, they— By the way, you talked about
为什么人们会觉得自己被代表了？ 是的，他们——对了，你刚才谈到了
how they complain about the taxes, which is one of the signs of a healthy society, that
他们抱怨税收的方式，恰恰 是健康社会的一个标志。
we... It's like complaining about the weather. The fact that you complain about the taxes
我们……这就像抱怨天气一样。你抱怨税收 这件事本身就说明了一些问题。
actually means that you're happy with the taxes, kind of counterintuitively, or it's not too
实际上，这表示你对税收感到满意，这有点 违反直觉，或者说税收并不太高。
bad. You're just complaining as part of the system.
坏的。你只是体制的一部分 ，在抱怨而已。
Anyway, but why? Why, why did it work so well? Why did everybody get along—
总之，为什么呢？为什么，为什么它 如此有效？为什么大家相处融洽？
- Oh, no, they—
哦，不，他们——
- ... feel represented? No, not get along. Not in a, in a silly way.
……觉得自己被代表了吗？不，我们相处 不来。不是以一种愚蠢的方式。
I mean, sufficiently to where they wouldn't... Warlords wouldn't
我的意思是，足以让他们 ……军阀们不会……
rise and break apart the system and—
奋起反抗，打破现有体制——
... or if there was those kinds of forces, they would come back together.
……或者说，如果真有那种 力量，它们终究会再次汇合。
Like, why is this such a great self-healing system?
为什么这是一个如此 强大的自愈系统？
- So you're exactly right. So sufficient is the key word. We don't want to idealize this,
- 所以你说得完全正确。所以，“足够”是 关键。我们不想把这件事理想化，
right? These aren't, like, they're not just dancing in the streets, holding hands and then
正确的？这些可不是那种，他们不 是在街上手拉手跳舞，然后……
direct... It's so— Even when it comes to the tax system,
直接……就是这样——即使是 税收制度方面也是如此。
they are complaining all the time. Of course, they're doing so because they know
他们总是抱怨个不停。当然 ，他们这样做是因为他们知道
that complaining gets you things.
抱怨并不能给你带来好处。
There's no disincentive to complaining. You might not get what you want, or you might get it,
抱怨并不会受到任何惩罚。你可能无法 得到你想要的，也可能会得到。
but you know, no harm will come to you. So they're complaining all the
但是你知道，你不会受到任何 伤害。所以他们一直在抱怨
time. They have all of these civil wars. They're like, "Okay." Um,
时间。他们之间爆发了这么多内战 。他们会说：“好的。”嗯，
so I think I would give you a two-part answer, so
所以我想我会分 两部分回答你，
really quickly, as to why this held together so well.
很快就明白了为什么 它能保持如此完好。
First is that an extraordinary effort was
首先，这是一项非凡的努力。
made by the authorities to persuade their subjects that they were
当局为了让臣民相信他们 是……而制定的。
ruling on their behalf, and I think, for the most part,
代表他们做出裁决，而且我 认为，在大多数情况下，
actually tended to do so. And the second is that it
实际上，他往往确实会 这样做。第二点是，它
had a very tightly unified identity
具有非常紧密的统一性
as Roman and as Orthodox. In other words, for the most,
既是罗马天主教徒，也是东正教徒。 换句话说，在大多数情况下，
most time, they knew that they were surrounded by enemies who were not those things.
大多数时候，他们知道自己被敌人包围 了，而这些敌人并非如此。
And they did not want to live under the power of non-Romans and
他们不愿生活在非罗马人 的统治之下，
non-Christian people. And so those two factors combined, I think, gave everybody
非基督徒。所以，我认为，这两个因素 结合起来，给每个人带来了影响。
reason to hold it together. The alternatives were worse.
维系它的理由。其他 选择更糟糕。
- Yeah. I mean, that's a really brilliant summary, and I think we should mention
- 是的。我的意思是，这真是一个精彩 的总结，我认为我们应该提一下。
that both the rhetoric and the action are important. I think you've
言辞和行动都很重要 。我认为你已经
articulated that rhetoric is really powerful, like stating over and over and over-
他指出，修辞的力量非常强大，就像 一遍又一遍地重复一样——
... that you represent the people, that you're acting on behalf of the people and
……你代表人民，你 为人民行事，而且
doing the action. But it's not enough to actually do the action. You would think that's all
执行该动作。但仅仅采取行动是不够 的。你可能会觉得这就完了。
Machiavelli says that's the only thing that matters. But no.
马基雅维利说，这才是唯一重要 的事。但并非如此。
It's the rhetoric actually has a lot of power- ... because it is a uniting idea-
这种修辞手法其实很有力量——因为 它是一种团结人心的理念——
... an ideal that propagates through time, and it pacifies you. It
……一种经久不衰的理想，它 能抚慰你的心灵。它
makes you, it puts you at peace. Rhetoric is important.
它让你感到平静 。修辞很重要。
- I'll give you an example. As an academic administrator, right?
我给你举个例子。作为一名 学术管理人员，对吗？
I mean, I was chair of a department for years and years.
我的意思是，我当 过很多年的系主任。
There's a difference between a dean who says, "Sorry, bad budget situation. We're
院长说“抱歉，预算情况不佳，我们 ……”和另一种说法是有区别的。
just going to have to cut your programs," on the one hand, and a dean who says,
一方面，院长说：“我们不得不削减一些 项目”，另一方面，院长又说：“
"I am fully on board with what you're trying to accomplish with
我完全赞同你正在 努力实现的目标。
these programs. I am a defender of the humanities. Unfortunately,
这些项目。我是人文学科 的捍卫者。很遗憾，
we have this budget situation, and we're going to have to cut some of the programs. But
我们面临目前的预算状况，不得不 削减一些项目。但
I assure you, the moment I'm in this with you together-
我向你保证，只要我和 你一起并肩作战——
... the moment we find the funds, we will restore them."
一旦资金到位，我们 将立即恢复它们。
Those two just rhetorical strategies, they're aiming at the same practical outcome,
这两种只是修辞策略，它们的目标 都是相同的实际结果。
will produce very different levels of compliance- ... right, and consensus.
这将产生截然不同的合规水平 ……没错，以及共识。
- And I should say that there's subtlety there.
——而且我应该说，这 里面蕴含着微妙之处。
The best rhetoric in that context, and maybe in the East Roman Empire,
在那种语境下，或许在东罗马帝国 时期，最好的修辞手法是……
is you also have to believe it.
你还得相信这一点。
- Yes. It has to be credible. You can't just say it and then not do it.
- 是的。它必须是可信的。 你不能光说不做。
- But one of the things I've learned about humans, just having, doing this little podcast,
但通过做这个小播客，我了解 到关于人类的一件事是：
is that people could-- Like, the best way to say a thing,
也就是说，人们可以——比如 ，最好的表达方式是，
a powerful thing, is to really believe it.
真正相信某件事，是一件很有力量的事。
And so, like, this is clearly one of the things that made
所以，很明显，这是导致这 种情况发生的原因之一。
the Roman Empire work, is doing the action is the best way to make the
罗马帝国的运作方式是，采取行动 是实现这一目标的最佳途径。
rhetoric powerful and effective.
雄辩有力，效果显著。
- Yeah. This is sort of what Aristotle says about tyrants.
- 是的。这有点像亚里士多德 对暴君的描述。
In The Politics, Aristotle's giving essentially advice to tyrants on how to protect
在《政治学》中，亚里士多德实际上是在向暴君们 提出如何保护自己的建议。
themselves because tyrants are usually hated and are killed in coups,
他们自己也会这样做，因为暴君通常会被 人憎恨，并在政变中被推翻。
right? And he says, "Well, how-- You know, essentially, how do you manage
正确的？他说：“嗯，如何—— 你知道，本质上，你如何管理
to secure yourself when you're a tyrant?" Well, you know, you can start
“当你是个暴君时，如何保护 自己？”嗯，你知道，你可以开始
by maybe, you know, obeying the laws or making sure that your subjects obey
或许，你知道，通过遵守法律 或者确保你的臣民遵守法律。
the laws and, you know, maybe work for the interests of yourself. Essentially,
法律，以及，你知道的，也许是 为了你自己的利益。本质上，
he's telling them to kind of become benevolent kings.
他是在告诉他们要 成为仁慈的君主。
And the best way to persuade your subjects that you're legitimate, benevolent
而说服你的臣民相信你是合法、 仁慈的，最好的方法就是
kings is to be that.
君王就是如此。
- So what, from all of this, from this 2,200-year history of the Roman Empire,
那么，从这一切，从罗马帝国这2200年 的历史中，我们能得出什么结论呢？
what lessons can we draw for modern times? Now we're sitting in America, this
我们能从中汲取哪些经验教训应用 于现代社会？现在我们身处美国，
young empire. I know we're not calling it an empire, but, you know.
年轻的帝国。我知道我们不 称它为帝国，但是，你知道的。
- Lots of people are calling it an empire. I thought it was sort of taboo. Yeah, in the 20th
很多人都称它为帝国。我当时觉得 这有点禁忌。是的，在20世纪
century, it was like, "Is America an empire now?" But like, I
上世纪，人们会问：“美国现在是 一个帝国了吗？”但是，我
think since the Iraq War, like since 2003, I've seen at least very casual uses of
我认为自从伊拉克战争以来，大概从2003年起 ，我至少看到过一些非常随意的用法。
America and empire in the same, you know, sentence without any kind of
把美国和帝国放在同一个句子中 ，你知道，没有任何意义。
hand-wringing.
焦虑不安。
- Is it ever called that in a academic setting?
在学术场合中，这种 说法是否也存在？
- Yes.
- 是的。
- I mean, it's technically, I guess you could say-
我的意思是，严格来说，我 想你可以这么说——
- Oh, yeah
哦，是的
- ... given, given the expanse of the military bases and,
鉴于军事基地 的规模，
and the military might and and the way that represents
以及军事实力 及其代表方式
itself in the geopolitical context.
就其本身而言，在地缘政治背景下。
- There are books published all the time that unironically
- 一直以来都有一些书籍出版 ，这些书籍毫不讽刺地
Discuss America as an empire in various ways. Yeah, no.
从各个方面探讨美国作为一个 帝国的地位。不，不是。
- By the way, both positive and negative.
顺便说一句，既有正面的，也有负面的。
So when you're saying a positive thing about America, calling it an empire, and when you're saying it
所以，当你说美国的好话，称它为 帝国，当你这么说的时候……
to criticize America, you call it an empire. Yeah, you're right.
批评美国，就称其为帝国 。是的，你说得对。
- Yeah. I mean, most academic books aren't trying to do, like, either. They're just trying to analyze a
- 是的。我的意思是，大多数学术书籍并没有 试图做到这一点。他们只是想分析一个
situation.
情况。
- What lessons about, about representing the people, about flourishing,
关于代表人民、关于繁荣发展 ，我们能学到什么？
about stability can we draw?
关于稳定性，我们能画个图吗？
- I will say that, just drawing on what we were talking about a moment ago,
我想说的是，就拿我们刚才 讨论的内容来说吧，
that investing in institutions that work for the majority of your subjects,
投资于那些为大多数 民众服务的机构，
even if indirectly, like they have to pay a cost for them, but you have to explain to them
即使是间接的，比如他们需要为此付出 代价，但你必须向他们解释清楚。
why they're paying that cost, is to the benefit of the ruling classes as well.
他们付出这样的代价，对统治 阶级来说也是有利的。
Because you're-- ideally, you're thinking about
因为你——理想情况 下，你在思考
long-term success and not just your own
长远的成功，而不仅仅是你自己的成功。
short-term, you know, gain. And I think that's what this society
你知道，就是短期收益。 我认为这就是这个社会
tends to do well. You know, the Romans generally, you know how they built roads for the,
通常表现良好。你知道，罗马人通常，你 知道他们是如何修建道路的，
the centuries and the millennia. They built institutions too. You know,
几个世纪，几千年。他们也建立 了各种机构。你知道，
one of the institutions they built was, like, the Christian Church.
他们建立的机构之一 就是基督教教会。
Like, they build things to last.
他们建造的东西经久耐用。
Um, and I think that's a, that's a good lesson beyond even the roads. I think
嗯，我认为这是一个很好的教训， 甚至超越了道路本身。我认为
institutions that explain, you know, to people why they exist,
那些向人们解释自身 存在意义的机构，
is... Yeah, I think we could we could use some of that.
是……嗯，我想我们 可以用上一些。
- And also the first point you made about the East Roman Empire. I think
还有你提到的关于东罗马 帝国的第一点。我认为
you've said that US foreign policy sometimes has a, quite a
你曾说过，美国的外交 政策有时相当……
large gap between the rhetoric and the in modern times, the rhetoric and the action.
现代社会中，言辞与行动 之间存在巨大差距。
- Oh, yeah. Yeah.
- 哦，是的。是的。
- And so that's to the Machiavelli's point that we want to
所以，这就是马基雅维利想要 表达的观点：
maybe narrow that gap for a successful empire, for a successful nation.
或许缩小这种差距，对一个成功的帝国、 一个成功的国家来说至关重要。
The rhetoric has to match the action.
言辞必须与行动相符。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- And it doesn't quite for some of the foreign policy engagements in the world.
——但对于世界上的一些外交政策 互动来说，情况并非如此。
- So in the context of the society I study, let's say the army
所以，就我研究的社会而 言，比如说军队。
is the single largest expense, is doing pretty much what
最大的单项开支，基本上 就是做什么的
the emperors say that it's doing, which is protecting its subjects.
皇帝们说，它正在这样做 ，那就是保护它的臣民。
That's actually what it's doing most of the time. Not all the time. So, for
实际上，它大部分时间都是这么做 的。并非总是如此。所以，对于
example, emperors will sometimes take the armies out on a
例如，皇帝有时会率领 军队外出……
raid or an expedition, you know, crack some skulls, gather some
突袭或者远征，你知道，就是打爆 几个脑袋，收集一些……
plunder, come back, and this is done to glorify the emperor. Like, yeah. Yeah, yeah, this,
掠夺而归，这样做是为了荣耀皇帝 。是啊。对，对，就是这样。
this does happen. But for the most part, they're doing that, not much else.
这种情况确实会发生。但大多数情况下， 他们只做这些，没做什么其他事。
And actually, in pre-modern context, it's very difficult to
事实上，在前现代语境 下，这非常困难。
operate like, you know, shadow foreign policies and things like
运作方式就像，你知道的 ，影子外交政策之类的。
this. Like, it's just not part of the-
这。就好像，它根本不属于——
... It's not in the cards. But America in particular has such
……这不可能。但 美国尤其如此。
a history of proclaiming the loftiest goals.
一段宣称拥有最崇高 目标的历史。
It just, sometimes just, you know, breathtakingly implausible.
有时候，这简直令人 难以置信，匪夷所思。
- Plus the incredible engineering behind the military industrial complex, so
再加上军工复合体背后令人难以 置信的工程技术，所以……
America's very good at creating- ... to the flamethrowers.
美国非常擅长制造…… 火焰喷射器。
- Yes.
- 是的。
- The technologies— ... of war, and so the lofty goals combined with
战争技术——以及 崇高的目标与
just a lot of profit that could be made on-
这其中蕴藏着巨大 的利润空间——
... the technologies of war creates a very difficult situation to navigate, where
战争技术造成了一种非常难以应对 的局面，在这种情况下，
the gap naturally widens.
差距自然而然地扩大了。
- Yeah. I don't think most of the world even believes, you know, what
- 是的。我觉得世界上大多数人 甚至都不相信，你知道，什么
American leaders say their goals are, especially when it comes to, like, war.
美国领导人表示，他们的目标 是，尤其是在战争等问题上。
Like spreading democracy? No, really?
比如传播民主？真的吗？
I remember when they were trying to convince me,
我记得他们当时试图 说服我的时候，
us, that the invasion of Afghanistan was a feminist war.
我们认为，入侵阿富汗 是一场女权主义战争。
- Oh, that was a thing, huh?
哦，原来还有这回事啊？
- Oh, yes. They were to liberate the women from the burqas or whatever, and, like,
- 哦是的。他们的使命是解放妇女，让她们 摆脱罩袍之类的束缚，然后，就像，
the news was just flooded with, like, how terrible women have it in Afghanistan.
新闻里全是关于阿富汗女性 处境有多么糟糕的报道。
It's like, you're really trying to persuade me that that's why you're
感觉你好像真的想说服我， 这就是你这么做的原因。
sending armed forces— like... Anyway.
派遣武装部队——比如……总之。
- I think there's a lot, a lot of wake-up calls about the war in Afghanistan and Iraq, where people
我认为阿富汗和伊拉克战争给人们敲响了许多警钟 ，人们在战争中遭受了巨大的痛苦。
realized that there is that gap between the rhetoric and the action.
意识到言辞和行动 之间存在差距。
And I mean, that's how, because of a lot of people waking up to that,
我的意思是，正因为很多人意识到 了这一点，情况才发生了变化。
they create pressure on the government to close that gap, and that's—
他们向政府施加压力，要求其缩小 这一差距，而这——
... how we kind of navigate this—
……我们该如何应对这种情况——
... complicated world, but it's a costly one. I mean, these, these were
……这是一个复杂的世界，但代价也 很高昂。我的意思是，这些，这些是
extremely costly wars— ... on every front, on every measure.
代价极其高昂的战争——…… 在各个方面，在各个方面。
- Yep, but the same lesson was learned in, like, the Vietnam War,
- 是的，但同样的教训在 越南战争中也吸取了。
and that was such a disaster that
那真是一场灾难……
essentially they had to switch to-- abandon the conscript army, switch to a
他们实际上不得不改变策略—— 放弃征兵制，转而采用……
professional army. And, like, it took them so long
专业军队。而且， 他们花了很长时间。
to be able to, like, wage, you know, these empire wars again
能够再次发动这些 帝国战争。
because of the sheer damage that the Vietnam War did to the credibility
因为越南战争对信誉造成 了巨大的损害。
of the military leadership in the country, right? This
指的是该国的军方 领导层，对吧？这
never happens in, like, this doesn't happen in Constantinople.
这种事绝不会发生，比如，这 种事在君士坦丁堡根本不会发生。
I can lose a w-- You can be criticized for losing a war. That's, that's one thing,
我可能会输掉一场战争——你可能会因为输掉 一场战争而受到批评。这是一件事，
right? But that you're using the army to do some, like... You know. No.
正确的？但你却利用军队去做一些事情 ，比如……你知道的。不。
- Some of this does have to do with the, the functioning of
- 其中一部分确实与 ……的运作有关
of how democracy works, the, the temporary nature of the
关于民主运作方式的， 以及民主的暂时性
leaderships, and that they're very-
领导层，而且他们非常——
... short-sighted because of the nature of the elected position or the executive.
……由于当选职位或行政 职务的性质，目光短浅。
I mean, that's what we're trying to figure out as a human civilization, how to do this for, in this
我的意思是，作为人类文明，我们正在努力弄 清楚的就是如何做到这一点，在这个过程中。
particular case, the democracy thing.
民主问题就是一个特殊的例子。
- There's no right answer, and by the way, I don't wanna be ruled by kings or monarchs or emperors
没有正确答案，而且，顺便说一句，我不 想​​被国王、君主或皇帝统治。
either. So it's like I wouldn't necessarily support that. I'm not
任何一个。所以，我未必 会支持这种做法。我不是
advocating here for anything. I'm just trying to explain. But you're exactly
在这里鼓吹任何事情。我只是想 解释一下。但你恰恰就是。
right. You know, we, we want democracy. We want leaders whom we can eject
正确的。你知道，我们，我们想要民主。我们想要 的是那种可以被我们罢免的领导人。
every four or five years-
每四五年一次
... which includes sometimes their, their, you know, teams of experts and policy
……其中有时包括他们的专家 团队和政策制定团队。
designers and whatever, and that comes at a cost too.
设计师等等，这些 也都需要成本。
- So you, you said that. You know, the Roman Empire, maybe ancient Greece,
所以，是你这么说的。你知道，罗马 帝国，或许还有古希腊，
maybe the societies before that, and now societies after that, the society
或许是之前的社会，以及 之后的社会，这个社会
we live in are very different. And so applying the lessons of history,
我们生活的世界截然不同。 因此，要吸取历史教训，
you have to be careful doing so. But are there things that are the same
这样做要小心。但是否 存在相同的事物呢？
with us humans?
和我们人类一起？
So of everything you've studied across hundreds of years and centuries,
所以，在你几百年甚至几个世纪 以来所研究的一切中，
are there aspects of human nature that kind of persist?
人性中是否存在一些 始终存在的方面？
- So look, intellectually, I have gone through,
所以你看，从理智上讲， 我已经经历过，
periods when, like when I was a grad student,
有些时期，比如我读 研究生的时候，
it was, you know, this was kind of when postmodernism, what
你知道，这就是后现代主义 兴起的时候。
we might call loosely, was kind of alive and well and not-
我们或许可以粗略地称之为，他当时还活 着，身体也很好，但又不是——
... had not yet been kicked in the pants.
……还没被踢过屁股呢。
Um, it was very common to find colleagues who
嗯，经常会遇到 这样的同事：
did not believe that there was such a thing as, let's say, human nature. In other
不相信世上存在所谓的 人性。在其他方面
words, that, let's say, the parameters of human psychology
用这些词语来形容 人类心理学的参数
are, you know, yes, there's considerable variation, but they're within a certain set
是的，你知道，确实存在相当大的差异 ，但它们都属于某个特定的范畴。
of, you know, norms. Like it's not--
你知道，就是那些规范。好像不是——
We're, we're not gonna behave like different species.
我们不会像不同物种 那样行事。
And, and that they did not believe that there
而且，他们 不相信有
was such a thing. In other words, that all of human history is essentially
确实有这么回事。换句话说 ，整个人类历史本质上是
a series of incommensurate slices of difference,
一系列不相称的 差异片段，
right? That you just couldn't go from one to the next. And I think it's a
正确的？你根本无法从一个过渡 到另一个。我认为这是一种
very problematic view for all kinds of reasons, like how, how small do you slice these
这种观点存在诸多问题，例如，你如何、如何 将这些元素细分到何种程度。
slices? I mean, it... And no, I'm with Thucydides on this one-
切片？我的意思是，它……不，在 这件事上我同意修昔底德的观点。
... Who says that, you know, more or less human beings are gonna, more or less,
谁说，你知道，人类或多或少 都会，或多或少地，
they're, they're going to be act-- Right? They love, and they hate, and they have
他们会，他们会采取行动——对吧 ？他们爱，他们恨，他们拥有
ambitions, and they're incompetent, and, you know, you find the whole
他们野心勃勃，却能力不足 ，你知道，你会发现整个
range of, you know, the whole gamut of diversity-
范围，你知道，涵盖了 多样性的方方面面——
... Pretty much in every, in any group of, of about 20 or 30 people, you're gonna
几乎在任何20到30人的群体中 ，你都会遇到这种情况。
find the same kinds of types. Now, culture then comes in and,
找到相同类型的人。现在， 文化因素就发挥作用了，
you know, tweaks things in all kinds of weird ways, and that's, as a historian, what I like
你知道，他会以各种奇特的方式对事物进行调整， 而作为一名历史学家，这正是我喜欢他的原因。
to study. I like just how the culture will modify, will set the dials, right?
学习。我喜欢这种文化变革的 方式，它会改变一切，对吧？
But that the dials go from one to 10 most people-
但大多数人认为拨盘上的 数字范围是1到10——
... it's like, yeah, yeah, yeah, I think so.
……嗯，是啊，是啊， 是啊，我也这么觉得。
- But every once in a while, there'll be a few,
但偶尔也会出现 一些例外情况。
A few folks who come along, whether it's Steve Jobs with a turtleneck
有些人会过来，比如穿着高领 毛衣的史蒂夫·乔布斯。
or some guy with a weird mustache or
或者某个留着奇怪胡子的家伙，或者
with a funny hat, and those can turn the tides of history.
一顶滑稽的帽子，就 能改变历史的走向。
- I think so. Occasionally, yes.
我也这么认为。偶尔会。
- But they're just ultra skilled at the right time- ... at the right moment.
但他们只是在关键时刻技艺 超群……在关键时刻。
- Oh, I believe that too. Oh, yeah. In other words, I don't-- I also don't
哦，我也这么认为。哦，是的。 换句话说，我不——我也不
think that, that cultural systems or ideologies are so
认为文化体系或 意识形态是如此
effectively totalitarian that they sort of colonize the mind of every person.
实际上，他们奉行极权主义，以 某种方式控制每个人的思想。
And so everyone in a culture is just like a clone. No, you
因此，同一文化中的每个人 都像克隆人一样。不，你
encounter this sometimes in, in historical scholarship.
在历史学术研究中，有时 会遇到这种情况。
And, no, I think people can sometimes just think for themselves, or they can think outside the
不，我认为人们有时可以独立思考， 或者跳出固有思维模式去思考。
box, and they can do all kinds of things. And, and I always wanna keep my
盒子，它们可以做各种各样的 事情。而且，我总是想保留我的
mind open to that possibility when I'm encountering historical agents. Yeah.
当我遇到历史代理人时，我会保持开放 的心态，接受这种可能性。是的。
- So just because you've seen this grand history,
- 仅仅因为你见证了 这段辉煌的历史，
I apologize for the ridiculous question, but if we look at the entirety of Earth,
我很抱歉问了这么个荒谬的问题 ，但如果我们纵观整个地球，
and we fast-forward a million years from now-
我们快进到一百万 年后——
- Oof
哎哟
- ... and the, and the history of life on Earth is written,
——地球生命史就这样 被书写下来了。
do you think we're at the very beginning of human history?
你认为我们现在正处于 人类历史的开端吗？
Or is, are we in the middle, or are we close to the end?
或者，我们正处于中间阶段 ，还是接近尾声？
- A million years from now. Um, I mean, I can't project or predict anything like a
一百万年后。嗯，我的意思是， 我无法预测或推断任何事情。
year from now.
一年后。
And I've become actually increasingly skeptical that I can do so at least.
而且我越来越怀疑自己是否 真的能做到这一点。
However, so I don't know about beginning, middle, and end. Um, I--
但是，我不知道开头、 中间和结尾。嗯，我——
It's easier to think in terms of like, like numbered phases.
用类似编号的阶段 来思考会更容易。
Like significantly different phases of human history.
就像人类历史上截然不同 的阶段。
And I would say we're probably in the third. I think there've only been three phases.
我认为我们大概处于第三阶段 。我认为只有三个阶段。
The first one being sort of hunter-gatherer period, which--
第一个时期有点像狩猎 采集时期，也就是——
...that lasted for the majority of human history so far.
……这种情况持续了迄今为止人类 历史的大部分时间。
Right? Then there's the agricultural revolution, basically. And
正确的？然后就是农业革命， 基本上就是这样。和
this is when you start to produce surpluses that create more complex societies.
这时，剩余产品开始出现，从而 创造出更复杂的社会。
And we're now living through a technological-- first industrial, now, you know--
我们现在正经历着一个技术变革的时代——首先 是工业变革，现在，你知道的——
- Yeah. You can throw it all in the same bucket.
- 是的。你可以把它们全 都扔进同一个桶里。
- ...all kinds of tech--
……各种技术——
- Industrial, technological.
工业、技术。
- Yeah. Industrial, technological. Which is modifying the parameters of what it
- 是的。工业、技术。这就 是对它的参数进行修改。
is that human beings can do and possibly be.
那就是人类能够做到 ，并且有可能成为。
And who knows where this will go. But I see these as very distinct,
谁知道这会发展成什么样呢？ 但我认为这两者截然不同。
In many ways. It's all human beings--
在许多方面。都是人类——
- Yeah, it's all humans--
是啊，都是人类干的——
- ...but very different contexts.
——但背景却截然不同。
- But they're almost modifying themselves. So the question is, is there a fourth?
但他们几乎正在自我改变。所以 问题是，是否存在第四个？
Is there going to be a--
是否会有——
- Yeah, I'm pretty sure there will be.
- 是的，我很确定会有的。
- And what does that look like? And is it-- When they look back at the third,
那会是什么样子呢？当他们回顾 第三点时，是不是这样？
would they still see us as the same
他们还会像以前那样看待我们吗？
as them, or would it be something completely different?
和他们一样，还是 完全不同的东西？
- Oh, no. I mean, we look back at the, you know, Romans or the Greeks or,
- 哦，不。我的意思是，我们回顾一下 古罗马人、古希腊人，或者……
like, any period in history, and we're like, "Yeah, no, I see what you're doing there.
比如历史上的任何时期，我们都会说：“ 是啊，我明白你的意思了。”
You're doing it with the, you know, the technological capabilities that you had
你是利用你所拥有的技术 能力来做这件事的。
at that time. You're doing it with the materials that you had. But I see what you're doing.
当时。你用的是手头现有的材料 。但我明白你的意图。
Yeah. You've got, you've got families, and you've got armies, and you've got, you know, you
是的。你有，你有家人，你 有军队，你还有，你知道，你
bury your dead, and you, you know."
埋葬你的死者，你，你懂的。
- Mm-hmm. But now we're increasingly actually having the
嗯。但现在我们 越来越多地真正拥有
tools and technology to modify,
用于修改的工具和技术，
to, like, deeply modify what it means to be human. Genetic engineering,
比如，从根本上改变人类存在 的意义。基因工程
brain-computer interfaces. As we understand the brain more, we can
脑机接口。随着我们对大脑 了解的加深，我们能够
modify things, expand completely. Plus artificial intelligence can expand the
修改事物，彻底扩展。此外 ，人工智能还可以扩展
knowledge base and the intelligence of the human mind. Unless
知识库和人类心智的 智慧。除非
we figure out the human mind is actually incredibly special to the
我们发现人类的思维 实际上非常特殊。
degree where it's-- At least with the tools we have this century, we cannot
至少以我们本世纪拥有的工具而 言，我们无法达到那种程度。
accomplish, we cannot achieve the level--
我们无法达到那种水平——
...of intelligence that-- general intelligence that humans have.
……人类所拥有的那 种普遍的智能。
Or one of the things we might figure out in stage four of
或者，这是我们在第四阶段 可能弄清楚的事情之一。
this long history is that the thing that makes humans
正是这段漫长的历史 造就了人类。
special is not intelligence. It's not any of the things we kind of
特殊并不等同于聪明。它不是我们 通常所说的任何一种东西。
value each other by. It's actually consciousness,
彼此尊重的方式是：实际上 ，这就是意识。
and consciousness is the thing that is very difficult to engineer.
而意识是很难人 为设计的。
And so that's the common thing from the hunter-gatherers,
这就是狩猎采集者 的共同之处。
to before the Industrial Revolution and after, is we're still the same.
工业革命前后， 我们依然如故。
We still feel like something to be alive,
我们仍然觉得自己活着是件好事，
and that's maybe an important component of what makes us fall in love with each
这或许是我们爱上彼此 的重要原因之一。
other or fear each other or suffer and all
彼此之间或互相恐惧或遭受痛苦等等
the full range of the human condition, the human experience.
人类境况的全部， 人类经验的全部。
Maybe even technology cannot, cannot replicate that, cannot
或许连科技都无法复制那 种效果，也无法做到。
modify that. Maybe that's what we learn. Or
修改一下。或许这就 是我们能学到的。或者
very possibly we destroy this whole thing.
很有可能我们会把这一切都毁掉。
'Cause now for the first time in human history, we have the tools-
因为现在，人类历史上第一次 ，我们拥有了这些工具——
- Yeah, yeah, we have
- 是的，是的，我们有
- ... unfortunately, to destroy everything.
——可惜的是，一切都将被摧毁。
- This is all very eloquent.
这一切都非常精彩。
I mean, after so many hours of my rambling about the medieval Roman
我的意思是，在我絮絮叨叨地讲了这么 多小时中​​世纪罗马之后……
Empire, you're, you're-- Yeah. I'm impressed.
帝国，你，你——是的 。我印象深刻。
- Okay. What gives you hope about this whole thing,
- 好的。是什么让你对 整件事抱有希望？
about the future of human civilization?
关于人类文明的未来？
- Look, there are a lot of challenges, right, that we, that
你看，我们面临 很多挑战，对吧？
we face and we talk about them a lot. As a historian, I see other periods that
我们经常面对和谈论这些问题。作为一 名历史学家，我认为其他时期……
were far, far more difficult
难度要大得多。
when people could have far more easily have given up hope, and sometimes did. Um,
人们本可以更容易地放弃希望 ，而且有时也确实如此。嗯，
but I don't think we're in one of those... Like, there, there's
但我认为我们并不处于那种境地 ……就像，那里，有……
some major issues like the uncertain future of technologies, what they might
一些重大问题，例如技术的未来充满 不确定性，以及它们可能带来的影响。
do, exactly what you were talking about.
就按你说的做。
I think they're solvable problems to a certain degree. Like, if we can
我认为这些问题在某种程度上是可以 解决的。比如，如果我们能
rein in some elites, a lot of these problems can be fixed, and that's not like a
约束一些精英，很多问题都能 解决，这并不像……
super difficult... I mean, it's difficult, but it's not, like, impossible.
超级难……我的意思是，确实很 难，但并非不可能。
Look, so I grew up during the Cold War. Uh,
你看，我是在冷战 时期长大的。呃，
let's just take the '80s, for example. And in the '80s, like, there was a
就拿 80 年代来说吧。到了 80 年代，就像……
pervasive sense that nuclear war could happen at any time and just
人们普遍感到核战争随时可能发生 ，而且这种感觉十分强烈。
annihilate everything, and we lived under that. If you look at the popular culture of
毁灭一切，而我们就生活在这样的 环境下。如果你看看流行文化……
the '80s, it's, like, all, like, upbeat and cheerful and naive and-
80年代，感觉一切都那么 乐观、快乐、天真——
... like, there was just no correlation. And then you move into the '90s, and the
……就好像，两者之间根本没有 相关性。然后就到了90年代，
Cold War is over, and everyone's all depressed. The music gets
冷战结束了，每个人都 情绪低落。音乐响起
all, like, whiny, and it's like, "What happened?"
大家都很爱抱怨，好像在问 ：“发生了什么事？”
There's just no correlation. Anyway, I just think that the, the, it's
两者之间根本没有相关性。总之， 我只是觉得，这个，这个是
a pervasive sense of hopelessness or, you know-
一种挥之不去的绝望感 ，或者，你知道的——
... Despair doesn't always match with,
绝望并不总是与……相符。
like, if you look at the situation objectively. I mean, yeah, it's, it, it
比如，如果你客观地看待这个问题 。我的意思是，是啊，就是它，就是它
can be pretty bad. I-- But there's so much that's happening that is good-
情况可能很糟糕。我——但是 现在发生了很多好事——
... All the time, so.
一直都是这样。
- I think this period of human history will be-- 'cause we've talked
我认为人类历史上的这一时期将会是 ——因为我们已经讨论过了
about the ups and downs of the Roman Empire. I think
讲述罗马帝国的 兴衰。我认为
unquestionably, this period in history, the 20th,
毫无疑问，历史上的这一 时期，即20世纪，
the, the late 20th century and the 21st century will be
20世纪末和 21世纪将是
seen as the flourishing of humans. So if we actually just wake up-
被视为人类的繁荣发展。所以 如果我们真的醒来——
... it's like what everything around us, by most measures of human flourishing-
……就像我们周围的一切，按照大多数 衡量人类繁荣的标准来看——
... we're doing pretty good.
我们做得相当不错。
- The amount of, like, sheer misery is probably objectively decreasing every year.
客观来说，诸如纯粹的苦难之类的 东西，其数量可能每年都在减少。
Now, you know, we're also creating problems, yes, that will cause
现在，你知道，我们也在制造问题 ，是的，这会造成……
misery down the road. Yeah, yes. But overall, I
未来的痛苦。是的， 没错。但总的来说，我
don't see a reason to despair and not have hope.
没有理由绝望，也 没有理由不抱希望。
- Yeah. We're doing okay.
- 是的。我们一切都好。
- We can do better. Let's do better. But yeah.
我们还可以做得更好。让我们 做得更好。是的。
- That's the... Let's do better. Well, Anthony, this was an incredible
——就是这样……让我们做得更好 。安东尼，这真是太棒了！
conversation. Thank you for all the
对话。感谢大家的一切
Amazing work you do and for the whirlwind journey
你的工作非常出色，也感谢 你这段旋风般的旅程。
through such a fascinating part of human history.
穿越人类历史上如此引人 入胜的篇章。
this was fun. Thank you for talking today.
这很有趣。感谢您今天与您交谈。
- It was a pleasure to be here, and thank you for, not just for
很高兴来到这里，感谢你们 ，不仅仅是因为……
inviting me, I mean, this is probably the, the largest audience, you know, I've,
邀请我，我的意思是，这可能是规模 最大的观众群，你知道，我，
I've ever spoken to but also just for giving my, my field and this,
我曾经和很多人交谈过，也只是为了感谢 他们给予我的、我的领域以及这一点，
this civilization that I study the opportunity to be seen and heard from more people.
我所研究的这个文明，给了我一个被 更多人看到和听到的机会。
I think that's very important. You've, you've done a real service here, so
我认为这非常重要。你，你在这里 做了一件非常有意义的事情。
I wanna thank you for that.
我想为此感谢你。
- Thank you.
- 谢谢。
Thanks for listening to this conversation with Anthony Kaldellis. To support this
感谢您收听与安东尼·卡尔德利斯 的对话。为了支持这一点
podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description, where you can also find
播客节目中，请查看简介中的赞助商 信息，您也可以在那里找到他们。
links to contact me, ask questions, give feedback, and so on.
联系方式，您可以在这里提问 、提供反馈等等。
And now, let me leave you with some words from Benjamin Franklin. "A great empire,
最后，我想和大家分享本杰明·富兰克林 的一段话。一个伟大的帝国，
like a great cake, is most easily diminished at the edges."
就像一块大蛋糕，最容易 被破坏的是边缘部分。
Thank you for listening, and hope to see you next time.
谢谢聆听，希望下次 还能见到您。